Hello and welcome to section for a asynchronous node.
Yes.
Now if you've read just one article about Noad you probably come across four terms a synchronous nonblocking
event based and single threaded.
All of those are accurate terms to describe node.
The problem is it usually stops there.
It's really abstract.
The goal in this section is to make that super practical by putting it all to use in our weather application.
That's the project we're going to be building in this section and to get it done.
We're going to need to make asynchronous HTP requests.
We're going to want to fetch from two API.
We'll be using Google's geo location API and we'll be using the dark sky API to take location information
like a zip code and turn that into real world current weather information.
Now in order to do all that we're going to look at callbacks promises HTP requests and more.
Let's go ahead and dive right in looking at the very basics of async programming in node