In this video you're going to make your very first request to the weather API and we're going to do
this in a static way at first meaning that it's not going to use the actual latitude and longitude for
the address you passed in.
We'll simply have a static you r l.
We'll make that request and we will explore what data we get back in the body and before we can add
anything to Adam I want to go ahead and explore this API so we can see how it works in the browser.
This is going to give us a better idea about what weather data we get back when we pass a latitude and
longitude to the API to do this.
We're going to head over to the browser and we're going to visit a couple of you ourselves.
First up let's go to forecast.
Io forecast out IOE is our regular weather Web site.
You type in your location and you get all the weather information you expect.
There's warnings there's radar.
There's the current weather and we have the weekly forecast down below.
This is similar to weather com.
But the one cool thing about forecasts daddio is that the API that powers this Web site it's actually
available to you as a developer.
You can make a request to you R-AL and you can fetch the exact same weather information.
That is exactly what we're going to do when we can explore the API by going to developer forecast.
Scott I go here we can sign up for a free developer account in order to get started making those weather
requests.
The dark sky forecast API.
It gives you 1000 free requests a day and I do not see us going over that limit after the 1000 requests
each costs a one one thousandth of a penny.
So you get 1000 requests for every penny you spend.
We're never going to go over that limit so don't even worry about it.
There is no credit card required to get started.
You'll simply get cut off after you make a thousand requests to get started.
You're going to need to register for a free account.
It's really simple.
You just need an e-mail and a password.
I already have an account so I'm going to log in take a moment to keep watching the video while I pull
up the dashboard.
Now I'd like you to pause the video go back and register your account.
And when you get to this screen once you have your account created and you're logged in you can go ahead
and click play and we'll pick up where we left off.
Take a moment to pause the video.
When you're done click play.
All right.
I'm going to assume that you've created an account and that you're looking at the dashboard that I see
the only piece of information we need from this page is our API key the API key is like a password.
It's going to be part of the you are as we request and it's going to help forecast out.
So keep track of how many requests we make a day.
You can see I've used 10 of my requests.
I still have nine hundred and ninety you left for today which is fantastic.
Now I'm going to take this API key and paste it inside of atoms so I have it accessible a little later
on.
Excellent.
The next thing we're going to do is explore the documentation the actual real structure we need to provide
in order to fetch the weather for a given latitude and longitude.
We can get that by scrolling up to the top and going to the API docs link.
Here we have a u r l this u r l is exactly what we need to make a request to in order to fetch that
data before we add this you are all into our app and use the request library.
I simply want to copy it and paste it into a new tab.
I'm not going to enter just yet because we do need to swap out some of this information.
For example we have our API key that needs to get replaced.
We also have latitude and longitude of both of those need to get replaced with real data.
Let's get started with that API key first since we already copy and paste the inside of atom.
I'm going to grab the API key copy it and replace the letters API key with the actual value.
Next up I can grab a set of long new tude and latitude coordinates.
I'm going to do that over inside the terminal by running our app node opt out.
Yes.
And for the address I'm going to use my zip 1 9 1 4 6.
Go ahead and use your current location so you can fetch the latitude and longitude coordinates.
Next up I'm going to start copying these over into the U R L where they belong.
The latitude goes between the forward slash and the comma.
Next up is the long itude and that is going to go after the comma minus 75 with a bunch of nines sets
right here.
Once you have a real u r l with all of those three pieces of info swapped out for actual info you can
make the request and what you can get back is the forecast information.
Now remember I'm using Jason view which is why mine might look a little different from yours.
I highly recommend installing it.
Now the data we get back it is overwhelming.
If you start scrolling down there is essentially an infinite amount of data.
We have a forecast by the minute we have forecasts by the hour by the week by the day all sorts of information.
It's really useful but it's also super overwhelming in this section.
We're just going to be using this first object currently this stores all of the current weather information
things like the current summary which has clear the temperature the precipitation probability the humidity
a lot of really useful information is sitting right in here.
In this case what we really care about is the temperature.
The current temperature in Philadelphia this morning is eighty four point nine five degrees.
It's going to get up to 100 so it's definitely going to be a hot one.
It already feels like 90.
This is the kind of information we want to use inside of our application when someone searches for the
weather in a given location.
Now in order to play around with this we're going to take this exact same you are Al a static you are
l and we're going to make a request over an X.
Yes.
And that's actually going to be your challenge for the video.
What I want you to do first is do a little setup work inside of app.
Yes I'm going to comment out everything we have so far and what you're going to do down below our API
key is make a call to request requesting this exact you are out just like we did for the geocoder API
in the beginning before we made it dynamic.
Then you're going to print out the body.
Currently temperature property to the screen.
So when I run the app I'll see the current temperature for whatever latitude and longitude that used
in this case.
It's a static latitude and longitude representing Philadelphia.
So take a moment to import request in this file make the request and print the current temperature to
the screen.
Once you have that temperature printing test it make sure it actually prints make sure the number looks
right and then you can go ahead and click play.
All right.
How'd you do.
Hopefully you were able to make that request and get the temperature showing up to the screen in order
to get started.
I'm going to in request.
Now we had it in this file before and then we removed it but we're going to add it back once again.
I'm going to add it right here.
By creating a contest called request and loading it in concert request equals require request.
Perfect.
Now we can go ahead and make the actual request just like we did for the geocoder API by calling request.
It's a function just like this.
We have to pass in our two arguments which you need to add for the challenge.
The options object is the first one and the second one is the arrow function.
This is our callback function that gets fired once the HTP request finishes before we fill out the actual
function.
I want to go ahead and set up our options.
There's two.
You are al and Jason.
I'm going to set you are Al equal to a static string the exact you are we have over in the browser.
I'm going to copy and paste it right inside of quotes.
Then on the next line after my comma I can go ahead and set Jason equal to true telling the request
library to go ahead and parse that body as Jason which it is.
From here we can go ahead and add our callback arguments error.
Response and body.
These are the exact same three arguments we have over here for the geocoding request.
Now that you had this in place the last thing you needed to do was print the current temperature which
is available on the body using console.
Not like I'm going to use counseled that loud to print body dot currently dot temperature.
Excellent.
Now that I have the temperature printing I need to test it by running it from the terminal from the
terminal.
I'm going to rerun the previous command.
The address is not actually being used here since we commented out that code.
And what I get is eighty five point two seven.
Perfect.
Now eighty five point to seven is different from what we got over in the browser.
We have eighty four point nine five but it is the morning here and the temperature is skyrocketing as
the sun starts coming up.
Here you can see it's already gone up a fraction of a percent since I ran that previous request.
Everything looks fantastic.
We have our weather API call working inside of the application.
Now in the next few videos we're going to start putting this together.
We're going to add our request inside of the callback for geocoder address.
This is going to let us take that dynamic set of latitude and longitude coordinates the lat long for
the address used in the arguments list and fetcher the weather for that location.
That is going to create a dynamic weather application as opposed to the static one we have right now.
Before we wrap this video up I do want to add a little air handling inside of our callback function.
We're going to handle errors on the air object and we'll also handle errors that come back from the
forecast that IO servers.
First up just like we did for the geocoder API we're going to check if air exists if it does that means
that we were unable to connect to the servers so we can print a message that relays that message to
the user console that.
Something like unable to connect to forecast IO servers excellence.
Now that we've handled the general errors we can move on to a specific area that the forecast IO API
throws.
This happens when the format of the U r l the latitude and longitude is not correct.
For example if I go ahead and I delete some numbers including the comma and I hit Enter we're going
to get a 400 back a bad request.
This is the actual HTP status code.
This is Andrew with a quick update on the status code.
You should see now is a 4.
0 4 not a 400.
I'm going to address that in just a minute.
When we implement this into our code if you remember from the geolocation API we had a bodycam status
property that was either ok or zero results.
This is similar to that property only this uses the HTP mechanisms instead of some sort of custom solution
that Google used.
In our case we're going to want to check if the status code is 400.
Now if we have a bad API key I'm going to go ahead and add a couple of E's right here.
We're also going to get to 400.
So both of these errors can be handled using the same code back inside of atom.
We can handle this by checking the status code property after our IF statement closing curly brace.
I'm going to add LCF else if response dot status code this is the property we looked at when we looked
at the response argument in detail response that status code is going to be equal to 400 if something
went wrong.
And that's exactly what we're going to check for here.
If the status code is 400 we're going to print a message console log unable to fetch weather.
Awesome.
Now we've handled those two errors and we can move on to the success case.
If
response dot status code equals 200.
The status code is going to equal 200 if everything went well in that case.
We're going to print the current temperature to the screen I'm going to cut this line out and paste
it inside of the code block.
Awesome.
Andrew back again to finish off that update I alluded to earlier.
What I have here is an updated code snippet and you can actually replace everything we have in the current
callback function with this code.
Now the condition checks if there is no error and the response status code is 200.
If that's the case what do we do.
We simply print the temperature like we were doing last time that was in the if clause at the very bottom.
Now we have an ELSE case here.
So if there is an error or the status code is not at 200 we're going to go ahead and print this message
to the screen.
This is going to handle things like the server not having a network connection or 404 from an invalid
or broken.
You are out.
All right.
Use this code instead and everything should be working as expected with the latest version of the weather
API.
Now we have some error handling in place and we can go ahead and test that our app still works from
the terminal.
I'm going to rerun the previous command and I still get a temperature 85 point to it back inside of
atom.
I'm going to go ahead and trash some of the data by removing the comma saving the file and rewriting
it from the terminal this time we would expect unable to fetch it whether to print to the screen.
And when I rerun the app that is exactly what we get.
Everything looks great.
I'm going to add the comma back in and test our last part of the code.
Right here we have.
If error I can test that by removing something like the dot from forecast.
I know I can rerun the app and I see unable to connect to the forecast.
I O server all of our air handling works great.
And if there is no errors the proper temperature prints to the screen which is fantastic and that is
it for this video we now have a way to fetch the weather based off of that latitude longitude combination.
And the next video we're going to start integrating this into our app using the latitude and longitude
that comes back from the geocoder API.
I am super excited to continue on.
So stay tuned.
I will see you next time.