In this video you're going to take the code we have here that we created in the last video and break
it out into its own file similar to what we did with the geocoding API request where we call G.O. code
address instead of actually having the request call in out.
Yes that means we're going to make a new folder a new file and we'll create a function in there that
gets exported.
After that we're going to go ahead and learn how to chain callbacks together.
So when we get that address from the terminal we can convert that into coordinates and we can take those
coordinates and convert them into temperature information or whatever weather data we want to pull off
of the return result from the forecast API.
Now before we can dive into any of that I'm going to go ahead and create that brand new file and we'll
worry about getting this code into that function.
Then there's going to be a challenge will you'll be responsible for creating that callback before we
dive into any of that.
So let's go ahead and make the directory
the directory is going to be called the weather.
And in the weather directory we'll make a new file called weather.
Yes.
Awesome.
Now in here we can take all of the code from apt.
Yes.
Cut it out and paste it.
The only thing we need to do in order to take this and convert it to what we actually need is to create
that function that's going to get exported and then we can move our call through request.
Inside of it I'm going to make a brand new function called Get weather good weather is going to take
some arguments but that will be part of the challenge.
For now I'm going to leave the arguments list empty and down below.
I'm going to take our call to request and move it inside from here.
We can go ahead and export this get weather function module DOD exports datt get weather is going to
get set equal to the get weather function that we defined up above.
Now that we have this in place we can go ahead and move into opt out just to add some stuff here.
The first thing I'm going to do is remove the API key we no longer need that and I'm going to highlight
all of the commented code and uncommented using command forward slash awesome.
Now in order to go ahead and set this challenge up I am going to import the file creating a to call
the weather and setting it equal to the require return result.
In this case we're requiring that brand new file which is created We're going to provide a relative
path forward slash because we're loading in a file that we wrote and then we're going to provide the
directory name whether followed by the file name whether dot G S And We can leave off that Jeff's extension
as we already know.
Now that we have the weather API loaded in down below we can go ahead and call it.
I'm going to comment out our call to G-code address real quick and down below we're going to go ahead
and run weather.
Dot get weather now as I mentioned there will be arguments in the future.
For now we're going to go ahead and leave them empty and we can run our file from the terminal.
This means we should see the weather printing for whatever coordinates you hardcoded in the previous
video.
In this case those coordinates are for Philadelphia.
So I'm going to go ahead and run it note amped up Jap's with no address argument.
Actually I am going to need to provide an address.
Since I haven't commented out the yard's code so I'll go ahead and do that address.
And this is just a dummy address.
I'm going to use a zip code in New Jersey from here.
If the geolocation code is never running because that is commented out.
But we are running in the weather code that got moved to the new file and we are indeed seeing a temperature
eighty point five two degrees which means that the code is properly getting executed over in the new
file.
Now your challenge for this video is going to be to take the weather function get weather and make it
similar to the Geo code address function.
And that means we're going to need to pass in some arguments including a callback function.
And over here we're going to need to use those arguments instead of a static lat long pair.
And we're also going to need to call the callback instead of using console Lague.
So let's break down what those arguments are going to be.
I'm going to leave a little comment right here.
First up you're going to want to pass in the latitude for now.
What I'd like you to do is take these static data like this number copy it and just paste it right inside
of the arguments list and you can do the same thing for longitude then you're going to go ahead and
provide a callback function and that callback function.
It's going to take the same two arguments that the geocoder Address function takes right here error
message and results the error message is going to be a string you can print to the screen and the result
is going to contain the weather which we also want to print to the screen.
Now once you have those three arguments set up here and you have your if statements that print the appropriate
data you can go ahead and actually make those changes to whether Don Jats you're going to want to take
the latitude and longitude arguments and use those inside of the you are Al you can go ahead and use
template Shearing's to do that which we've already used heavily in the course.
And then you need to use that callback function.
In this case you're going to provide an error message argument and no results argument.
Same for this one down below.
Instead of calling console log you're going to call the callback.
This time though you're going to provide undefined for the error message because in this case there
is no error.
Instead you're going to provide the results object.
Now I'd like you to print the temperature and the actual temperature Propertius that's going to let
us print a message like it is 56 in Philadelphia but it feels like 61 something along those lines.
You can explore all of the properties available and add any you like to the message but those are the
two I really want the temperature and the actual temperature.
Now that means you are going to print the object it to the screen over an x J s like we do here.
There is no need to actually print the formatted string just yet.
We'll worry about that once we integrate the entire app.
So take a moment to knock that out.
Add the three arguments here.
This is where the council calls are going to happen like they do above.
And in whether not just as you're going to remove all the council calls replacing them with callback
calls and you're going to remove the static long to toot and latitude pairs.
Take a moment to pause the video.
Knock that out.
Test it from the terminal.
Make sure you get the same data because you should be using the same static coordinates and when you're
done go ahead and click play.
Note the temperature might go up or down by a few degrees depending on what time of day you're watching
the video.
How do you do.
Hopefully you're able to wire up those arguments as well as the callback.
Now the first thing I'm going to do before I actually change the weather just code is change the amp
code.
I'm going to pass in the other two arguments the next one is going to be the other part of our coordinate
pair.
I'm going to grab that from the you I'll copy it and paste it over inside of Apple just as the second
argument.
Then I can go ahead and provide the third one which is going to be the callback function.
This function is going to get fired once the weather data comes back from the API.
I'm going to use an arrow function that's going to get those two arguments we discussed earlier.
Error message
and results the results containing any sort of temperature information we want in this case it could
be the temperature and the actual temperature.
Although you might have included others I'm going to change results to weather results and I'll talk
about why in a second.
Long story short I want to differentiate weather results from the results variable up in geocoder address.
Now obviously I did not mention this when I gave you the challenge so you can go ahead and just change
them inside of get whether we now need to use if.
Else statements in order to print the appropriate thing to the screen depending on whether or not the
error message exists.
If there is an error message we do want to go ahead and print it using console log.
In this case we're just going to pass any error message variable.
Now if there is no error message we're going to go ahead and use the weather results object will be
printing a nice formatted message a little bit later.
For now we can simply print the weather results object using that pretty printing technique we talked
about where we call Jason docstring a FI inside of console that lock here.
I'm going to provide those three arguments.
The actual object whether it results undefined for our filtering function and a number for our indentation
in this case.
I'm going to go with two.
Once again and now that we have our weather call getting called with all three arguments we can go ahead
and actually implement this inside of weather.
Yes.
To get started.
I'm going to make the L right here dynamic which means I need to replace the strings with template strings.
Very cool.
Now that I have template strings in place I can inject those arguments latitude and longitude right
in to the you are out.
Let's go ahead and define all the arguments that are getting passed in.
We had the last the long and our callback first aquil to inject that latitude.
I'm going to take the thirty nine point nine three remove it and between the forward slash and the comma
I'm going to inject it using dollar with our curly braces which lets us inject a value into our template
string.
In this case let And we can do the exact same thing right after the comma with the law intituled I'm
going to remove these static long to use of the dollar sign with our curly braces to inject the variable
into the string.
Now that you are l is dynamic the last thing we need to do inside of get whether is change or cancel
log calls to callback calls.
And now for the first two console log calls we can actually replace console dialog with callback.
And this is going to line up with the arguments that we specified over an app out G-S where the first
one is the error message and the second one is the weather results.
In this case we're passing the error message back and the second argument is undefined which it should
be.
We can do the same thing right here for unable to fetch whether now the third console call is going
to be a little more complex.
We're going to have to actually create an object instead of just passing the temperature back.
I am going to call the call back with the first argument being undefined because in this case there
is no error message.
Instead we're going to provide that whether results object.
Right here we can define all the temperature properties we like in this case I am going to define temperature
setting and equal to body ADOT currently which stores all of the current weather data temperature awesome.
Now that we have the temperature what I am missing the dot right here.
We can go ahead and provide that second property to the object which is actual temperature.
Actual temperature is going to account for things like humidity wind speed and other weather conditions.
The actual temperature data is available under a property on currently called apparent temperature.
I'm going to go ahead and provide that right here.
And as the value we're going to use the same thing this is going to be body data currently.
This gets us to the currently object just like we do for temperature and then we can provide a parent's
temperature
awesome.
Now we have two properties so we can go ahead and remove that council lock statement at a semi-colon
and now we can go ahead and run the app because everything is done.
We have our get weather function wired up both inside of the weather.
Just file and inside of actually yes.
Now once again we are still using static coordinates but this would be the last time we run the file
with that static data.
From the terminal I'm going to rerun the application and right here we get our temperature object printing
to the screen.
We have our temperature property eighty 1.6 one and we have the apparent temperature which is already
at 87 degrees and this early in the morning with this in place we're now ready to learn how to chain
our callbacks together.
That means in.
Yes we're going to take the results that come back from geocoder address pass them in to get weather
and use that to print dynamic weather for whatever address you provide over here in the terminal in
this case.
I would get the address for the town in New Jersey as opposed to the static address which I'm using
right now that latitude longitude pair is for Philadelphia to get started.
We have to take our get weather call and actually move it inside of the callback function for geocoder
address because inside this callback function is the only place we have access to the latitude and longitude
pairs.
Now if I open the geocoder Jeff's file you can remember that we get the formatted address back as the
address property we get the latitude back as latitude and longitude back as long itude.
I'm going to go ahead and start wiring this up.
First up we do need to remove the comments here and I'm going to go ahead and take the console log statement
in the success case and remove it replacing it with a console log call that's going to go ahead and
print the formatted address right here.
Console log printing results dot address.
This is going to print the address to the screen so we know exactly what address we're getting weather
data for now that we have our console log printing the address that we can go ahead and take the get
weather call.
Cut it out and move it right below that line.
And with this in place we're now really really close to actually checking the two callbacks together.
All that's left to do is take these static coordinates and replace them with the dynamic ones which
are going to be available in that results object.
The first argument is going to be results.
Latitude which we define right here on the object and the second one is going to be results long into
awesome and that's it.
This is all we need to do to take the data from geocoder code address and pass it in to get whether
this is going to create an application that prints our dynamic whether the whether for the address in
the terminal.
Now before we go ahead and run this I am going to replace the object call with a nicer and more formatted
one.
We're going to take both of the pieces of information the temperature and the apparent temperature and
use them in that string.
Which means that we can remove this console log replacing it with a different one console log.
And I am going to use template strings since I plan to inject a few variables in it's currently followed
by the temperature.
I'm going to go ahead and inject that using weather results.
Data temperature awesome.
And then I can go ahead and put a period and say something along the lines of It feels like followed
by the apparent temperature which I'm going to inject using weather results dot apparent temperature
I'm going to go ahead and put a period after that and we are done.
We don't have a council that live statement that prints the weather to the screen.
We also have one that prints the address to the screen and we have air handlers for both geocoder address
and get weather.
Let's go ahead and test this by rerunning the previous command.
I'm going to go ahead and use that same zip code 0 8 8 2 2.
When I run it I get Flemington New Jersey has the formatted address where it currently is.
Eighty one point five six but it feels like eighty five point five seven that attest that this is working.
I'm going to go ahead and type in something else inside of quotes something like Key West Florida.
And when I run this command I do indeed get Key West Florida right here as the formatted address where
it's currently 80 4.1 7 but it feels like ninety four point two degrees with this in place.
The weather application is now wired up.
We take the address we get the lat long pair using the Google geocoder API then we use our forecast
API to take that lat long pair and convert it into temperature information.
With this in place we're done for this video.
Let's take a quick moment to recap what we did.
First up we took that request call that was originally an apt.
And we moved it into weather.
Yes defining it right here.
We used a callback to pass the data from weather data I guess into ever file happened to call it.
In this case that came from Apple.
Yes.
Where we imported weather up above down below.
Inside of the callback for geocoder address we call get weather and we only call get weather in the
success case if geocoder address goes bad.
We obviously are not going to have the lat long pair and we're not going to want to take that information
and pass it to get weather because to get weather call would fail it needs the lat long in order to
work.
Now this is working great because of the Get weather call sits right here and inside of that callback
we print the weather specific information to the screen.
This is either an error message related to the weather API.
Maybe you have bad coordinate information or maybe you don't have internet access on your machine.
And then in the success case we go ahead and print the formatted message to the screen.
This is all done using callback functions and that is it for this video.
I'll see you next time where we're going to talk about a different way we can synchronize our asynchronous
code using E.S. six promises.
Stay tuned.
I will see you then