In this video you're going to learn about promises now promises are available in javascript sense yes.
Six although they have been around in third party libraries for quite some time but they finally made
their way into the core javascript language which is great because they're a really fantastic feature
promises aim to solve a lot of the problems that come up when you have a lot of asynchronous code in
your application and then make it a lot easier to manage your asynchronous computations.
Things like requesting data from a database or in the case of the weather app things like fetching data
from you are out down below.
We do a similar thing using callbacks.
Here we have two callbacks.
One that gets passed into your code address and one that gets passed in to get whether we use this to
manage our asynchronous actions in our case it's things like fetching data from an API using an HTP
request.
We can use promises in this example to make the code a lot nicer.
And that's exactly what the aim is going to be a little later.
For now though we're going to explore the very basics.
I'm not going to compare and contrast callbacks versus promises just yet because there's a lot more
subtleties than can be described without knowing exactly how promises work.
So what I'd like to do before we even talk about why they're better is go ahead and simply create some
over inside of the playground folder we're going to do that and we're going to call this file promise
dot J as before we define promises and talk about exactly how they work.
I want to go ahead and just run through a simple example because I find that is the best way to learn
just about anything going through an example and seeing how it works.
We'll learn a little bit about how promises work and we'll start to understand exactly why they're useful
why they've even come to exist inside of javascript to get started.
We're going to work through a very very basic example.
We're not going to do anything complex.
We're going to stick to the core promise features to get started with this very simple example.
I'm going to make a variable called some promise.
This is going to eventually store the promised object.
We'll be calling various methods on this to do something with the promise we're going to set the some
promise variable equal to the return result from the constructor function for promises we're going to
use the new keyword to create a new instance of a promise and then we're going to provide the thing
we want to create a new instance of promise with a capital P..
Now this promise function which is indeed a function you have to call it like one.
It takes one argument.
This argument is going to be a function I'm going to use an anonymous arrow function and inside of here
we're going to do all of the asynchronous stuff we want to do.
It's all going to be abstracted kind of like we extract the HTP request inside of this geocoder address
function.
All of the complex logic in here does indeed need to happen but the opt out file doesn't need to worry
about it.
Opt-Out J us has a very very simple statement that checks if there's an error and if there is we print
a message if there's not great we move on the same thing is going to be true with promises inside of
here.
We're going to do anything we need to do.
That's going to be involved with that asynchronous action.
This callback function is going to get called with two arguments resolve and reject.
And this is how we're going to manage the state of our promise.
When you make a promise you're making a promise you're saying hey I'm going to go off it I'm going to
fetch that Web site data for you.
Now this could go well in which case you would resolve the promise setting it state to fulfilled when
a promise is fulfilled it's gone out and it's done the thing you've expected it to do.
That could be a database request NHT request or something else completely.
Now when you call reject you're saying hey we tried to get that thing done man but we just could not.
So the promise has been considered rejected.
Those are the two states that you can set a promise to fulfilled or rejected just like inside of geocoder
Jay.
We either provide one argument for an error or we provide that second argument if things went well instead
of doing that though promises give us two functions we can call now in order to illustrate exactly how
we can use these We're going to go ahead and call resolve once again this is not asynchronous we're
not doing anything quite yet.
So all of this is going to happen in essentially real time as far as you see in the terminal.
We're going to call resolved with some data in this case I'm going to pass in a string.
Hey it worked.
Now this string this is the value the promise was fulfilled with.
This is exactly what someone is going to get back in our case.
It could be the data whether it's the results or the error message.
In our case though we're using resolve.
So this is going to be the actual data the user wanted.
When things go well this is what they expected.
Now you can only pass one argument to both resolve and reject which means if you want to provide multiple
pieces of information I recommend resolving or rejecting an object that you can set multiple properties
on.
In our case though a simple message hey it works.
We'll do the job.
Now in order to actually do something when the promise gets either resolved or rejected we need to call
a promise method called then some promise dot then and then lets us provide callback functions for both
success cases and error cases.
And this is one of the areas that callbacks differ from premises in a callback.
We had one function that fired no matter what.
And the arguments let us know whether or not things went well and promises were going to have two functions.
And that is going to be what determines whether or not things went as planned.
Now before we dive into adding two functions let's start with just one right here.
I'm going to call then passing in one function.
This function is only only only going to get called if the promise gets fulfilled meaning it works as
expected when it does it's going to get called with the value passed to resolve in our case it's a simple
message but it could be something like a user object.
In the case of a database request.
For now though we'll stick with message and we'll print that message to the screen right inside of the
callback when the promise gets fulfilled.
We're going to call cancel that log printing success and then as a second argument I'm going to print
in the actual message variable.
And now that we had a very basic premise example in place.
Let's go ahead and run it from the terminal using gnomon which we installed in the previous section
node man.
Then we're going to go into the playground folder.
Forward slash promis dot J as.
When we do this right away our app runs and right away we get success.
Hey it worked as you saw this happened instantaneously.
There was no delay because we haven't done anything asynchronously.
Now when we first explored callbacks we used set time out to simulate a delay and that's exactly what
we're going to do here right inside of our function.
I'm going to call set time out passing the two arguments the function to call after the delay and the
delay in milliseconds.
I'll go with two thousand five hundred which is two and a half seconds.
Now after those two and a half seconds are up then and only then do we want to resolve the problems.
This means that our function that when we pass into then this is not going to get called for two and
a half seconds because as we know this is not going to get called until the promise resolves.
I'm going to save the file which will restart gnomon over in the terminal you can see we have our delay
and then success.
Hey it worked.
Prints to the screen.
That two and a half second delay was caused by this set timed out and after the delay was up.
In this case it's an artificial delay.
But later it'll be a real delay.
We're able to resolve with the data.
Now there's a chance that things didn't go well.
You have to handle errors inside of your node applications.
In that case you wouldn't call resolve.
You would call reject.
Let's go ahead and comment out this resolve line and create a second one where we call Project.
I'm going to call Project much the same way I called resolve.
You have to pass in one argument and in this case a simple error message will do.
Unable to fulfill promise not one we call reject.
We're telling the promise that it has been rejected meaning the thing we tried to do did not go well
and currently we don't have an argument that handles that.
As you mentioned this function only gets called when things go as expected.
Not when we have errors.
If I save the file and rerun it over in the terminal what we're going to get is a promise that rejects
but we don't have a handler for so nothing is going to print to the screen.
And this is going to be a pretty big problem.
What we need to do is do something with that error message maybe we want to alert the user or we want
to try some other code here.
You can see that nothing printed between the restarting and the exiting in order to do something with
the error we're going to add a second argument to then this second argument.
This is what lets us handle errors in our promises.
This argument is going to get executed and called with that value in this case is our message.
I'm going to create an argument called error message right here inside of here we can do something with
that and this case will print it to the screen using console log printing error with a calling and a
space to add some nice formatting followed by the actual value that was rejected error message.
And now that we have this in place we can go ahead and refresh things by saving the file and we are
going to see our error message over in the terminal because we now have a place for it to do something.
In this case we have a place for it to print the message to the screen on able to fill promis prints
to the screen which works exactly as expected.
And this is fantastic.
We don't have a promise that can either get resolved the rejected if it gets resolved meaning the promise
was fulfilled.
We have a function that handles that if it gets rejected.
We have a function that handles that as well.
And this is one of the reasons I really love promises.
You're going to provide different functions depending on whether or not the promise got resolved the
rejected.
This lets you avoid a lot of the complex if statements inside of your code which we needed to do in.
Yes to manage whether or not the actual callback succeeded or failed.
Now inside of premise it's important to understand that you can only either resolve or reject a promise
once if you resolve a promise you can't reject it later.
And if you resolve that with one value you can't change your mind at a later point in time.
For example if I have code like this where I resolve it first and then I reject we're going to get our
success message printing to the screen and we're never going to see the error message because as I just
said you can only do one of those actions once you can either resolve wants or you can reject once you
can't do both and you can't do either twice.
This is another great advantage over callbacks.
There's nothing preventing us from accidentally calling the callback function twice.
For example I could have another line right here.
This is a more obvious example but it could easily be hidden inside of complex if else statements.
And this case our callback function and J S is indeed going to get called twice which can cause really
big problems for our program.
Inside of the promise example this callback.
It is never going to get called twice.
No matter how many times you try to call resolver reject this function is only going to get fired once
we can prove that right now by calling resolve again.
In this case when I saved the file and refresh things we're going to resolve with our message hey it
worked and we're never ever going to have the function fired a second time with no message because as
we said the promise is already resolved once you set a promise is state to either fulfilled or rejected.
You can't set it again.
Now before a promise is resolved or object function gets called a promise is in a state which is known
as pending meaning that you're waiting for information to come back or you're waiting for your async
computation to finish.
In our case while we're waiting for that weather data to come back the promise would be considered pending
and a promise is considered settled when it has been either fulfilled or rejected.
No matter which one you chose you could say that promise has settled.
Meaning that it's no longer pending in our case this would be a settled promise that was indeed fulfilled
because resolve is called right here.
So those are just a couple of the benefits of promises you don't have to worry about having callbacks
called twice.
You can provide multiple functions one for success handling and one for error handling.
It really is a fantastic utility and now that we've gone through a quick example of how promises work
going over just the very fundamentals we're going to move on to something a slightly more complex and
they'll also be a challenge for you.
So you can learn how to create your own promises that is coming up in the next video.
So stay tuned.
I will see you then.