In this video you're going to explore two more ways to use promises will create functions that take
input and return a promise and will explore promise changing which is going to let you combine multiple
promises.
Now the problem with our example is that we have this promise but it doesn't take any input and that's
most likely never going to be the case when we're using real world promises.
We're going to want to provide some input like the idea of a user to fetch from the database a u r l
to request or a partial u r l for example just the address component.
Now in order to do that we're going to have to create a function for this example.
We're going to make a variable which will be a function called a sink and that's going to be a function
that simulates a sync functionality using set time out.
And in reality it's just going to add two numbers together.
But it is going to illustrate exactly what we need to do later in the section to get our weather app
using promises.
Now in here we are going to take two arguments A and B and what we're going to do is return a promise.
So whoever calls this method async and they can pass in input but they can also get the promise back
so they can use then to sync up and wait for it to complete.
Right here we're going to use Return to do just that.
We're going to return a new promise using the exact same new promise syntax we did when we created a
promise down low.
Now this is the same exact function so we do need to provide that constructor function that gets called
with both resolve and with reject just like this perfect.
Now we have an async function it takes two numbers and it returns a promise.
The only thing left to do inside of here is actually simulate that delay and make the call to resolve
right here.
I'm going to simulate that delay using set time out and then I'm going to go ahead and pass in my callback
function setting the delay to one and a half seconds or one thousand five hundred milliseconds in here.
Although I'm going to do is write a simple if else statement that's going to check if the type of both
of these is a number.
If it is great will resolve the value of the two numbers added.
If they're not numbers 1 or more then we're going to go ahead and reject to do that we'll use an if
statement with the type of operator if type of A is equal to number.
Here we're using typeof to get the string type for the variable.
And we're checking if it's equal to a number which is what's going to come back from type of when we
have a number.
Now if the type of A is a number and using double ends the type of B is also a number.
Then we're good to go we can go ahead and add the two up resolving the value inside of the code block
of the statement.
That's exactly what we're going to do.
We're going to resolve passing in a plus be perfect.
This is going to add the two numbers up passing in one argument to resolve.
Now this is the happy path when both A and B are indeed numbers.
If things don't go well we're going to want to go ahead and reject.
I'm going to use else to do that.
If this condition fails we're going to go ahead and reject by calling reject arguments must be numbers
awesome.
And now we have an async add function that takes two variables A and B returns a promise.
And anyone who happens to call async add can add a then call on to the return result to get that value.
Now what exactly is this going to look like to show you.
I want to comment out all of the code we have below and just below where we make a sink ad I'm going
to go ahead and actually call it.
We're going to call it like we would any other function a sink add passing in to values member this
could be a database ID or anything else for an async function in our case it's just two numbers.
I'm going to go with five and I'll go with 7.
Now the return value from the function it is a promise we could make a variable and call then on that
variable but we could also just tack then on right here and that's exactly what we're going to do when
we use promises.
We're going to tack on then passing in our callbacks.
The first one being the success case and the second one being the case here we're going to get our error
message which we can look to the screen using console dot Lague console dialog error message if one
or more of the numbers are not actually numbers.
The error function is going to fire because we called Project.
If both our numbers all we're going to do is get the result and print it to the screen console dialog.
I'll print the string results with a call in and then as the second argument I'll pass in the actual
number which is going to print it to the screen as well.
Now that we have our promise async add function in place.
Let's go ahead and test this out.
Over inside of the terminal I'm going to run gnomon to start up the app node gnomon playground forward
slash promise.
Scott Jap's perfect.
Now right away we do get that delay and the result 12 prints to the screen.
And this is fantastic.
We were able to create that function that takes that dynamic input but still returns a promise.
Now notice we've taken an async function that usually requires callbacks and we've wrapped it to use
promises.
This is a really really handy feature.
As you start using premises and node you're going to come to realize that some things do not support
promises and you'd like them to.
For example that request library we use to make our HTP requests that does not support promises natively
but you can wrap your request call inside of a promise which is what we're going to do later in the
video.
For now though we have a basic example illustrating how this works.
Now what I'd like to do is talk about promise chaining.
This is the idea of having multiple promises run in a sequence.
For example I want to take an address and convert that into coordinates and take those coordinates and
convert them into weather information.
That is an example of needing to synchronize two things and we can do that really easily using promise
chaining in order to chain your promises.
What you're going to do inside of your success call is return a new promise.
In our example we can return a new promise by calling a sink ad.
Again I'm going to call async add right here passing into arguments the result whatever the previous
promise returned and some sort of new number.
Let's go ahead and use 33.
Now what I'm doing is returning a promise so I can add my chaining onto it by calling then again that
then is going to get called after we close the closing parentheses for our previous then we're going
to tack it on right here.
And this is also going to take one or more arguments we can pass in a success handler which is going
to be a function and an error handler which will also be a function perfect.
And now that we have are then callbacks set up we can go ahead and actually fill them out.
Once again we are going to get a result here.
This is going to be the result of five plus seven which is 12 plus 33 which is going to be 45 right
here.
We can print console dialog should be 45 then we're going to go ahead and print the actual value from
the results variable.
Now our air handler is also going to be the same right here.
I'm going to have my error message and I'm going to print it to the screen using council log printing
error message.
Now what we have is some chaining.
These functions are going to fire based off the result of our first Eysenck and if it goes well the
first one will fire.
If it goes poorly the second function is going to fire our second call is going to be based off of the
async ad call where we add thirty three.
This is going to let us change the two results together and we should get 45 printing to the screen.
I'm going to go ahead and save this file which is going to restart things over inside of gnomon and
eventually we're going to get our two results the 12th and R should be 45.
Right here we get just that result 12 and should be 45 printing to the screen.
Now when it comes to error handling there are a few quirks.
So what I want to go ahead and do is simulate some errors.
First up let's go ahead and simulate an error right here with our second async add call and we know
we can do that by passing in a value that's not a number.
In this case I'm going to go ahead and wrap 33 inside of quotes.
This is going to be a string.
And our call should reject.
Now I can go ahead and save the file and we can see what happens.
Things restart.
We get our result 12 and then we get our error arguments must be numbers exactly as we expect.
This is printing right here.
Now this case works just as expected.
Instead of getting should be 45 we get our error message but things get a little trickier when something
earlier on in the promised chain and gets rejected.
Let's go ahead and swap 33 out for the number 33 then up here we're going to replace seven with the
strings 7.
This is going to cause our first promise to fail which means we'll never see the result.
We should see the error message printing to the screen but that's not what's going to happen when we
start.
We do indeed get the error message printing to the screen but then we get should be 45 is undefined.
This console dialog is running because the promised change things we've cleaned up the error because
we provided an error handler right here.
It's running the air handler.
Then it says OK things must be good.
Now we ran the air handler.
Let's go ahead and move on to the next then call calling the success case to fix this.
What we can do is actually remove both of our air handlers from both then calls and replace them with
a call at the very bottom to a different method.
Well we're going to do down here is call it dat catch the catch promise method is similar to then but
it just takes one function and this is the error handler right here.
We can specify one error handler.
If any of our promised calls fail we're going to take that error message and we're going to print it
to the screen using console dialog error.
Message.
Now I know promises can be pretty confusing at first especially when it comes to promise chaining.
I promise though.
No pun intended we are going to be using this throughout the course and things will be a lot clearer
as we start working with real world examples.
For now though if things are a little blurry that is O.
K. as long as you're starting to see exactly what we're doing we're taking the result from one promise
and we're passing it to a different one.
In this case the result works exactly as expected.
The first promise fails.
We get arguments must be numbers printed to the screen and we don't get that broken statement where
we try to print 45 but we get undefined instead using catch we can specify an error handler that's going
to fire for all of our previous failures.
And this is exactly what we want.
Now as I mentioned earlier some libraries support premises and others don't.
The request library does not.
Your challenge for this video is going to be to make a function that wraps request returning a promise
I'll give you a quick setup and then you're going to be responsible for actually filling it out in the
playground folder.
We can make a new file to store this called promise to promise haif into dot J.S. and what we're going
to do is make a function called geocoder address the geocoder address function is going to take the
plain text address and it's going to return a promise you'll be responsible for writing that code in
just a second.
I will show you how I'd like it to run by calling it down below.
Geocoder address is going to return a promise.
So if I pass in a zip code like 1 9 1 4 6 I would expect it promised to come back that I can attach
a then call to.
This is going to let me wait for that request to finish right here.
I'm going to tack on a call to then passing in my two functions.
The success handler when the promise is fulfilled and the air handler for when the promise is rejected.
Now when things go well I'm going to expect that location object with the address the latitude and the
long tattoo'd.
And when things go poorly I would expect that error message when the error message happens we'll just
print it to the screen using console log console that log error message.
And for now when things go well and the success case runs we're just going to print that entire object
using our pretty printing technique.
Dot law and then we'll call Jason docstring if I like.
We've done many times before passing into three arguments and the object undefined for the filter method
which we're never going to use in the course.
And the number two for the number of spaces we like to use as our indentation.
This is what I want you to create the function that lets this functionality work as expected.
Then call should work as typed here.
Now I'll give you a few hints on how I want you to do this.
The first thing you're going to need to do is load and request in this file since it's not here then
you're going to copy the G.O. code.
J.S. code from here take everything from the variable declaration all the way down through the closing
of the request callback parentheses.
Now inside of here you are going to have to make a few changes.
You're still going to get the address we specified that right here.
But you're no longer going to get that callback.
Instead what you're going to have is the promises resolve and reject functionality.
That means instead of calling the call back with one argument to trigger an error you'll carjacked and
instead of calling it with that second argument for the success case you're going to call resolve.
Now this also means that the request code needs to get put inside of the promise constructor function.
Kind of like we have here right here is where you're going to want to put request inside of the promise
you're returning.
Now I know this is a little open ended and I know it's a little difficult considering we just got started
with promises but they are a really important topic and I want to give you experience upfront.
Playing around with them.
So go ahead and try to knock this out if you don't get on your first try.
No problem as long as he gave an honest shot and you tried something out then that is considered a success.
You can always ask me in the queue area if you got stuck on this one.
Take a moment to pause the video.
Knock this out.
Run the code from the terminal exactly as I have here.
And when you're done click play.
How'd you do.
Hopefully you were able to add that call to request inside of geocoder address and you wrapped it in
a promise.
So the code down below worked to get started.
I'm going to go ahead and return that promise by calling return new promise passing in my constructor
function inside of here is where I'm going to add that call to request.
Let's go ahead and out on some missing semi-colons and then we can provide that the arguments resolve
and project.
Now that we have our promise set up we can go ahead and load in the request module up top creating a
constant called request and setting that equal to the return result from required request.
Next up in our list of things to do is going to be to move into the code J.S. file grab everything inside
of the function and move it over into the promise to file right here inside of the constructor.
Now from here we are mostly good to go.
We really only need to change a few things.
The first thing we need to do is replace our air handlers.
Right here we call our callback handler with one argument.
Instead what we're going to do is call reject because if this code runs we want to reject the promise.
We have the same thing right here.
We're going to call project if we get zero results.
That is indeed a failure and we do not want to pretend we succeeded.
Now down below this is where things did go well.
What we can do here is call resolve and we can also remove that first argument since as we know resolve
and reject they only take one argument.
We are able to specify multiple values though because we do resolve an object with properties on it.
Now that we have this in place we are done we can actually go ahead and save our file or rerun it over
inside of the terminal and test things out.
I'm going to save the file move into the terminal and shut down and gnomon for the promised japes file
and I'm going to run node for the promise to file.
It's in that playground folder and it's called promis hyphen to J.
Now when I run this program we're actually making that HTP request and right here you can see the data
comes back exactly as we expected.
We got our address we get our latitude and we get our long itude.
This is fantastic.
Now before we stop I do want to test out what happens when I pass in an invalid address something like
five zeros which we've used before to simulate an error.
I'm going to save the file rerun the program and right here.
Unable to find that address Prince to the screen.
And this only happens because we call project we call reject inside of the promised constructor function
down below we have our air handler which prints the message to the screen.
And this is an example of how to take a library that does not support promises and wrap it in a promise
creating a promise ready function.
In our case that function is code address.
Now in the next video we're going to take a look at a library similar to request called X-posts that
actually does support promises.
So there's no need to wrap our function calls inside of a promise.
This is going to let us simplify our code creating our promised calls really really easily.
We're going to actually rebuild the entire weather app in the next video.
So stay tuned.
I will see you then.