In this video you're going to learn how to use a library that has premises built in.
We're going to explore the X-Post library which is really similar to request although instead of using
callbacks like request does it uses promises.
So we don't have to wrap our calls in promises to get that promise functionality we're actually going
to be recreating the entire weather app in this video.
We're only going to have to write about 25 lines of code.
We'll go through the entire process taking the address getting the coordinates and then fetching the
weather to do this.
I'm going to duplicate apt.
Yes because we do configure yards in here and we're going to want to carry over that code to the new
project.
There's no need to rewrite it right here.
I'm going to duplicate app.
J.S. giving it a new name app hyphen promise.
Yes.
Inside of here before we add anything let's go ahead and read some stuff out.
I'm going to be ripping out the code and weather variable declarations we're not going to be requiring
any files.
Then I'm going to remove everything after our Yard's configuration which in this case is just our call
to geocoder address.
Excellent.
Now that we have a clean slate we can go ahead and get started by installing the new library before
we run the NPM install command.
I want to show you where you can find the documentation.
You can get it by googling NPM x x x i o s right here we have the X CEOs NPM library page where we can
view all sorts of information about it including the documentation which we have down below here you
can see some things that look familiar.
We have calls to then and catch just like we do when we use premises outside of axioms.
Over on the right hand side you can see this is a super popular library and the most recent version
is zero point 1 3.1.
That's the exact version we're going to be using.
Feel free to come back to this page when you use x Yeo's in your projects.
It is a lot of really good examples and documentation.
For now though we can install it back inside of the terminal.
I'm going to be running NPM install the library name is X-posts and I am going to specify the version
0.1 3.1 with the Save flag.
Updating the package that Chaisson file.
Now I can go ahead and run the install command which is going to install an over inside of our app promis
file we can get started by loading in X he shows up at the top.
I'm going to make a constant called X-posts setting equal to require axis just like this.
Excellent.
Now that we have this in place we can actually start making the calls down below.
And this is going to involve us pulling out some of the functionality from the geocoder and whether
file.
So what I'm going to do is close all of my files except app promise I'm gonna open up geocoder J.S.
and then I'm going to open up whether data.
Us because we are going to be pulling some of the code from here things like the u r l and some of the
error handling techniques although we talk about the differences as they come up.
The first thing we need to do is encode the address and get that G.O. code you are out.
Now this stuff happens inside of geocoder.
Yes.
So what I'm going to do is actually copy this line.
Exactly.
Where we create the encoded address and paste it over here Double-O the are the variable.
Now we do need to tweak this a little bit.
The address doesn't exist.
What we have is are the ADOT address perfect.
And now we have the encoded address.
The next thing we need to get before we can start using Access is that you are out.
We want to make the request too.
I'm going to grab that over from the geocoder japes file as well.
I'm going to take the R L from the opening ticket to the closing.
Copy and paste it over an app promise Dutch Yes.
Hear what I'm going to do is make a new variable called G.O. code.
You are l sending an equal to what I copied over from the other file.
Now we do use the encoded address variable inside of here and that's fine because it does exist right
here.
So at this point we have our G.O. code you r l and we can get started making our very first X-post request.
In this case we're going to be taking the address and getting the Vita tude and long into to make our
request down below.
We're going to call a method available on X-ers X-posts dot.
Get get is the method that lets us make our HTP get request which is exactly what we want to do here.
And it's really simple to set up when you're expecting Jason data.
All you have to do is pass in the U R L which we have in the geocoding u r l variable.
There's no need to provide any other options like a option letting it know it's Jason X-post knows how
to automatically parse our Jason data and what get returns is actually a promise which means we can
use dot and then in order to run some code when the promise gets fulfilled or rejected whether things
go well or things go poorly inside of then I'm going to go ahead and provide one function for the moment.
This is going to be the success case the success case is going to get called with one argument which
the X-ers library recommends you call response although technically you could call it anything you like.
Now here we're going to get access to all of the same information we got inside of the request library
things like our headers.
Things like response and request headers as well as the body information all sorts of useful info.
What we really need though is the response dot data property.
I'm going to go ahead and print that using console dot Lague console dialog response dot data and now
that we have this in place we can go ahead and run our app promis file passing in a valid address and
we can see what happens when we make that request over inside of the command line.
I'm going to use clear to clear the terminal output.
Then I'm going to run node app HIF and promise.
Jay asks passing in an address I'm going to use a valid address.
I'll go ahead and use 1301 Lombard Street.
Philadelphia perfect.
The request goes out and what do we get back.
We get back the results object exactly as we saw it when we used the other module.
The only difference in this case is that we're using promises built in instead of having to wrap it
in promises or using callbacks.
And this is really fantastic.
Now aside from this success handler we can also add a call to catch which is going to let us catch all
of the errors that might occur.
We're going to get the air object as the one and only argument and then we can do something with that
air object inside of here.
I'm going to kick things off by using council dot log to print the error argument.
And now we can go ahead and simulate an error by removing the dot and we can see what happens when we
run the program.
Now I'm doing this to explore the Acciona library.
I know exactly what's going to happen that's not why I'm doing it I'm doing it to show you how you should
approach new libraries when you get a new library you want to play around with all the different ways
it works what exactly comes back in that era argument when we have a request that fails.
That's important information to know.
So when you go ahead and write a real world app you can add the appropriate error handling code.
In this case if I rerun the exact same command we're going to get an error.
And as you can see there really is nothing to predict here.
We have a lot of very cryptic error codes and even the error message property which usually contains
something good does not get address info.
Then we have an error code followed by the U R L but we want to do instead is print a plain text English
message.
To do this we're going to use an if statement checking what the code property is.
This is the error code and in this case enough found we know it means it could not connect to the server
down inside of the air handler.
We can add this by having if and checking the condition if the DOT code equals the not found in upper
case if that is the case we're going to print some sort of custom message to the screen using console
that Lague console dialog unable to connect to API servers.
Excellent.
Now we have an air handler that handles this specific case so we can go ahead and remove our call to
cancel the log.
Now if we save the file and rerun things from the terminal we should get a much nicer error message
printing to the screen.
That's exactly what we get.
Unable to connect to API servers.
Now I'm going to add that back in so things start working and we can worry about the response that comes
back.
And as you remember inside of the geocoder file there was some things we needed to do.
We've already handled this error but there is still another error.
If the Bobby status property equals zero results we want to do something we want to print an error message
to do that.
But we're going to do inside of app promise is create our very own error.
We're going to throw an error inside of this function that error is going to cause all of the code after
it to not run.
And it is going to move right into the air handler down below.
Now we only want to throw an error if the status property is set to zero results.
We're going to add an if statement at the very top to check if response dot data dot status equals in
upper case zero underscore results.
If that is the case then things went bad and we do not want to move on to make their request.
We want to run our cash code down below to throw a new error that our promise can catch.
We're going to use a syntax called throw new error.
This creates and throws an error letting node know that something went wrong.
We can provide our own error message something that's readable to a user unable to find that address
should get the job done.
And this is a message that's going to let the user know exactly what went wrong.
Now in this era gets around the same code is going to run down below and Currently we only have an IF
condition that checks if the code property is enough found.
Well we're going to do is add an else clause inside of here we can print the error message which is
the string we typed up above using the message property console dialog.
The DOT message if the error code is not enough found will simply print the message to the screen.
This is going to happen if we get zero results.
So let's go ahead and simulate that to make sure the code works over in the terminal.
I'm going to go ahead and rerun it passing in a zip code at first I'm going to use a valid zip code
0 8 8 2 2 and I should get my data back and I do then I'm going to use an invalid one is 0 0 0 0 0 when
I run this request.
I do get my error.
Unable to find that address by calling throw new error we're immediately stopping the execution of this
function.
So the council laid down below never prints which is exactly what we want.
We move right on to the error code below.
Now that we have our air handler in place we can go ahead and start generating that whether you are
l in order to generate that you are out.
I'm going to go ahead and copy that you are from the weather file taking it with the ticks in place
and moving it over into the app promise file.
I'm going to make a new variable called Whether you are all setting it equal to exactly what we copied.
Now whether you are does need a few pieces of information we need that latitude and longitude.
We have two variables lat and long.
So let's go ahead and create them.
Just above getting the appropriate value from that response object var and var log.
Excellent.
Now in order to pull them off we have to go through that process of digging into the object.
We've done it before.
We're going to be looking in the response object at the data property which is similar to the body in
the other library.
Then we're going to go into results grabbing the first item accessing the geometry property then we're
going to access location dot latt.
Now we can copy what we just typed create an equal sign for the long tattoo'd variable and paste it
here replacing lat with L and G.
And now we have our lat long variables.
Now before we go ahead and make that weather request I do want to print the formatted address because
that's something the previous app did as well.
I'm going to take our consulate log down below and instead of printing response data I'm going to dive
into the data object getting the formatted address.
This is also on the results arrays.
First item and we're going to be accessing the property formatted underscore address perfect.
Now that we have our formatted address printing to the screen we can go ahead and make our second call
by returning a new promise.
This is going to let us chain these calls together.
We're going to return a call to Acciona dot get passing in the RL would justify that.
It is whether you are l.
Now that we have this call returning would you go ahead and attach another then call right between our
previous then call and catch by calling then passing in one function just like this.
This function is going to get called when the weather data comes back.
We're going to get that same response argument because we're using the same method ASIO's don't get
in out of here.
We don't have to worry about throwing any errors since we never needed to access abody property in order
to check if something went wrong with the weather request.
If this callback runs then things went right and we can go ahead and print the weather information in
order to get that done we're going to make two variables one called temperature.
This is going to get set equal to response dot data.
Then we're going to access that currently property then we're going to access temperature and we're
going to pull out a second variable the actual temperature or apparent temperature which is the property
name of our apparent temperature.
We're going to be setting this equal to response data.
Currently not apparent temperature
now that we have heard two things pulled out into variables we can go ahead and add those things inside
of a call the council land.
I chose to define two variables so I didn't have to add these two really long property statements to
the council log.
I can simply reference the variables console like.
And we're going to be using template strings here so we can inject those two values inside of quotes.
It's currently followed by the temperature I'm going to inject that right here.
Then I can add a period.
It feels like followed by the apparent temperature.
I'm going to inject that right here.
Now that we have our string printing to the screen we can go ahead and test that our app works as expected.
I'm going to save the file and over inside of the terminal I'm going to go ahead and rerun the command
two commands ago where I had a valid zip code.
When I run this we do get the weather info for Flemington New Jersey it's currently 84 degrees but it
feels like 90.
If I go ahead and run something that has a bad address I do get the error message so everything looks
great.
I'm going to test it out with one more zip code my current zip code 1 9 1 4 6.
When I run it I get the appropriate address and I get the weather info printing it to the screen.
And this is fantastic.
By using the Acciona library we're able to change promises like this without needing to do anything
too crazy.
The Acciona get method returns or promise so we can access it directly using then.
Here we use then once to do something with that geo location data.
We print the address to the screen then we return another promise where we make the request for the
weather inside of here.
Our second then call we go ahead and print the weather to the screen and we also add in a catch call
which is going to handle any errors if anything goes wrong with either of our promises or if we throw
an error like we do here catch is going to get fired printing the messages to the screen.
And this is all it takes to use X-post and set up promises for your HTP requests.
Now one reason people love promises over traditional callbacks is that instead of nesting you can simply
chain.
So your code doesn't get indented to crazy levels as we saw in app.
Yes we went a few indentation levels deep just to add to calls together if we needed to add a third.
It would have gotten even worse with promises we can keep everything at the same level keeping our code
a lot easier to maintain.
And now that you know a little bit about promises we are done with the async section.
Obviously we're not done with a sync every single thing we do throughout the rest of the sections in
this course is going to be a sink in the next section we're going to start creating web servers which
will be a saying will make API which will be a sink and will create real time socket apps which will
be a sync.
It is a critical part to node.
J.S. all we've done here is we've gone over the very basics of callbacks and promises we've gone through
a few examples creating a pretty cool weather app but now it's time to move on to creating node apps
that we deploy to servers and those servers are accessible via anybody with a web connection that is
coming up in the next section.
I am super super excited to get there.
So stay tuned.
I will see you then.