This brings us to the end of our asynchronous node section but that does not mean you have to stop building
out the weather app.
Students love adding new features.
They've said they've learned a lot doing it so I'm going to give you a couple of ideas as to what you
could do to continue on with this project.
First up you could load in more information.
The response we get back from the weather API contains a ton of stuff besides just the current temperature
which is what we use.
I like to incorporate some of that stuff in there.
Whether it's high low temperatures or chance of precipitation.
Next up would be really cool to have a default location ability.
There would be a command that lets me set a default location and then I could run the weather map with
no location argument to use that default.
I could always specify a location argument to search for whether somewhere else this would be an awesome
feature and it would work kind of similar to the Notes app where we save data to the file system.
If you do end up implementing any of these posts in the Q&A send a link to the project.
I would love to see what you built.
That's all for now.
I'll see you in the next section.