In this video you're going to create your first asynchronous nonblocking program which means your app
is going to continue to run while it waits for something else to happen.
In this case we're going to stick with a really basic example.
But in this section we're going to be building out a weather app that communicates with third party
API like the Google API and a weather API.
We're going to need to use asynchronous code to fetch data from those sources before we get into any
of that.
So in this video we're going to go over a basic example of asynchronous programming and in the next
one we're going to talk about what happens behind the scenes when you run a synchronous code.
That video coming up next we'll give you a really good idea about how your program runs.
What tools and tricks are happening behind the scenes to make it run the way it does.
For now though all we need to do is make a new folder on the desktop for this section.
I'm going to navigate onto my desktop and use M-K DVR to make a new directory and I'm going to call
this one whether an app.
All I need to do before I switch to Adam is navigate into the weather app perfect and I'm going to use
clear to clear the terminal output.
Awesome.
Now we can open up that new weather app directory inside of atom.
This is the directory we'll be using throughout this entire section in this video.
We're not going to be building out the weather app just yet.
We're going to be playing around with the async features.
So inside of weather app I want to make that playground folder.
This code is not going to be part of the weather app but it will be really useful when it comes to creating
the weather app in a couple of videos.
Now inside a playground we can go ahead and make the file for this video.
Eysenck hyphen basics.
J.S..
Awesome.
I'm going to close this untitled tab and we can get started.
To illustrate how the asynchronous programming model works we're going to get started with a really
basic example using console Lague.
Let's get started by adding a couple console dialog statements in a synchronous way.
Nothing new here.
We're going to create one at the beginning of the app that's going to say starting app and we can add
a second one to the end down below console log.
And this one will print finishing up awesome.
Now these are always going to run synchronously no matter how many times you run the program starting
app is always going to show up before finishing app in order to add some asynchronous code.
We're going to take a look at a function that node provides called set timeout set capital-T time out
said time out is a great method for illustrating the basics of nonblocking programming.
It takes two arguments.
The first one is a function.
This is going to be referred to as a callback function.
It's going to get fired after a certain amount of time and that's the second argument.
It's a number the number of milliseconds you want to wait.
So if you want to wait one second you would pass in 1000 milliseconds.
Let's go ahead and call set time out passing an arrow function as our first argument.
This is going to be the callback function.
It's not going to get fired right away.
It's going to get fired after the time out is up after are two seconds and then we can set up our second
argument which is the delay 2000 milliseconds which equals those two seconds inside of year.
We're going to do is use a console that logs so we can figure out exactly when this function fires because
the statement will print to the screen console log and something like inside of callback will get the
job done inside of callback awesome now with this in place we're actually ready to run our very first
async program.
And I'm not going to use gnomon to execute it.
I'll show you why in just a second I'm going to run this file from the terminal using the basic node
command.
Node space playground and the file inside the playground folder is a async hyphen basics.
Yes.
Now pay close attention to exactly what happens when I hit Enter right away.
Two messages show up then two seconds later our final message inside of callback prints to the screen.
Right away we got starting app basically immediately after that finishing up prints to the screen finally
inside of callback over here inside of the file this is not the order we wrote the code but it is the
order of the code executes.
In starting out prints to the screen as you expected down here we call set time out but we're not actually
telling it to wait two seconds.
We're registering a callback that's going to get fired in two seconds.
This is going to be an asynchronous callback which means that node can do other things while these two
seconds are happening.
In this case the other thing it does is it moves down to finish it up.
Now since we did register this callback by using that time out it is going to fire at some point in
time and two seconds later we do indeed see inside of callback printing to the screen.
Hopefully this makes a little bit of sense by using non-blocking I O.
We're able to wait.
In this case two seconds without preventing the rest of the program from executing.
If this was blocking we would have to wait two seconds for this code to fire.
Then finishing up would print to the screen and obviously that would not be ideal.
Now obviously this is a pretty contrived example.
We're not exactly going to be using set time out in our real world apps to create unnecessary arbitrary
delays but the principles are the same.
For example when we fetch data from the Google API we're going to need to wait about 100 to 200 milliseconds
for that data to come back and we don't want the rest of the program to just be idle it's going to continue
on.
We're going to register a callback in that callback is going to get fired once the data comes back from
the Google servers the same principles apply.
Even though what's actually happening is quite different.
Now in order to wrap this video up I want you to write another set.
Time out right here on line 7.
I want you to register a set time out that prints a message something like second set timeout works
that's going to be inside the callback.
I want you to register a delay of 0 milliseconds 0.
No delay at all.
Then go ahead and run the program from the terminal and see exactly what happens.
How to go.
Hopefully you were able to run the program and maybe you saw something that didn't quite make sense.
Let's go ahead and fill out the async basics.
Set time out.
I'm going to call set time out with my arrow function passing in a delay of 0 milliseconds.
Us inside of here.
I'm going to use cancel that log so I can see exactly when this function executes and I'm going to use
second set time out as the text.
Now that we have this in place we can go ahead and run the program over from the terminal and it's really
important to pay attention to the order the statements print.
Or on the program right away we get three statements.
And then at the very end.
Two seconds later we get our final statement.
We start with starting out which makes sense.
It's at the top then we get finishing up after finishing up we get second set time out which seems weird
because we clearly told node hey we want to run this function after 0 milliseconds which should run
it right away.
But in our example.
Second set time out printed.
After finishing up finally inside of callback printed to the screen this behavior is completely expected.
This is exactly how no jackass is supposed to operate and it's going to become a lot clearer after that
next video where I go through this example exactly showing you what happens behind the scenes.
We're going to get started with a more basic example showing you how the call stack works we'll talk
all about that in the next video.
And then we're going to go on to a more complex example like this one that has some asynchronous events
attached to it.
I promise.
The reason why second set timeout comes up after finishing up is going to be very obvious after the
next video.
I'm super excited to get to it.
So stay tuned.
I will see you then.