In the last video you ended up creating your very first asynchronous application.
But unfortunately we ended up asking more questions than we got answers to.
We don't exactly know how async programming works even though we've used it.
My goal for you in this video is to understand why the program runs the way it does.
For example why does this two second delay not prevent the rest of the app from running.
And why does a zero second delay cause the function to be executed after finishing up prints to the
screen.
These are all questions we're going to answer in this video.
This video is going to take you behind the scenes into what happens in vitæ and Noad when an async program
runs.
It's a little complex which is why I recommend multiple viewings.
I would watch it once.
Now I'd work through the weather app and I would watch it once again.
When you come back to it after having played around with a lot of async programming it's going to make
a lot more sense.
Now let's dive right into how this program runs.
We're going to start with a basic example then we'll move on to figuring out exactly what happens here.
Here is example number one on the left.
We have the code in this case a really basic synchronous example.
And on the right we have everything that happens behind the scenes the call stack our node API is the
callback queue and the event loop.
Now if you've ever read an article or watched another video on how Knode works you most likely heard
about one or more of these terms in this video we're going to be exploring how they all fit together
to create a real world working node application.
Now for our example here the first one the synchronous one all we need to worry about is the cost stack
the cost stack is part of the.
And for our synchronous example it's the only thing that's going to run.
We're not using any known API.
And we're not doing any asynchronous program.
The call stack is a really simple data structure that keeps track of program execution inside of the
8.
It keeps track of the functions currently executing and the statements that Byard the cost.
These are really simple data structure that can do two things.
One you can add something on the top of it and two you can remove the top item that is all it can do.
That means if theres an item right here and theres an item above it you can't remove the bottom item
you have to remove the top item if theres already two items and you want to add something onto it.
It has to go on the top because thats how the call stack works.
Think about it like a can of Pringles or a thing of tennis balls.
If theres already an item in there and you drop one in the item you just dropped in.
Its not going to be the bottom item its going to be the top item and you cant remove the bottom tennis
ball from a can of tennis balls.
You have to remove the one on top first.
Thats exactly how the call stack works.
Now when we start executing this program the first thing that happens is node runs the main function
the main function is that wrapper function we saw over in node.
Man that gets wrapped around all of our files when we run them through node.
In this case by telling V8 to run the main function we are starting the program.
The first thing we do in the program is we create a variable x setting an equal to one and that's the
first statement that's going to run.
Notice it comes in on top of main.
Now this statement is going to run creating the variable.
Once it's done we can remove it and move on to the next statement where we make the variable y which
gets set equal to x which is 1 plus 9 that means y is going to be equal to 10 right here we do that
and we move on to the next line the next line is or counseled that live statement cancelled that log
is going to print.
Why is ten to the screen.
We use templates strings to inject the Y variable.
Right here when we run this line it gets popped onto the stack and once it's done it gets removed.
At this point we've executed all of the statements inside of our program and the program is almost ready
to complete the main function is still running.
But since the function ends that wrapper function it implicitly returns and when it returns we remove
main from the call stack and the program is finished.
At this point our node process is closed.
Now this is a really basic example using the call stack.
We went into the main function and we moved line by line through the program.
Before we get into an async example I want to go over one that is slightly more complex.
This is example.
Here we start off by defining an add function the add function takes arguments A and B it adds them
together storing that in a variable called total and it returns total down below we add up 3 and 8 which
is 11.
Storing it in the r s variable.
Then we print out the response and that's it.
Nothing synchronous is happening.
Once again we just need the call stack.
The first thing that happens that shouldn't surprise you.
We execute the main function.
This starts the program you see right here.
Then we go ahead and run the first statement where we define the variable add and we're not actually
executing the function we're simply defining it right here.
I guess added on to the stack and we define add the next line.
Line 7.
This is where we call add storing the return value on the response variable.
When you call a function it gets added on top of the cost stack when you return from a function.
It gets removed from the call stack.
Right here we're calling a function.
So we're going to add add on to the call stack and we're going to start executing that function as we
know.
When we added main we started executing main.
When we add add we start executing at the first line inside of ADD sets the total variable equal to
a plus b which would be 11.
Then we return from the function using return total.
That's the next statement.
And when this runs and it gets removed.
So return total finishes add gets removed and then we move on to the final line in the program or console
the log statement where we print 11 to the screen.
This is going to run.
It's going to print 11 to the screen.
It's going to finish.
And now we're at the end of the main function which gets removed from the stack.
When we implicitly return and there we go.
The second example of a program running through the V-8 call stack.
Now so far we haven't used node API as the callback hewe or the event loop.
The next example we're going to use all four and right here we have our async example exactly as we
wrote it in the last video in this one we are going to be using the call stack will also be using the
node API.
The callback.
Q And the event loop.
All four of these are going to come into play for our asynchronous program know things are going to
start off as you might expect.
The first thing that happens is we run the main function by adding it onto the call stack.
This tells ideate to kick off the code over here on the left.
The first statement is really simple a council that log statement that prints starting out to the screen
that runs right away and we move on to the second statement the second statement is where things start
to get interesting and this is a call to set timeout which is indeed a node API.
It's not available inside a V-8.
It's something that node gives us access to when we call it.
We're actually registering the event callback pair over here.
The event is simply to wait two seconds and the callback is the function we provided that first argument
when we call that time out it gets registered right over here.
Now this statement is going to finish up the call stack is going to move on.
And the set time hour is going to start counting down just because this that time is counting down.
It doesn't mean the call stack can't continue to do its job.
The call stack can only run one thing at a time but we could have events waiting to get processed even
when the cost is executing.
Now the next statement that runs is the other call to set timeout.
Here we register a set time out callback function with a delay of 0 milliseconds and the exact same
thing happens.
It's a node API.
It's going to get registered over here essentially saying hey after zero seconds go ahead and execute
this callback that gets registered and the call stack removes that statement.
Now at this point let's go ahead and assume that set time out.
The one that has zero second delay finishes when it finishes.
It's not going to get executed right away.
It's going to take that call back and move it down into the callback.
Q The callback Q Is all the callback functions that are ready to get fired.
Right here we move the function down into the callback queue.
Now the callback queue is where our callback functions are going to wait.
They need to wait for the call stack to be empty when the stock is empty.
We can run the first function does another function after it.
We're going to have to wait for that first function to run before the second one does.
And this is where the event loop comes into play the event loop takes a look at the call stack.
If the call stack is not empty it doesn't do anything because it can't.
There is nothing it can do.
You can only run one thing at a time if the call stack is empty.
The event loop says Great let's go ahead and see if has anything to run right here.
There is a callback function but because we don't have an empty call stack the event loop can't run
it.
So let's move on with the example.
The next thing that happens is we run our council that lock statement which prints finishing up to the
screen.
This is the second thing that shows up in the terminal.
This statement runs our main function is complete and it gets removed from the Costic at this point
the event loop says hey I see that we have nothing in the call stack and we do have something in the
callback.
Q So let's go ahead and run that callback function is going to take the callback and move it into the
call stack.
This means the function is executing.
It's going to go ahead and run the first line which is sitting right here on line 8 counsil that log
printing.
Second set time out to the screen.
This is why a second set time out shows up after finishing up because we can't run our call back until
the call stack is complete.
Since finishing up is part of the main function it's always going to run before.
Second set timeout.
After our second set time out statement finishes the function is going to implicitly return and call
back we'll get removed from the call stack.
At this point there's nothing in the call stack and nothing in the callback.
Q But there is still something in our node API.
We still have an event listener register so the node process is not yet complete.
Two seconds later this event is going to fire and it's going to take that callback function and move
it into the callback queue it gets removed from the node API.
And it gets added to the callback queue.
At this point the event loop is going to take a look at the call stack and see it's empty then it's
going to take a quick look at the callback queue and see there is indeed something to run.
What's it going to do.
It's going to take that callback added on to the call stack and start the process of executing it.
This means we're going to run our once statement inside of callback after that finishes the callback
function implicitly returns.
And our program is complete.
This is exactly how our program ran.
This illustrates how we're able to register our events using known API.
And why when we use a set time out of zero the code doesn't run right away and needs to go through the
node API.
In through the callback queue before it can ever execute on the call stack.
Now as I mentioned in the beginning of this video the call stack the node API the callback in the event
loop are pretty confusing topics.
And the big reason they're confusing is because you never actually directly interact with them.
They're happening behind the scenes.
You're not calling the callback here you're not firing an event loop method to make these things work.
This means you're not aware they exist until someone explains them to you.
And now that you know a little bit about how our code executes behind the scenes I want you to move
on with the rest of the section and start creating that weather app that interacts with third party
API eyes when you're done with the weather app come back and give this one a second viewing.
These are topics that are really hard to grasp the first time around by writing real asynchronous code.
It's going to become a lot clearer how it works.
Then when you come back and re watch this.
My hope is that it makes more sense if you have any questions about how this works.
Please ask in the Q and A section.
It's impossible to cover everything that happens but I've tried to go through a few examples that illustrate
how the cost acq note API is the callback queue and the event loop work and that is it for this one.
I will see you next time where we start building out the weather application