In this video you're going to take an in-depth look at callback functions.
Then we're going to go ahead and use them to fetch some data from that Google geolocation API that's
going to be the API that takes an address and returns the latitude and longitude coordinates.
And this is going to be great for the weather app because the weather API we use requires those coordinates
and it returns the real time weather data.
That's stuff like the temperature the five day forecast wind speed humidity and other pieces of weather
information.
Now before we get started making that request I want to take a few moments to talk about callback functions
and we have already used them right here inside of set time out.
We used a callback function in general a callback function is defined as a function that gets passed
as an argument to another function and is executed after some of that happens.
Now this is a general definition.
There is no strict definition in javascript but it does satisfy the function in this case.
Here we have a function and we pass it as an argument to another function set time out.
And it does get executed after some event that event and being two seconds passing now the event could
be other things.
It could be a database query finishes it could be an HTP request comes back in those cases you are going
to want a callback function like the one here to do something with that data.
In the case of that time out we don't get any data back because we're not requesting any.
We're just creating an arbitrary delay.
Now before we go ahead and actually make an HDTV request to Google I want to create a callback function
example inside of the playground folder.
Let's make a new file called callbacks.
Yes inside of here we're going to create a contrived example of what a callback function would look
like behind the scenes.
We're going to be making real examples throughout the course and we'll be using dozens and dozens of
functions that require callbacks.
But for now we're going to start with something pretty simple to get started.
Let's make a variable called Get user.
This is going to be the function will define.
That's going to show you exactly what happens behind the scenes when you pass a callback to another
function the get user callback is going to be something that simulates what it would look like to fetch
a user from a database or some sort of web API.
It is going to be a function.
So we'll set it as such using aira function and it is going to take some arguments.
The first argument it's going to take is that the ID this is going to be some sort of unique number
that represents each user.
I might have an idea at 54 and you might have an idea of two thousand.
Either way we're going to need the ID to find a user.
Next up we're going to get a callback function.
This is what we're going to call later with the data with that user object.
This is exactly what happens when you pass a function to set time out the set time out function definition
looks like this.
It has a callback and it has a delay.
You take the call back and after a certain amount of time passes you call it.
In our case though we're going to switch the order with an I.D. first and the callback second.
Now we can go ahead and call this function before actually filling it out.
We're going to call get user down below on line 5 just like we did with set time out.
I'm going to call get user passing in those two arguments.
The first one is going to be some I.D. since we're faking it for now it doesn't really matter.
I'm going to go with 31.
And the second argument is going to be the function that we want to run when that user data comes back.
And this is really important.
Right here we're going to define that function.
Now the callback alone isn't really useful to being able to run this function after the user data comes
back only works if we actually get the user data.
And that's what we're going to expect right here.
We're going to expect that the user object things like ID name email password or whatever comes back
as an argument to the callback function then and here I can actually do something with that data.
I could show it on a web app I could respond to an API request or in our case I can simply print it
to the console console log using.
Now that we have the call in place let's go ahead and fill out the get user function to work like we
have it defined here.
The first thing I'm going to do is create a dummy object that's going to be that user object in the
future.
This is going to come from database queries.
But for now we'll just create a variable user setting an equal to some object.
Let's set an id property equal to whatever ID that user passes in and we'll set a name property equal
to some name.
I'm going to go ahead and use Vikram now that we have our user object what we want to do is call the
call back passing it as an argument.
Then down here we'll be able to actually run this function of printing the user to the screen in order
to do that.
We would call the callback function like any other function simply referencing it by name and adding
our parentheses like this.
Now if we call it like this we're not passing any data from get user back to the callback.
In this case we're expecting a user to get passed back which is why I'm going to specify a user right
here.
Now the naming isn't important.
I happen to call it user here here and here but I could easily call this user object and user object
here.
All that matters is the arguments position.
In this case we called the first argument and user object and the first argument passed back is indeed
that user object.
With this in place we can now run our example over in the terminal.
I'm going to run this using node.
It's in the playground folder.
And we call the file callbacks.
Yes.
When I go ahead and run the file right away our data prints to the screen.
And this is awesome.
We have created a callback function using synchronous programming.
Now as I mentioned this is still a contrived example because there is no need for a callback in this
case.
We could simply return the user object.
But in that case we wouldn't be using a callback and the whole point here is to explore what happens
behind the scenes how we actually call the function like it's passed in as an argument.
Now we can also simulate a delay using set time out.
So let's go ahead and do that before going into a real world example right here.
I'm going to use SET TIME OUT.
Just like we did before I'm going to pass an arrow function in as the first argument.
And I'm going to go ahead and set a delay of three seconds using three thousand milliseconds.
Now I can take my call back.
Call delete it from line 10 and add it inside of the callback function call back user.
Now we're not going to be responding to the get user request until three seconds have passed.
Now this is going to be more or less similar to what happens when we create real world examples of callbacks
we pass in a callback some sort of delay happens whether we're requesting from a database or from an
HTP endpoint then the callback gets fired.
If I save callbacks J.S. and to rerun it from the terminal you can see if we wait those three seconds
that's the simulated delay and then the user object prints to the screen.
This is fantastic.
This is exactly the principles that we need to understand in order to start working with callbacks and
that is exactly what we're going to start doing right now.
Now the request that we're going to be making to that geo location API it can actually be simulated
over in the browser before we ever make the request in node.
And that's exactly what I want to do to get started.
This is going to require you to type a kind of long u r l but hopefully you only have to type it once
because it will be saved in your browser history.
So follow along for just a second.
HTP ass Colan forward slash forward slash maps dot Google API is dot com.
Now we're going to go to forward's slash maps forward slash API forward slash geocoder forward slash
Jason.
That's it.
I promise you only have to type at this one time hopefully it saved in your browser history and you
can simply copy and paste it.
Now this is the actual end point and you are Al.
But we do have to specify the address for which we want to geocoder.
We're going to do that using query strings which are going to be provided right after the question mark
here.
We can set up a set of key value pairs key followed by the equal sign value and we can add multiples
using the ampersand.
Here we have two equals value two.
In our case all we need is one query string address and for the address query string we're going to
set it equal to an address.
Now I'm not using my actual address so please don't try to send me an e-mail.
They will not get to me in order to fill out that query address.
I'm going to go ahead and start typing 13:1 space Lombard Street.
Space Philadelphia now you'll notice that I am using spaces here.
I'm doing this to illustrate a point you can use spaces in the browser because it's going to automatically
convert those spaces to something else but inside of node we're going to have to take care of that ourselves
and we'll talk about that a little later.
It's super easy.
For now though we can leave the spaces in.
Hit enter and you can see they automatically get converted for us space characters get converted 2 percent
to 20 which is the encoded version of a space down below.
I have all of the data that comes back now I'm using a extension called Jason view which is available
for Chrome and Firefox.
I highly recommend installing Jason view.
You can even take a moment to pause the video install it for your browser then refresh the page and
you should see a much nicer version of your Jason data.
It lets you minimize and expand various properties and makes it super easy to navigate.
Now the data below has exactly what we need.
We have an address component's property.
We don't need that down below we have a formatted address which is really nice.
13:1 Lombard Street.
It includes the state the zip code and the country which I didn't even provide in the address query.
Down below though we have what we really came for in geometry.
We have location and this includes the latitude and longitude data.
Now what we got back from the Google Maps API request is nothing more than some Jason data which means
we can take that Jason data convert it to a javascript object and start accessing these properties in
our code.
To do this we're going to use a third party module that lets you make these HTP requests inside of your
app.
This one is called request.
You can visit it by going to NPM.
J.S. dot com forward slash package forward slash request when you visit that page you're going to see
all the documentation all the different ways you can use the request package to make your HTP requests.
For now though we're going to stick with some basic examples down below on the right hand side you can
see this is a super popular package.
It has several hundred thousand downloads in the last day which is pretty ridiculous.
In order to get started we're going to install it inside of our project and we're going to make a request
to this exact you are out to do this.
Let's go to the terminal first and install the module using and PM in it first to create that package.
Jason File.
I'm going to run NPM in it and use enter to use the defaults for every single option.
At the end I'll type yes and hit enter again.
Now that we have our package Jason File we can use NPM install followed by the module name request and
I am going to specify a version you can always find the latest version of modules on and the NPM page
if you scroll down here you can see two point seventy three point zero is the latest version.
At the current time that I'm filming so I'm going to go ahead and add that at two point seventy three
point zero.
Then I can specify the save flag because I do want to save this module in my package.
Jason File it's going to be critical for running in the weather application and now that we have the
request module installed we can go ahead and start using it over inside of them.
We're going to wrap this video up by making a request to that you R-AL in a new file in the root of
the project called app.
Yes this is going to be the starting point for the weather application the weather app is going to be
the last command line as we create in the future we'll be making the backend for web apps as well as
real time apps using socket IO.
But to illustrate asynchronous programming a command line app is the nicest way to go.
Here we have our out file and we can get started by loading in request just like we did with our other
NPM modules.
I'm going to make a constant variable.
I'm going to call it request and I'm going to set it equal to require request perfect.
Nothing here should look new.
Now what we need to do is make a request in order to do this.
We're going to have to call this request function.
Let's go ahead and call it on line 3 request.
And it takes two arguments.
The first argument is going to be an options object where we can configure all sorts of information.
We'll use that in just a second.
The second one is going to be a callback function.
This is going to get called once the data comes back from the HTP endpoint.
In our case it's going to get called once that Jason data the data right here comes back into the node
application back inside of atom we can add the arguments that are going to get passed back from request.
Now these are arguments that are outlined in the request documentation.
I'm not making up the names for these here in the docs.
You can see they call it error response and body.
That's exactly what we're going to call ours back inside an atom we can add air response and body just
like they do now.
From here we can go ahead and fill out that options object.
This is where we are going to specify the things unique to our request in this case.
One of the unique things is that you are Al that you are Al specifies exactly what you want to request.
And in our case we have that in the browser.
Let's go ahead and copy the well exactly as it appears.
Pasting it inside of the string.
You are al property.
Now that we have the U R L property in place we can Atacama at the very end and hit enter because we
are going to specify one more property.
We're going to set Jason equal to true this tells request that the data coming back is going to be Jason
data and it should go ahead and take that Jason string and convert it to an object for us that lets
us skip a step.
It's a really useful option with this in place we can now do something in the callback in the future
we'll be taking this long to toute and latitude and fetching weather.
For now we're simply going to print the body to the screen console dialog printing body right here.
I'm going to pass the body argument into console that lock.
Now that we have our very first HTP request set up and we have a callback that's going to fire when
the data comes back we can run it from the terminal to do this like you might expect.
We're going to use node and we're going to run that app file when we do this.
The file is going to start executing and there's going to be a really short delay before the body prints
to the screen.
As you saw it really wasn't that long maybe a fifth of a second maybe even less.
And when we get back is exactly what we saw in the browser.
Some of the properties like address components show object.
In this case because we're printing it to the screen but those properties do indeed exist.
We'll talk about how to get them a little later.
For now though we do have our formatted address right here.
We also have the geometry object a place id and types and this is what we're going to be using to fetch
the long 9:58 the latitude and the later to fetch the weather data.
A few students reported getting the following error in the response body over queery limit.
If you're seeing that or if you are not I recommend heading over to this u r l this you or I was going
to redirect you to a course Q&amp;A on you to me in one of my replies.
I list out a guide for how you can fix it.
Now I recommend doing this even if you're not getting any error right now and you are seeing the expected
output that's going to make sure that you don't run into any issues in the next several videos.
All right.
That's it for the update.
Let's dive back into the regular video now that we have this in place.
We are done.
We have the first step of the process complete.
We've made a request to the Google geolocation API and we're getting the data back.
We'll continue on creating the weather app in the next video.
I am super excited to get started building it out.
So stay tuned.
I will see you soon.