It before we continue on learning about HTP and what exactly is in sign of error response and body.
I want to take a quick moment to talk about how we can pretty print and object to the screen as we saw
in the last video when we ran our app with node apps.
Yes the body prints to the screen.
But since there is a lot of objects nested inside of each other javascript starts clipping them.
It tells us an object is here but we don't get to see exactly what their properties are.
This takes place for address components geometry and types.
Obviously this is not useful.
We want to do is see exactly what's in the object to explore all of the properties.
We're going to look at a way to pretty print are objects.
This is going to require a really simple function call to a function We've actually already used.
Jason docstring define Jason dot string of phi.
This is the function that takes your javascript objects which body is remember we use Jason true to
tell request to take the Jason and convert it into an object right here.
We're taking that object passing it in and providing the arguments.
Now this is how we've usually used Jason docstring if to find the past we provided just one argument
the object we want to string if I in this case we're going to provide a couple of other arguments.
The next argument is used to filter out properties.
We don't want to use that.
I've actually never used it.
It's usually useless.
So I'm going to leave it as undefined for the moment.
The reason we need to provide that is because the third argument is the thing we want the third argument
is going to format the Jason and you're going to specify exactly how many spaces you want to use per
indentation.
You could go with two or four depending on your preference.
I'm going to go ahead and pick to save the file and rerun it from the terminal when we string a fire
Jason and print it to the screen as you're going to see it when you rerun the app.
We get the entire object showing up.
None of the properties are clipped off.
Here we can see the entire address components array everything shows up.
No matter how complex it is down below we have our geometry object.
This is where our latitude and longitude are stored.
And you can see them right here also down below that we have our types which was cut off before even
though it was an array with one item which is a string.
Now that you know had a pretty print your objects that's going to be a lot easier to scan data inside
of the council.
None of your properties are going to get clipped and it's formatted in a way that makes the data a lot
more readable.
And that is it for this one.
Just a quick tip on how you can format objects when you want to print them to the con..
Stay tuned.
We'll see you next time as we start diving into HTP and all of the arguments in our Colbeck