In the last two videos you learned how to use the request module to make an HTP request for some information.
In our case you Arel we requested was a Google Maps geocoding you RL and we passed in the address we
want the latitude and the long to 3:58 then we use a callback function which got fired once that data
came back.
Now the goal in that video is not to understand how HTP works or what exactly these arguments error
response and body are.
The goal was to come up with a real world example of a callback as opposed to the contrived examples
that we've been using so far with set time out in our case.
We had a real callback that got fired once the HTP request came back from the Google servers we were
able to print the body and we saw exactly what we had over in the web site.
In this video we're going to dive into those arguments.
So let's kick things off by taking a look at the body.
This is the third argument that request passes to the callback.
And now the body is not something unique to the request module body is part of HTP which stands for
the hyper text transfer protocol when you make a request to a Web site.
The data that comes back that is the body of the request and you've actually used the body about a million
times in your life every single time you request a u r l in the browser.
What you get rendered inside of the screen that is the body in the case of NPM and s dot com the body
that comes back is an HTL web page that the browser knows how to render the body could also be some
Jason information which is the case in our Google API request.
Either way the body is the core data that comes back from the server.
In our case the body stores all of the location information we need and we're going to be using that
to pull out the formatted address the latitude and longitude in just a second before we go ahead and
dive into the body.
I want to talk about the response object.
We can go ahead and look at it by printing it to the screen.
I'm going to swap out body in the console lock statement for response.
Then I'm going to save the file and rerun things over inside of the terminal by running node app.
Yes we're going to get that little delay while we wait for the request to come back and then we get
a really complex object.
If you scroll up to the top where we originally made the request you can see the first thing we have
in the response object is a status code the status code is something that comes back from an age TTP
request it's part of the response.
And that tells you exactly how the request went.
In this case a 200 means everything went great and you're probably familiar with some status codes like
404 which means the page was not found or 500 which means the server crashed.
Now there are other body codes we'll be using throughout the course like I mentioned.
We're going to be making our very own HTP API so you'll become intimately familiar with how to set and
use status codes for now all we care about is that the status code is at 200.
That means things went well.
Next up on the response object we actually have the body repeated because it is part of the response.
Since it's the most useful piece of information that comes back the request module developers chose
to make it the third argument.
Although you could access it using response dot body as you can clearly see here in here we have all
of the information we've already looked at address components formatted address geometry so on and so
forth down below body we have something called headers no headers are part of the HTP protocol.
They are key value pairs as you can see here where the key and the value are both strings.
They can be sent in their request.
That's from the node server to the Google API server and in the response from the Google API server
back into the node server.
Headers are fantastic because a lot of built in ones like content type the content type is H.T. a model
for a web site and in our case it's application forward slash.
Jason we'll talk about header's more in the future.
Most of these headers are not important to our application and most we're never ever gonna use when
we go on and create our own API later in the course you'll be setting your own headers.
So you'll be intimately familiar with how these headers work.
For now we can ignore them completely.
All I want you to know is that the headers you see here these are headers set by Google they're headers
that come back from their servers down below headers.
We have the request object this store some information about the request that was made here you can
see the protocol HTP Yes the host that Google API is dot com Web site and all sorts of other things
like the address parameters the entire you are l everything about the request is stored right here down
below.
We also have our own headers and these are headers that were sent from node to the Google API.
Now you're probably wondering how this even got set.
Well this Hetter got set.
When we added Jason true to the options object we told request we want Jason back and request went on
to tell Google hey we want to accept some Jason data back.
So if you can work with that format and go ahead and send it back and that's exactly what Google did.
This is the response object.
It stores information about the response and about their request.
Well we're not going to be using most of the things inside of the response argument.
It is important to know they exist.
So if you ever need to access them you know where they live.
We'll be using some of this information throughout the course.
But as I mentioned most of it is not necessary for the most part.
We're going to be accessing the body.
One thing we are going to be using is the thing at the very top that status in our case it was 200.
This is going to be important when we're making sure that that request was fulfilled successfully.
If we can't fetch the location if we get an error in the status code we do not want to go on to try
to affect the weather because obviously we don't have the latitude and longitude information.
We're not going to worry about the status code errors yet that is going to come up soon.
For now we can move on to the final thing which is air.
Now as I just mentioned the status code can reveal that an error occurred but this is going to be an
error on the Google servers.
Maybe the Google servers have a syntax error and their program is crashing.
Maybe the data that you sent is invalid.
For example you sent an address that doesn't exist.
Those errors are going to become evident via the status code.
What the error argument contains is errors related to the process of even making that HTP request.
For example maybe the domain is wrong.
If I delete x and the dot with G.
Oh I get it you are Alabam most likely doesn't exist in this case.
I'm going to get an error in the air object because node cannot make the HTP request it can't even connect
it to the server.
I could also get an error right here if the machine on making the request from does not have access
to the Internet is going to try to reach out to the Google servers.
That is going to fail and we're going to get an error.
Now we can check out the error object by deleting those pieces of text from the U R L and making a request.
In this case I'm going to swap out response for error.
Awesome.
Now over inside of the terminal I can scroll to the bottom.
Rerun the application by running node app.
Yes and we can see exactly what we get back when I make the bad request.
We get our air object printing to the screen and the thing we really care about is the error code.
In this case we have the e not found error.
And this means that our local machine could not connect to the host provided in this case map.
Google's API a dot com it doesn't exist.
So we're getting an error rate here.
These are going to be those systems as I talked about things like your program not being able to connect
to the Internet or the domain not being found.
This is also going to be really important when it comes to creating some error handling for our application.
There is a chance that the user's machine won't be connected to the Internet and we're going to want
to make sure to take the appropriate actions and we'll do that depending on what is inside of the air
object.
For now though we can fix the U R L setting it back to maps dot Google API I's dot com.
Now if we make the exact same request by using the up error key and the Enter key the request error
object it's going to be empty.
Here you can see no prints to the screen.
In this case everything went great.
There was no error.
It was able to successfully fetch the data which it should because we have a valid u r l that is a quick
rundown of the body the response and the error argument.
We are going to be using them in more detail as we add error handling.
I wanted to give you a quick overview of exactly what is inside of each.
To wrap this video up we're going to print some data from the body to the screen.
I'm going to get started by printing the formatted address and you are going to be responsible for printing
both the latitude and longitude
in order to figure out exactly where formatted address is I'm going to go to the browser and use Jason
view one of the reasons I love Jason view as it makes it easy to see where inside of the response that
data you have highlighted lives at the bottom you can see that little blue bar shows up when I highlight
over items and it changes as I switch items for formatted address.
For example we access the results property result is an array.
In the case of most addresses you're only going to get one result.
We're going to use the first result every time.
So we have the index of 0.
Then it's the dot formatted on your score address property that does exactly what we need to type over
inside of our node code back inside of atom.
I'm going to delete this line and replace it with a new console log statement console dock log and I'm
going to use template strings to add some nice formatting to this.
I'm going to say address with a colon and a space.
Then I'm going to inject the address using the dollar sign on the curly braces.
We're going to access the body then we're going to access results.
Then we're going to access the first item in the results array followed by formatted address dot formatted
underscore address.
With this in place I can now add a semi-colon at the end and save the file over inside of the terminal.
I can rerun the application and this time around we get our address printing to the screen 3 0 1 Lombard
Street Philadelphia P.A. 1 9 1 4 7 in the US.
Now that we have the address printed to the screen what I would like you to do is print both the latitude
and longitude.
Now there are a few variations of that.
There's the bounds the northeast and the Southwest bounds.
We don't care about that.
What we want is this location property is latitude and longitude.
That means you're going to go into geometry.
You're going to go into location and you're going to grab those two props used to console dialogue statements
one for latitude and one for long tattoo'd printing both to the screen.
When you're done.
Go ahead and rerun the app from the terminal.
Make sure you see the formatted address and make sure you get the right latitude and longitude printing
to the terminal.
If you do then you are done the challenge and you can go ahead and click play.
Take a moment pause the video.
Knock that one out and click play.
How'd you do.
Hopefully you were able to print both the latitude and longitude to the screen in order to get started
over inside of Adam.
I'm going to add another console log line right below console log.
And I'm going to use template strings once again to add some nice formatting.
Let's print the latitude first latitude followed by a colon then I can inject my variable using the
dollar sign with the curly braces.
And in this case the variable we want is on the body.
It's also in that first results item results at the index of zero.
This time we're not going to be going into formatted addresses.
We're going to be going into geometry from geometry we're going to grab the location prop it in there
is the latitude dot laughed.
Awesome.
Now that we have this in place we can do the exact same thing for long and I'm going to add another
console log line right below console that log.
I'm going to use template strings once again typing long into first.
After that we're going to put a colon and then we'll inject the value in this case the value was on
the body.
It's in that same results item.
The first one we're going to go into geometry location again instead of last.
We're going to access dot LNG then we can go ahead and get a semi-colon at the end and save the file.
Now that we're done updating the opt out.
Yes part of the challenge we can finish up by testing it from the terminal.
I'm going to rerun the previous command and right here you can see we have the latitude thirty nine
point nine four.
And the long itude minus seventy five point one six printing to the screen.
And these are the exact same values we have over inside of the Chrome browser thirty nine nine for minus
75 16.
With this in place we've now successfully pulled off the data we need to make that request to the weather
API in the next video.
We're going to go ahead and add some error handling to this callback because that's going to be really
important for our age to requests.
There's a chance that things go wrong and when they do inside of the callback we're going to want to
handle that error by printing a nice error message to the screen.
So stay tuned.
I am super excited to continue building the weather application.
I will see you next time.