In this video you're going to learn how to set up your eggs for the weather app and you're going to
learn how to include user input and that is going to be really important for our application.
The user is not going to type their encoded address into the terminal.
Instead they're going to be typing in a plain text address like 13:1 space Lombard space street.
Now this is not going to work for are you rl.
We need to encode those special characters like the space replacing them with percent 20 now percent
20 is the special character for the space.
Other special characters have different encoding values.
We're going to learn how to encode and decode strings so we can set up this you r l to be dynamic.
It's going to be based off of the address provided in the terminal.
That's all going to happen in this video.
By the end you'll be able to type in any address you like and you'll see the formatted address the latitude
and longitude before we can get started doing any encoding.
We have to get the address from the user and before we can set up yours we have to install it.
So that's exactly what I want to do first in the terminal.
I'm going to run NPM install the module name is yours and we're looking for a version four point eight
point one which is the latest version at the time of the filming.
I am going to use the save flag to run this installation.
Now the save flag is great because as you remember it updates the package that Jason File and that's
exactly what we want.
This means we can get rid of the node modules folder which takes up a ton of space but we can always
regenerate it using NPM and stuff.
If you're on NPM install of out anything else no other module names or flags.
It's going to dig through that package.
Jason File looking for all the modules to install and it'll install them recreating your node modules
folder exactly as you left it.
Now we don't have to wait for this installation to complete because we still have quite a bit of configuration
to do so over and out.
Yes we can get started by first loading in yards.
I'm going to make a constant called yards setting equal to require yards just like this.
Now we can go ahead and actually do that configuration down below.
We're going to make another constant called Arvie.
This is going to be the object that stores the final parsed output that's going to take the input from
the process variable pass it through yards and the result will be right here.
This is going to get set equal to yards.
And now we can start adding some calls.
Now when we created the Notes app we had various commands you could add a no.
And that required some arguments you could list a note which required just the title you could list
all notes which didn't require any arguments and we specified all of that inside of Yorke's for the
weather app.
The configuration is going to be a lot simpler.
There is no command the only command would be get weather but if we only have one.
Why even make someone type it.
In our case when a user wants to fetch the weather all they're going to do is type node apt J.S. followed
by the address flag just like this.
Then they can type their address inside of quotes.
In my case it could be something like 1801 Lombard Street.
Once again that is not my real address but this is exactly how the command is going to get executed.
There's no need for an actual command like fetch whether we go right from the file name right into our
arguments to configure that.
Things are going to look a little different but still pretty similar.
I'm going to get started by calling dot options which is going to let us configure some top level options
in our case.
We're going to pass in an object where we can figure all of the options we need.
Now I'm going to format this like I do for all of my chained calls where I move the call to the next
line and I indented like this.
Now we can set up our options and in this case we just have one.
It's going to be that a option is going to be short for address.
I could either type address here and I could put in the alias or I could put a here and type address
in the alias.
In this case I'm going to put a right here.
Next up I can go ahead and provide that empty object and we're going to go through the same exact options
we used inside of the notes app.
We are going to demand it.
If you're going to fetch the whether we need an address to fetch the weather for.
So all set demand equal to true.
Next up we can set an alias.
I'm going to set alias equal to address and finally we'll set describe we can describe anything we think
would be useful in this case.
I'm going to go with address to fetch whether for perfect.
No these are the three options we provided for the Notes app.
But I'm going to add a fourth one to make our yagis configuration for the weather app even more foolproof.
This is going to be an option called string.
Now string takes a boolean either true or false.
In our case we want true to be the value.
This tells yardages to always always parse the A or address argument as a string as opposed to something
else like a number or a boolean.
Back in the terminal if I were to delete the actual string address yards would still accept this.
It would just think I'm trying to add a boolean flag which could be useful in some situations.
For example do I want to fetch in Celsius or Fahrenheit.
But in our case we don't need any sort of true false flag.
We need some data.
So we're going to set string to true to make sure we get that data.
Now that we have our options configuration in place we can go ahead and out a couple of other calls
that we've explored.
I'm going to add help calling it like this which adds the help flag.
This is really useful especially when someone is first using a command and then we can access our Wii
which takes all of this configuration runs it through our arguments and stores the result right here
in the variable.
Now with the help method ads that help argument we can also add an alias for it right afterwards by
calling dot alias now that alias takes two arguments.
The actual argument that you want to set an alias for the alias.
In our case we already have help registered it gets registered when we call help and we're going to
set an alias which will just be the letter H.
Awesome.
Now we have all sorts of really great configurations set up for the weather app for example.
Over inside of the terminal I can now run help.
I can see all of the help information for this application.
I could also use the shortcut hyphen H and I get the exact same data back.
Now the address is also getting passed through but we don't print it to the screen so I'm going to take
a quick moment to do just that right after the configuration.
Let's use console dialog to print the entire the variable to the screen.
This is going to include everything that got parsed by Yorke's.
Let's go ahead and rerun it this time passing in an address.
I'm going to use the a flag and specifying something like 13 0 1 Lombard Street.
Closing the quotes and hitting enter.
When I do this we get our object and right here we have 13 0 1 Lombard Street the plain text address.
Now down below we happened to fetch the latitude and longitude for that address but that's just because
we have it hardcoded right here.
I am going to still need to make some changes in order to get the address.
The one that got typed inside of the argument to be the address that shows up right here to explore
how to encode and decode strings.
We're going to head into the terminal I'm going to clear the screen using clear.
And then we can boot up a node process by typing node.
We've explored this in the past right and here we can run any statements we like when I'm exploring
a really basic node or javascript feature I'd like to mess around in here first and then I go ahead
and add it into the actual application.
In our case we're going to look at two functions in code.
You are a component and decode you are-I component.
Let's get started with encoding first the method itself is called in code you are a component in code.
You are I in upper case component and it takes just one argument the string you want to code.
In our case that string is going to be the address something like 13:1 space Lombard space street space
Philadelphia.
When I actually run this address through code you or I component by hitting enter I get the uncoated
version back right here.
You can see all of the spaces like the space between 13:1 and Lombard have been replaced with their
uncoded character and for the case of the space it is percent 20.
And this is fantastic bypassing our string through encode you or I component.
We're creating something that's ready to get injected right into the R L so we can fire off that dynamic
request.
Now the alternative to encode you are i component is de-code you or I.
Component de-code you are by component.
This is going to take an encoded string like the one here and take all the special characters like percent
20 and convert them back into their original values.
In this case space inside of de-code you or I component.
Once again we're just going to pass a string.
Let's go ahead and type our first and last name.
In my case it's Andrew.
And instead of a space between them I'm going to add percent 20 which we know is the encoded character
first space and since we're trying to decode something it's important to have some encoded characters
in here.
Once yours looks like this with your first and last name you can go ahead and enter.
And what we get back is the decoded version right here.
I have Andrew Mead with the percent 20 being replaced by the space.
Exactly what we expected.
This is how we can encode and decode you are the components in our app.
Now your challenge for this video is going to be this what I want you to do is pull the address out
of our Wii.
We already saw that it's there.
I want you to encode it and I want you to inject it right here replacing everything that I currently
have highlighted.
This is going to essentially create that dynamic request we've been talking about.
Someone will be able to type in any address they want whether it's an address or a zip code or city
state combination and they'll be able to fetch the formatted address the latitude and longitude take
a few moments to knock that out.
You're going to need to call in code.
You are component passing in the address then you're going to want to inject that result right here
inside of the you are l.
You can use template strings.
Currently we're using regular strings but feel free to swap that out when you're done.
Go ahead and test it.
Type in your home address over in the terminal.
Make sure you get the proper formatted address as well as a latitude and longitude and then try somewhere
else completely to make sure you get a different result when you're done.
You can go ahead and click play how to go.
Hopefully you were able to encode that address get it to show up inside of that you are.
And then you were able to make dynamic location requests from the terminal in order to get started.
The first thing I'm going to do is get the encoded address.
Let's make a variable called in coded address where we can store that result.
I'm going to set this equal to the return value from the method we just explore it over in the terminal
in code you are-I component.
This is going to take the plaintext address and return the encoded result.
Now we do need to pass the string and we have that available on the dot which is the alias.
You could also use that address both are going to work the same.
I'm going to go ahead and use dot address.
And now we have that encoded result.
All that's left to do is inject it inside of the u r l string.
Currently I'm using a regular string.
I'm going to swap this out for a template string so I can inject a variable inside of it.
Perfect.
Now that we have a template string we can highlight the static address which ends at Philadelphia and
goes up to the equal sign and remove it.
And then here instead of typing in a static address we can inject the dynamic variable inside of my
curly braces encoded address excellence.
With this in place we are now done.
We get the address from the terminal.
We encode it and we use that inside of our geocoder call.
So the formatted address latitude and longitude should match up over inside the terminal.
I'm going to shut down node by using Control-C twice and use clear to clear the terminal output.
Then I can go ahead and run our app using node X..
J.S. passing in either the A or address flag.
In this case I'll just use a then I can go ahead and type in an address.
I'm going to use one of my old addresses 16:14 South Broad Street Philadelphia awesome.
Go ahead and type in either your current or a previous address when you run it you should have that
small delay while we fetch the data from the geocoding you are out.
And in this case you can see it's actually taking a little longer than I would expect about three or
four seconds.
But we do get the address back.
Here we have the formatted address with the proper zip codes state and country.
We also have the latitude and longitude showing up great over inside of the terminal.
I'm going to try a few other examples.
For example a town in Pennsylvania called Chalfont.
I can type in Chalfont P-A which is not a complete address but the Google geocoder API is going to convert
it into the closest thing in this case.
It's essentially the address of the town Chalfont P-A 1 8 9 1 for the zip with the State USA right here.
I have the general latitude and longitude data for that town.
And this is going to be fine for fetching weather data.
The weather isn't exactly changing when you move a few blocks over.
Now that we have our data coming in dynamically we are able to move on to the next video where we're
going to handle a lot of the errors that happen inside of callbacks.
There's a lot of ways this request can go wrong and we're going to want to figure out how to recover
from errors inside of our callback functions when we're doing asynchronous programming.
That's the topic of the next video.
So stay tuned.
I will see you soon.