In this video you're going to learn how to handle errors inside of your callback functions because as
you might guess things don't always go as planned.
For example the current version of the app has a few really big flaws.
If I try to fetch whether using node apps out Jap's with a flag for a zip that doesn't exist like 0
0 0 0 0 the program crashes which is a really big problem it's going off it's fetching the data.
Eventually that data is going to come back and we get an error is trying to fetch properties that don't
exist body results zero formatted address is not a real property.
And this is a big problem.
Our current callback it expects everything went as planned.
It doesn't care about the error object doesn't look at response codes it just starts printing the data
that it wants.
This is the happy path.
But in a real world node apps we have to handle errors as well.
Otherwise the applications are going to become really useless and a user can get super frustrated when
things don't seem to be working as expected in order to do this.
We're going to add a set of if else statements inside of the callback.
This is going to let us check certain properties to determine whether or not this call the one to this
u r l should be considered a success or a failure.
For example if the response code is a 404 we might want to consider that a failure and we're probably
going to want to do something other than trying to print the address latitude and longitude if everything
went well though this is a perfectly reasonable thing to do.
There are two types of errors that we're going to worry about right now that's going to be machine errors
things like being on able to connect to a network and these are usually going to show up in the air
object and then errors coming from the other server the Google server.
This could be something like an invalid address or anything else in order to get started.
Let's take a look at what can happen when we pass a bad data to the Google API to view what actually
comes back in a call like this where we have an invalid address.
I'm going to head over to the browser and pull up that you are Al we used in the past I have it saved
it right here and I'm going to go ahead and remove the address we used previously from the browser history
type in 0 0 0 0 0.
Hit enter.
And right here you can see what comes back.
We get our results right but there's no results and we have the status the status says 0 results.
And this is the kind of information that's really important to track down.
We can use the status text value to determine whether or not the request was successful.
If we pass in a real zip code like 1 9 1 4 7 which is Philadelphia we're going to get our results back
and down below the status is going to get set equal to.
OK we can use this to determine that things went well between the status property and the air object
which we have over inside of atom we can determine what exactly to do inside of the callback.
The first thing we're going to do is add an if statement checking if the error object exists.
This is going to run and the code inside this code block if the object exists if it doesn't fine we'll
move on to the next else if statement which will write in just a moment if there is an error for the
moment all we're going to do is cancel that log a message to the screen something like.
Unable to connect to Google servers.
Perfect.
This is going to let the user now that we were unable to connect to the user's servers.
Not that something went wrong with their data like the address was invalid.
This is what's going to be inside of the air object.
Now the next thing that we're going to do is add an ELSE IF statement and inside of the condition we're
going to check that status property if the status property is zero results which it was for the zip
code 0 0 0 0 0.
We want to do something other than trying to print the address right here.
Status equals zero results inside of our conditional.
In Adam we can check just that if the abody dot status triple equals zero underscore results if that's
the case we're going to print a different message other than unable to connect to the Google servers
for this one.
We can use Konsole dot larg to print unable to find that address this lets the user know that it wasn't
a problem with the connection.
We were just unable to find the address they provided and they should try with something else.
I'm going to add an E an address to fix that typo.
Perfect.
Now we have error handling for those system errors like being unable to connect it to the Google servers
and for errors with the input.
In this case we're unable to find a location for that address.
And this is fantastic.
We have both of our errors handled.
Now this body status property that shows up here.
This is not going to be on every API.
This is specific to the Google geocoder API when you explore a new API.
It's important to try out all sorts of data good data like a real address and bad data like an invalid
zip code to see exactly what properties you can use to determine whether or not the request was successful
or if it failed.
In this case if the status is zero results we know the request failed and we can act accordingly.
Back inside of atom we can now go on to add our last else if clause.
If things went well and this is going to be your challenge for the video I want you to add the else
if clause.
Checking if the body's status property equals OK.
If it does you can go ahead and run these three lines inside of the code block.
If it doesn't these lines shouldn't run because the code block is not going to execute and then a way
to test things out over inside of the terminal try to fetch the address of 0 0 0 0 and make sure that
instead of the program crashing you get our error message printing to the screen.
Then you can go ahead and mess this you are all up by removing some of the important characters.
Try again and make sure this time you get on able to connect to the Google servers.
And last but not least.
See what happens when you enter a valid address.
Make sure our three console log statements still execute.
Take a moment add that else clause.
Test things out and when you're done go ahead and click play.
Hopefully that didn't cause you too much trouble to get started.
We're going to add that ELSE IF statement and inside of that condition we're going to check if body
status is ok.
Body dot status checking if it equals using triple equals.
OK if it is OK then we're going to simply take these lines and move them right here.
If it is OK to run those three cancel dot log statements.
I'm going to add a missing semi-colon onto that last console dialog and now we have a request that handles
errors really well if anything goes wrong.
We have a special message for it and if things go right we print exactly what the user expects the address
the latitude and longitude.
To test this over inside of the terminal I'm going to start by rerunning the command with an address
that's invalid.
When I run this command you can see that.
Unable to find address Princip to the screen and that is fantastic.
Instead of the program crashing printing a bunch of errors we simply have a little message printing
to the screen.
This is because the code here that tried to access those properties that didn't exist no longer runs
because this condition gets caught and we simply print the message to the screen.
Now we also want to test that the first message prints when it should.
I'm going to delete the asked and the dot from the U r l save the file and then I'm going to go ahead
and rerun the previous command this time around you can see unable to connect to Google servers prints
to the screen.
Just like it should.
Now I can test and the final thing by first re-adjusting and you are out to make it correct.
And then fetching a valid address from the terminal I'm going to use the app node app g s setting address
equal to the 0 8 8 to 2 which is a zip code in New Jersey.
When I run this command we do indeed get our formatted address for Flemington New Jersey with a zip
code and the state and we have our latitude and longitude right here.
This is fantastic.
We don't have the complete error handling model.
To quickly recap what we did we simply added else if statements inside of the callback callbacks are
just one function.
So in order to figure out if things went well or if things didn't go well we have to use LCF statements.
This lets us do different things like print different messages depending on whether or not we perceive
the request to have gone well.
For example when we make a request to Google providing a address that has problems in this case there
are zero results.
The error object is not going to get populated because it's not technically an error in terms of what
request thinks it is.
It's actually in the response object which is why we have to use bodycam status in order to check this
error.
In this case we have zero results status.
That is indeed an error and we act accordingly.
And that is it for this one we now have error handling in place we handle system errors.
Google server errors and we have our success case in the next video we're going to be moving this into
a separate file and abstracting a lot of details.
We'll talk about what that means and why it's important next so stay tuned.
We'll see you then.