In this video we're going to be refactoring apt.
Yes taking a lot of the complex logic related to geocoding and moving it into a separate file.
Currently all of the logic for making the request and determining whether or not the request succeeded
if else statements live inside of apt objects.
This is not exactly reusable and it really doesn't belong here.
What I'd like to do before we add even more logic related to fetching the forecast that's the topic
pick up the next video is break this out into its own function.
This function is going to live in a separate file like we did for the notes application in the Notes
app.
We had a separate file that had functions for adding listing and removing notes from our local adjacent
File.
We're going to be creating a separate function responsible for geocoding a given address all of the
logic is going to stay the same there really is no way around it it's just going to be abstracted out
of the file and into its own location.
Now this is going to be the challenge for the video.
We're going to start with a challenge and in the end of the video we'll add a few more advanced features
to the function.
But for now I'm going to tell you what I'd like you to do.
First up you are going to need to create a new directory and a new file for this challenge.
I'm not going to actually create the directory or file.
That's part of the challenge but I will show you what the require statement is going to look like we're
going to load in via a constant variable called the code.
The module require daat forward slash.
Since we're requiring a local file We're going to add that relative path code forward slash geocoder.
That means that you need to make a directory called G.O. code in the weather app folder and a file called
geocoder G-S.
Since we have a dot jast extension we can actually leave it off of our require call down below.
What you need to do is call G.O. dot G-0 code address geocoder address that is going to be the function
responsible for all the logic we currently have an app.
Yes.
Joe code address is going to take the address on the address.
It's going to be responsible for doing everything and coding that you are all making the request and
handling all of the error cases.
This means in that new file you need to export the G.O. code address function just like we exported
functions from the notes application file down below.
We have all of the logic here.
This logic needs to get moved inside of that function.
Everything I have highlighted should not be in the laptop just file after the challenge has been completed.
Now you can copy and paste this directly.
There really is no way around some of the more complex logic but you are going to need to make a few
changes.
You're going to need to load a request into that new file since we use it and it isn't going to be required
in that file by default.
Then you can go ahead and clean up the request require call here since we won't be using it in this
file.
Next up the org object is not going to exist.
You're going to get that passed in via the first argument.
Just like I have shown right here.
That means you're going to need to swap this out for whatever you happen to call that first argument.
I'd recommend calling that first argument something like address when you're done.
The program should work exactly as it works now.
There should be no change in functionality.
So take a moment create the folder create the file.
Require request.
Create that geocoder address function.
Copying all the code below and export it.
Then make that quick change.
Changing this to whatever you happen to call that first argument when you're done.
Test things out.
Try a valid address and make sure you get the address latitude and longitude and try an invalid zip
code and make sure.
Unable to find that address prints to the screen then go ahead and click play how to go.
Hopefully you were able to create that file and get everything up and running to get started.
I'm going to make a brand new directory in weather app.
That's the first thing we need to do.
The directory is called G.O. code which aligns with the required statement I have above in geocoder
are going to make our file geocoder Yes new file geocoder.
Yes now inside of here we can get started by loading in request.
Let's make a constant called request.
And we'll set it equal to require request excellence.
Now we can go ahead and define the function responsible for geocoding.
This one will be called the G.O. code address.
I'm going to make a variable called G-code address setting equal to an arrow function and this arrow
function is gonna get an address argument passed in.
This is the plain text unin coded address.
Now before we copy the code from actually yes into the function body I want to export our geocoder address
function using module that exports which we know is an object.
Anything we put on this object is going to be available to any files that require this file.
In our case we want to make a G.O. code address property available setting it equal to the G.O. code
address function that we defined up above.
Excellent.
Now it's time to actually copy all of the code from app dot J s into geocoder Yes I'm going to highlight
everything here.
Cut it out.
Using command x.
Move into geocoder J.S. and pasted inside of the body of our function.
The only thing we need to change inside of here is how we get the plaintext address.
We no longer have that the object.
Instead we get the address passed in as an argument.
Excellent.
With this in place we're now done with the G.O. code file.
It contains all of the complex logic for making and finishing the Everquest over an opt out.
Yes we can clean things up by removing some extra spaces and removing the request module which is no
longer used in this file.
Now at this point the functionality should be exactly the same and this is all you needed to do for
the challenge over inside of the terminal you are supposed to run a few examples to make sure it worked.
I'm going to go ahead and run a few to confirm my changes worked.
I'll use the a flag to search for a zip code that does exist something like 1 9 1 4 7.
And here we go.
I can see the address the latitude and longitude.
Now I'm going to swap out that zip code for something that does not exist like 0 0 0 0 0 0 0.
When I run this through the geocoder you can see unable to find address print the screen and that's
fantastic.
It means all of the logic inside of geocoder J S is still working.
This is all you needed to do for the challenge.
Now the next step in the process and the step I'll walk you through is the process of adding a callback
function to code address.
Now the goal of refactoring the code and app down was not to get rid of the callback.
The goal was to abstract all the complex logic related to encoding the data making their request and
checking for errors Altace should not care about any of that.
It doesn't even need to know that an HTP request was ever made.
All the on jast should care about is passing an address to the function and doing something with the
result the result being either an error message or the data in the formatted address the latitude and
longitude.
Before we go ahead and make any changes in geocoding Yes I want to take a look at how we're going to
structure things over here inside of APTA.
Yes we're going to pass a function to code address that's going to be an arrow function and this is
going to get called after the request comes back in here.
We're going to expect two arguments error message which is going to be a string and results which is
going to contain the address the latitude and longitude.
Only one of these is going to be available out of time.
If we have an error message we're not going to have results and if we have results we're not going to
have an error message.
This is going to make the logic down below.
Of determining whether or not the call succeeded much simpler will be able to use an IF statement.
If error message and if there is an error message we can simply print it to the screen using Konsole
that lock cancel that log error message.
There's no need to dig into any sort of object and figure out exactly what's going on.
All of that logic is abstracted NGO code.
Yes.
Now if there is no error message inside of the else clause we can go ahead and print the results.
I'm going to use that pretty print method we talked about previously.
Console log Jason docstring ify
and we're going to pretty print the results object which will be an object containing an address property
a latitude property and a long tattoo'd property in here.
I'm going to pass the undefined argument as our second argument.
This skips over the filtering function which we don't need.
And then I can specify my spacing which is going to format this in a really nice way.
I'm going to use two spaces right here.
Now that we have our function set up over inside of geocoder address and we have a good idea about how
it's going to look we can go ahead and implemented over inside of geocoder.
Yes in our arguments definition instead of just expecting an address argument.
We're also going to expect a callback argument and we can call this callback argument whenever we like.
We're going to call it in three places.
We're going to call it once inside of this if block instead of calling cancel dialog.
We're simply going to call the callback with this string.
This string is going to be the error message right here.
In order to do this all we need to do is change our consulate call to a callback call passing the first
argument our error message.
We can take the string exactly as it appeared and counsel that log and move it into the arguments for
callback.
Then I can remove the council dialog call and save the file.
Now we can do the exact same thing down below for our other council dialog statement.
When there is zero results I'm going to replace cancel that log with callback.
Now the last one is going to be a little trickier.
It's a little tricky here because we don't exactly have our object and we also need to create an undefined
variable for the first argument since an error message is not going to be provided when things go well.
All we have to do to create that undefined error message is call callback passing an undefined as the
first argument.
Then we can go ahead and specify our object as the second argument and this object.
This is going to be exactly what's right here.
The results.
Now as I mentioned in the results it's going to have three properties.
The first one is going to be formatted address.
So let's go ahead and knock that out first.
I'm going to set address equal to body results just like we have here I'm going to grab the first item
formatted underscore address here we're making things even easier instead of having complex properties
that are nested deep inside of an object inside of Opt-Out J s we'll be able to access a simple address
property and we're going to do the same thing for latitude and longitude down below.
I'm going to grab the code that let us fetch the latitude.
Let me add my second property latitude setting and equal to the code I grab below.
Then we can go ahead and add the last property which is going to be long itude setting that equal to
the latitude code replacing l a t with L and G.
Now that we have this in place we can add a semi-colon at the end and remove the council that Lague
statements since they're no longer necessary.
And with this we are done we can now rerun the file and when we do we're going to pass an address to
geocoder address.
This is going to go off and make the request and when the request comes back we'll be able to handle
that response in a really simple way.
Over inside of the terminal I'm going to go back to commands to run the command where I used the zip
of 1 9 1 4 7.
Everything works as expected.
Right here you can see I have my results object with an address property a latitude property and a long
itude property.
Everything looks fantastic.
The last test is going to be to test what happens when I pass in a bad zip code.
I just want to make sure the error message still shows up and it does.
Unable to find that address prints to the screen and that is happening because of this if statement
right here.
We check if there is an error message and if there is we print it to the screen after abstracting all
of that logic to the G.O. code file.
Actually yes.
Now a lot simpler and a lot easier to maintain.
We can also call G.O. code address in multiple locations if we want to reuse the code.
We don't have to copy and paste the code which would not follow the dry principle which stands for.
Don't repeat yourself.
Instead we can do the dry thing and simply call G.O. code address like we have here with this in place
we are now done fetching D-Ga. code data.
And the next video we're going to start wiring up that forecast API fetching real time weather data
for the address which you coded.
Stay tuned.
I am super excited to get to that.
I will see you next time.