Hello and welcome to Section 3 node fundamentals in this section you're going to be learning a ton about
building node applications and you're going to actually build your first one a note application.
This is where all the really fun stuff is going to start.
We're going to kick things off by learning about all of the modules that come built into node.
These are objects and functions and let you do stuff with javascript.
You've never been able to do before.
We're going to learn how to do things like read and write from the file system which we'll be using
in the Notes application to persist our data.
Now we're also going to be looking at third party NPM modules.
This is a big part of the reason that node became so popular.
NPM gives you a great collection of third party libraries you can use and they'll solve really common
problems so you don't have to rewrite that boilerplate code over and over again.
We're going to be using a third party module in this section to help with fetching input from that user.
Now aside from all of that we're going to be looking at debugging broken apps.
We'll look at some new iOS 6 features.
It's all coming up now but we're going to kick things off talking about something called require