It in the last video you created the ad no function which works well.
It starts by creating some static variables.
Then we fetch any existing notes.
We check for duplicates if there are none.
We push it onto the list then we save the data back into the file system.
And this is great.
The only problem is that we're going to be doing a lot of these steps over and over again for every
method that down below for example get all the ideas to fetch all of the notes send them back to app
dot J.
So we can print them to the screen for the user.
The first thing we're going to do inside of here is have the same exact code we're going to have our
try catch block to fetch the existing notes.
Now this is a problem because we're going to be repeating code throughout the application.
It's going to be best to break out the fetching of notes and the saving of notes down below into separate
functions that we can call in multiple locations.
Up above I'd like to get started by creating two new functions.
The first one is going to be called fetch notes.
It's going to be an arrow function and it's not going to take any arguments since it's going to be fetching
notes from the file system.
We'll fill that out in just a second.
The second function we're going to create is called Save Notes know save notes is going to need to take
an argument it's going to need to take that notes array.
You want to save the file system.
We're gonna set it equal to an arrow function.
Then we're going to go ahead and provide our argument which I will name.
Notes.
Excellent.
Now that we have these two functions we can go ahead and start moving some of the functionality from
AD note up into the individual functions.
First up let's do notes fetch notes is going to need this try catch block I'm actually going to cut
it out of add no and paste it up above.
Now this alone is not enough because currently we don't return anything from the function.
We want to do is return the notes.
That means instead of saving the result from Jason parse onto the notes variable which we haven't defined
We're going to go ahead and simply return it to the calling function.
So if I call fetch nodes down below I will get the notes array.
Because of this line.
Now if there are no notes maybe there is no file at all or there is a file but the data isn't Jason.
We can go ahead and return an empty array and we're going to do that inside of catch because remember
catch runs if anything inside of try fails.
Now this lets us simplify and note even further we can remove the empty space and we can take the array
that we set on the notes variable and remove it and instead call fetch notes with this in place.
We now have the exact same functionality we had before but we have a reusable function fetch notes which
we can use down below to handle the other commands that our app is going to support.
And this is awesome.
Instead of copying code and having it in multiple places in your file we've broken it into one place.
If we ever want to change how this functionality works whether we want to change the file name or some
of the logic like the try catch block we can change once instead of having to change every function
down below.
Now the same thing is going to go for save notes save notes is going to take the notes variable and
it's going to say that using FS to write files sync.
I'm going to cut out the line down below in AD note that does this and paste it up above.
Now save notes doesn't need to return anything.
In this case we're going to copy the line in there and then call save notes down below.
This might seem like overkill.
We've essentially taken one line and replaced it with a different line but it is a good idea to start
getting in the habit of creating reusable functions now calling save notes with no data is not going
to work.
We want to pass in the notes variable which is our notes array defined up above.
With this in place the ADD note function should now work as it did before we did any of our refactoring
going to remove that line there.
Putting all the variable declarations next to each other next step and the process is going to be to
test this out by creating a new note we already have two notes with the title of secret and a title
of secret too.
Let's go ahead and make a third one using Knode apt.
Yes.
We're going to use the ad command and we're going to pass in a title of two by and a body of food.
Awesome.
This should create a new note.
And if I run the command you can see we don't have any obvious errors.
And over inside of our file if I scroll to the right we have our brand new note with a title of two
by and a body of food.
So everything is working as expected even though we've refactored the code.
Now the next thing I want to do inside of ad note is take a moment to return the note that's getting
added and that's going to happen right after save notes comes back.
We're going to return note this note is going to get returned to whoever called the function.
And in that case it's going to get returned to app dot J.S. where we call it right here.
We can make a variable to store this result and we can call it note.
Now your challenge for this video is going to be to print a message.
If no it exists then we know the note was created.
That means we can go ahead and print a message like No created and we can print out the note title and
the note body.
Now if note does not exist if it's undefined that means there was a duplicate and that note title already
exists.
If that's the case I want you to print an error message like no title already in use.
There's a ton of different ways you could do this.
You can use an IF statement to check what the note variable equals.
You could use a library like low dash to do your type checking for you wherever you happen to get it
done works.
The goal though is to print two different messages depending on whether or not a note was returned.
Now inside of our note if this statement never runs we don't have an explicit call to return.
But as you know in javascript if you don't call return undefined automatically gets returned.
That means if duplicate notes that length is not equal to zero.
Undefined is gonna get return and we can use that as the condition for our state.
So take a moment to knock this out.
Feel free to use stack overflow.
Google around do whatever you need to do to get it done.
The goal though is to have a message print if things went well or if things went bad you still want
to print that message.
Once you're done go ahead and test it out in the terminal by creating a new note without a duplicate
title and a note with a duplicate title when you're done.
You can go ahead and click play.
How'd you do.
Hopefully you were able to knock that out without too much trouble.
The first thing I'm going to do is create an if statement if Note
this is going to be an object if things went well it's going to be undefined if things went poorly.
This code in here is only ever going to run if it's an object.
Undefined is going to fail the condition inside of javascript.
Now if the note did get created successfully what we're going to do is print a little message to the
screen console log.
Note created if things went poorly inside of the else clause we can call console log and we can print
something like.
Note title taken.
Awesome.
Now the other thing we want to do if things went well is print out the notes content.
I'm going to do this by first using console that log to print a couple of hyphens.
This is going to create a little space above my note then I can use council dot like twice the first
time we're going to print the title.
I'm going to add title as a string to show you what exactly you're seeing.
And then I can concatenate the title which we have access to in note dot title.
Now this uses an S-5 syntax we can swap this out with an S 6 syntax using what we already talked about
template strings title colon space then we can use our dollar sign with our curly braces to inject the
note title variable.
I'm going to copy this line and paste it down below to print out the body of the note.
I'm going to replace title with uppercase B body and I'm going to reference the body attribute on the
note object.
Excellent.
Now with this in place we should be able to run our app and see both of these notes printing.
I'm going to go ahead and rerun it.
This is going to try to create a note with two by which already exists.
So we should get an error message and right here you can see note title taken.
Now we can rerun the command.
Changing the title to something else like to buy from store.
This is a unique note title.
So the note should get created without any problems.
And right here you can see we get just that.
We have our note created message.
We have our little spacer and we have our title along with the body.
This is fantastic.
The ad note command is now complete.
We have an output when the command actually finishes and we have all the code that runs behind the scenes
to add the note to the data that gets stored in our file.
Now this code right here is going to get simplified a little later.
For the moment we're going to leave it like it is though and that is it for this one.
In this video we pulled out a lot of the code from AD note into separate functions.
Fetch notes and save notes which are now separate and they're able to be reused throughout the code.
So down below when we start filling out the other methods we can simply call fetch notes and save notes
instead of having to copy the contents over and over again to every new method.
We also inside of apt out J has added a little bit of output after the command runs.
We print a nice message if the note gets added successfully and if things go wrong we just tell them
the note title is already taken so they can adjust the command.
They ran.
That is it for this one.
I will see you next time as we start adding support for all the other commands inside of the notes application