In this video you are going to write the code for removing a note when someone uses that remove command
and they pass in the title of the note.
They want to remove.
Now we already created some utility functions that help us with fetching and saving notes so the code
should actually be pretty simple.
We're going to start this video off with a challenge.
Then we're going to go ahead and wrap the video up with a few things that I'll walk you through.
The first step in the process is going to be to fill out remove note and this is going to be your challenge.
Let's go ahead and remove canceled out like you only need to write three lines of code to get this done.
Now the first line is going to be to fetch the notes.
I'll leave a little comment for each line.
Then if the job is going to be to filter out the notes filter notes removing the one with title of argument
that means that we want to go through all of the notes in the notes array and if any of them have a
title that matches the title we want to remove it we want to get rid of them.
And this can be done using filter.
All we have to do is switch the equality statement from equals to not equals.
And this code will do just that.
It's going to go through the notes array every time it finds a note that doesn't match the title it's
going to keep it which is what we want and if it does find the title it'll return false.
It'll remove it from the array and then we're going to go ahead and add the third line which is to save
new notes or array.
Those are the only three lines you need to fill out.
Don't worry about returning anything from remove note or filling out anything inside of aperture.
Yes.
What I'd like you to do is take a moment to fill out these three lines and test things over inside of
the terminal.
Try to delete one of the notes you have in notes data.
If you don't have any that's fine go ahead and create one and then try to delete that one.
Take a moment.
Knock out these three lines.
Test things over in the terminal and when you're done go ahead and click play
out of Go.
Hopefully you are able to fill out these three lines without too much trouble.
The first thing we want to do for the fetch notes line is to create a variable called notes just like
we did an add note and we're going to set it equal to the return result from fetch notes.
At this point our notes variable stores an array of all of the notes.
The next thing we need to do is filter our notes.
If there is a note that has this title we want to remove it that is going to get done by creating a
new variable.
I'm going to call this one filtered notes.
You might have called it something else that is perfectly fine.
You might not have created a variable at all.
Maybe you did it in two lines and that's fine too.
The goal is just to get something that works here.
We're going to set filter notes equal to the result that's in a come back from notes dot filter which
we've already used up above.
We know that node start filter takes the function as its one and only argument and that function gets
called with the individual item in the array.
In this case it would be a note and we can do this all on one line using the ESX era syntax.
If we have one statement we don't need to open and close curly braces.
That means right here we can return true if Note title does not equal to the title that's passed into
the function.
This is going to populate filtered notes with all of the nodes whose titles do not match the one passed
in.
If the title does match the title passed in it will not be added to filter notes because of our filter
function.
Two lines down one more to go.
The last thing to do is call save notes right here.
We're going to call save notes passing in the new notes array which we have under the filtered notes
variable.
If we were to pass in notes it wouldn't work as expected.
We're filtering the notes out but we're not actually saving those notes so it's not going to get removed
from the Jason we need to pass filter notes in right here.
And these are the three lines I wanted to write and we can test these by saving the file and trying
to remove one of our notes.
I'm going to go ahead and try to remove secret too.
That means all we need to do is run the command which we called remove which is specified over in apparat.
Yes.
And then it's going to call our function.
I'm going to run node with app J us and we're going to pass in and lever move command.
And the only argument we need to provide for remove is the title there's no need to provide the body.
I'm going to set this equal to secret to excellent.
If I hit enter you can see we don't get any output although we do have the command remove printing.
There is no message saying whether or not a note was removed but we'll add that soon.
For now we can go ahead and check that data.
And right here you can see Secret Two is nowhere in sight and this means our removed method is indeed
working as expected it removed the note whose title matched and it kept all the notes whose title was
not equal to secret to exactly what we wanted.
Now the next thing we're going to do which is not part of the challenge is going to be to print a message
depending on whether or not a note was actually removed.
That means opt out jackass which calls remove note.
It's going to need to know whether or not a note was removed and how do we figure that out.
How can we possibly return that given the information we have right here.
Well we can't because we have two really important pieces of information.
We have the length of the original notes array and we have the length of the new notes array.
If they're equal then we can assume that no note was removed.
If they are not equal We're going to assume a note was removed and that is exactly what we're going
to do if the removed note function returns true.
That means a note was removed if it returns false.
That means a note was not removed.
Right here we can add return.
We're going to check if notes dot length does not equal filtered notes dop like if they're not equal
it's going to return true which is what we want because a note was removed if they're equal it's going
to return false which is great.
Now over inside of Aptor Yes we can go ahead and add a few lines down below to make the output for this
command a little nicer.
The first thing to do is to store that boolean.
I'm going to make a variable called note removed and we'll set that equal to the return result which
will either be true or false on the next line.
We can go ahead and create our message and I'm going to do this all on one line using the term unary
operator a VAR a message is going to get set equal to.
Now the ternary operator lets you specify a condition.
In this case we're going to use the condition note removed which will be true if a note was removed
and false if it wasn't.
Now the ternary operator can be a little confusing but it's really useful inside of javascript and node
j us after the condition we're going to put a space with a question mark and a space.
This is the statement that's going to run.
If it's true if the note removed condition passes what we want to do is set message equal to note was
removed.
Now if no remove is false we can specify that condition right after the colon.
This is the format for the ternary operator condition questionmark the Truthy expression to run colon.
And then the falsie expression to run here.
If there is no note removed we're going to use the text note not found.
Excellent.
Now with this in place we can go ahead and test out our message.
Last thing to do is print the message to the screen using cancel that log passing in message.
This lets us avoid if statements that make our else if clause for Remove unnecessarily complex back
inside an atom we can rerun the last command.
And in this case no no is going to get removed because we already deleted it and when I run it you can
see that no not found prints to the screen.
Now I'm going to go ahead and remove a note that does exist in notes data.
Jason I have a note with a title of secret.
Let's go ahead and rerun the command removing the 2 from the title.
When I run this command you can see note was removed print to the screen and this is fantastic.
We now have the ability to add and remove notes from our application.
And since we already made those utility functions we're able to reuse them here.
Making the process of filling out remove.
Note that much easier.
Back inside of apparat J.
We also did something depending on how the removed note function executed if it did remove the note
we print a message if it didn't we print a different message.
That is it for this one.
We now have two of our commands in place and the next one we're going to take a look at how we can create
our read command.
Read is going to be responsible for fetching the body of an individual note as opposed to a list which
we'll do later.
That is going to fetch all the notes and print them to the screen.
That's it for this one.
I will see you next time.