In this video you are going to be responsible for filling out the rest of the read command.
Now the read command does have an ELSE IF block defined below where we call get note and get note is
defined over inside of notes.
Yes even though currently it just prints out some dummy text.
What you're going to need to do is wire both of these up.
Now before I set you free I'm going to tell you exactly what I'd like you to do.
First up you are going to need to do something with the return value from get note are getting that
function is going to return the note object if it finds it.
If it doesn't it'll return undefined.
Just like we do for ad note up above after you store that value you're going to do some printing using
cancel that log similar to what we have here.
Obviously note created will be something like.
Note read and note title taken will be something like.
Note not found but the general flow is going to be exactly the same.
Now once you have that wired up inside of apt at Jasin you can move on to notes.
Scott japes filling out the function.
Now the function inside of notes isn't going to be that complex.
All you need to do is fetch the notes like we've done in every single method so far.
Then you're going to use notes from filter which we explored to only return notes whose title matches
the title passed in as the argument.
Now in our case this is either going to be zero notes which means the note has not found or it's going
to be one note which means we've found the note that the person wants to return from here we do need
to return that note.
It's important to remember the return value from notes felt there is always going to be an array.
Even if that array only has one item what you're going to need to do is return the first item in the
array.
If that item doesn't exist that's fine it'll return undefined like we want if it does exist.
Great.
That means we found the note.
This method should only require three lines of code one for fetching one for filtering and the return
statement.
Now once you have all that done I do want you to test that out.
Try reading a note whose title does not exist.
Then try reading a note whose title exists inside of your notes.
Data Chaisson file.
In this case I could try to buy and I could also try to not buy.
And in that case to not buy should return the message.
Note not found.
Now if you do things slightly different than what I do later in this video that is fine as long as you
get the core functionality working.
So take a moment to pause the video try to knock this out and test it and when you're done go ahead
and click play
had to go.
Hopefully you didn't have too much trouble wiring up the read command.
Now the first thing I'm going to do is fill out right here inside of apt J s a variable called note
which is going to store the return value from it get.
Note Now this could be an individual note object or it could be undefined down below.
I can use an IF statement to print the message if it exists or if it does not exist.
I'm going to use if Note.
Just like I do above and I am going to attach an else clause.
This clause will be responsible for printing an error if the note is not found.
Let's get started with that first since it's pretty simple.
Console log.
Note not found.
Awesome.
Now that we have our else clause filled out we can go ahead and fill out the if statement up above.
The first thing I'm going to do is print a little message console that log something like note found
will get the job done.
Then we can move on to printing the actual note details and we already have that code in place.
Right up above we have our hyphenated spacer.
Then we have our new title and our note body for the moment.
I'm going to copy and paste this code down below though we will be moving this into a utility function
that we use in both places a little bit later.
That was not part of the challenge.
The challenge was just to get things working.
And this does indeed get things working.
Now that we're done over inside of abduct J s we can move into the notes japes file and fill out that
get note method because currently it doesn't do anything with a title that gets passed in over inside
of notes.
When you needed to do was fill out those three lines.
The first one is going to be responsible for fetching the notes.
We already have done that before with the fetch notes function.
Var notes equals fetch notes perfect.
And now that we have our notes in place we can call notes dot filter returning all of the notes.
I'm going to make a variable called filtered notes setting equal to notes and Dot filter and now we
know that the filter method takes a function I'm going to go ahead and define an arrow function just
like this.
Here we can pass in as many statements as we like.
We're going to be using one and then refactor it to use the expression version.
But I find it a lot easier to start with these statements of version first especially when you're new
to aero functions.
Right here we're going to get the individual note passed in and we're going to return true when the
note title the title of the note we found in our Jason File equals using triple equals title perfect.
This is going to return true when the note title matches and false if it doesn't.
Now since we are using era functions and we only have one line like this where we return something we
can cut out our condition remove the curly braces and simply paste that condition right here.
This has the exact same functionality only it's a lot shorter and easier to look at.
Now that we have all of the data all we need to do is return something and we're going to return the
first item in the filtered notes array filtered notes.
We're going to grab the first item which is the index of 0 and then we just need to return it using
the return keyword and there we go.
Now there is a chance that filtered notes the first item doesn't exist and that's fine it's going to
return undefined in which case or else clause will run printing No not found.
If there is a note.
Great.
That's the note we want to print and over in apt.
Yes we do just that.
Now that we had this in place we can go ahead and test out this brand new functionality over inside
of the terminal by running our app using node APTA.
Yes I'm going to use the read command and I'm going to pass in a title equal to some string that I know
does not exist inside of a title in the notes data Jason File.
Something here.
When I run the command we get right here.
No not found.
And this is exactly what we want.
Now if I do try to fetch a note where the title does exist I would expect that note to come back in
the data file.
I have a note with a title of two by.
Let's go ahead and try to fetch that one.
I'm going to use the up arrow key to populate the previous command and replace the title with to space
by and hit enter.
And this time around you can see note found prints to the screen which is fantastic.
Below that we have our spacers and below that we have the title which is to buy and the body which is
food exactly as it appears over inside of the data file.
With this in place we are done the read command.
Now as I talked about earlier there is one more thing I want to tackle before we wrap this video up
over inside of apprecate.
Ass.
We now have the same code in two places.
We have the spacer title body here and we have that exact same code here.
When you find yourself copying and pasting code it's probably best to break that out into a function
that both locations call.
This is the dry principle which stands for don't repeat yourself in this case we are repeating ourselves.
It would be best to break this out into a function that we can call from both places in order to do
this all we're going to do is make a function in notes that g s called log note.
Now this was not part of the challenge you did not need to do this but we are going to do it as an exercise
in refactoring down here below remove.
Note we can make that brand new function a variable called log.
Note this is going to be a function that takes one argument.
That argument is going to be the no object because we want to print both the title and the body right
here.
Well expect the note to get passed in.
Now filling out the log note function is going to be really simple especially when you're solving a
dry issue because you can simply take the code that's repeated cut it out and paste it right inside
of the function.
In this case the variable names line up already.
So there is no need to change anything.
Now that we have a log note function in place we can go ahead and change things over and APTA.
J.S. Right here where we remove the council lock statements.
We can call notes dot Lague.
Note passing in the note object just like this and we can do the same thing up above.
I can remove these three console log statements and call notes dot log and note passing in.
Awesome.
And now that we have this in place we can rerun our program and hopefully what we see is the exact same
functionality.
The last thing to do before we run the program is export the Lague note function down below logged note
it's going to get exported and we're using that yes six syntax to do that.
With this in place I can now rerun the previous command from the terminal using up and enter and right
here we get note found printing to the screen with a title and the body just like we had before.
I'm also going to test out the ad command to make sure that one's working node Apgar J.S. ad will use
a title of things to do and a body of
go to post office.
Now when I hit Enter we would expect the same log to print as it did before for the ad command and that's
exactly what we get.
No created prints.
We get our spacer and then we get our title and our body that is it for this video in this one we were
able to successfully fill out that read command and we also created a really cool utility function that
we can take advantage of in multiple places.
This keeps our code dry and prevents us from having the same code in multiple places inside of our application
in the next video we're going to cover one of the most important topics frankly in the entire course.
This is debugging knowing how to properly debug programs is going to save you literally hundreds of
hours over your node.
Yes career debugging can be really painful if you don't have the right tools but once you know how it's
done it really isn't that bad and it can save you a ton of time.
So stay tuned.
I will see you next time.