Before you get started this video and the next video.
It's a two part series on Node debugging and I just Aris filmed them for node version 8.
So in the past we had tools for debugging node VI 67 and others did indeed have debugging tools.
But some of the more experimental and subject to change.
Well they finally got finalized and we now have some new tools for debugging our node app.
So we're going to work through both of them in these two videos and this one we're going to learn how
to debug our node apps from the command line in the next one we're going to learn how we can debug our
node apps from the chrome developer tools now to kick this off.
What I'd like to do is create a separate file in the playground folder we're going to add a simple example
in there in a file called debugging Dhananjay us and then we'll be able to create this file.
We'll run it in normal mode and then we'll look at how we can it run it in a special debug mode.
So let's go ahead and create the world's most useless application will create a Person object and we
can give that person a name.
Then I can set person dot age equal to something like 25 and we'll set person dot name equal to the
string.
Mike now yeah I know I could have done all of this right here in the object but I am breaking this out
onto multiple statements which we'll look at in just a little bit.
We're going to look at how we can iterate over all of these in order.
So next up the last thing we're going to do is use council dialogue to log a person to the screen.
Now if we run this program like we've been running our program so far we can take a pretty good guess
at what's going to happen right here.
We're going to get an object printed to the screen with a name of Mike and an age of 25 if we do that
node playground forward slash debugging dot J s that does exactly what we get.
Now the goal when you're debugging is not to just run through your program because you do bugging for
a reason most likely something is going wrong at some point in your program you might have a typo causing
things to not work correctly.
So what we're going to do is run this exact same program in a special debug mode.
Now you do need to be on Node a V-8 in order for this to work.
So I'm going to run node with the flag here I'm on 8.1 point to make sure you're on 8 or greater if
you're on V-6 the 4 or 7.
You can indeed update and then you'll be able to continue on with this video.
Now what are we going to do from here.
We're going to run the program just like we have it here but we're going to insert something before
our file name.
So we start off with node then we type inspect followed by playground forward slash debugging dot J
S.
Now when we run the program like this it's going to look completely different from what we had up above.
You'll see a whole bunch of outputs go ahead and break this down.
The first three lines can be ignored.
This is just letting you know that the debugger was successfully set up and now you're now able to debug
from the command line.
There's also a link if you want to learn more about how to debug.
But we're going to go through that right now.
So these three lines aren't particularly important to the application we're currently debugging.
Down below though we are getting some important output right here.
Break on start in playground forward slash to bugging Dhananjay ass line 1.
So when we run our program in debug mode we don't just want to fly through the entire application.
We want to go through our application statement by statement figuring out exactly what the application
looks like at each point in time.
So when you run debug mode your app actually hasn't started at all.
Now you'll notice that we have some code here some code we did not write highlighted there and some
code we did write this stuff right here.
Let's go ahead and take a look at our first debug command.
That's going to allow us to explore exactly what's going on right here.
This one which you can run it from the debug mode is a function list and you pass in the number of lines
you want to view.
Now I just mentioned that when we run our app in debug mode it pauses it pauses before any of our code
runs.
So there's not even a person variable when we use a list 10 it prints the 10 lines above and below the
place we're paused.
We have nine line file.
So by running list 10 we should be able to see the entire contents and here we have it.
So what do we have here.
We have our code but it's sitting inside of this wrapper function.
This wrapper function is actually created by node AJ as an every single piece of node code you write.
It's wrapped in this function.
It gives us access to stuff we've seen before like require and others we have not seen before but will
explore later.
So when we use module that exports module is defined right here when we require a library like O S or
f s that comes from right here.
Now at this point we want to actually start moving through our application.
We don't just want to sit up here before any code runs we want to get say to the middle and figure out
exactly what person looks like as we run through the app when we're in debug mode.
We have a few commands we can use to get that done.
The first one n n which is short for next is going to move on to the very next statement.
In our case that's going to take us from this wrapper function into our actual code.
Now at this point we've paused right here and we're actually paused before this ever runs.
So there's still no person variable we can use.
And again though to continue through and now we're down here on line 5.
Now once again we've paused on line 5.
This line hasn't actually executed.
So person age is not equal to 25 Yet person is an object with a single property name which is set to
Andrew.
Now at some point we're going to be done going line by line when we are we can use C C which stands
for continue is going to continue on until your program completes.
So if I run C you can see that the other lines all run automatically.
So what runs the age gets at the 25.
The name gets set to Mike and we use cancel that log to log person out which we are seeing right here
and then tells us that we're all done.
Now we actually went through the entire program but we didn't do any debugging.
I just wanted to walk you through the basic navigation commands that is n and seat.
Let's go back through our program again in debug mode and look at how we can stop at various places
and see exactly what variable values are equal to.
To do that I'm going to shut down the debugger using Control C twice then I can clear the terminal output
to make this a little easier to view and we're going to rerun that command.
We just ran node inspect playground debugging dot J.
As I'm going to run the program and once again we have the same output we've seen before we have the
messages letting us know that everything started correctly.
It's saying that we've braked before our code ran and then we have the line that we are currently on.
Now what are we going to do from here.
Well we are going to use and a couple of times.
So let's use it just one time right here and now we're going to use it again and we will use it one
more time.
So we want to make sure we're paused right here on line 7.
So we're here on line 7 and we've paused right here which means the line hasn't executed.
So the person name is still Andrew.
But we're going to do is look at a tool inside of the debugger called R E P L which stands for read
evaluate print loop and you can think of this like the consul over in the chrome developer tools.
If you're familiar it's a place where you can explore variable values.
You can mess around with various Javascript functions.
You could take values and manipulate them.
You can do all sorts of cool things.
Now we need to leave debug mode and get into our EPL by typing R E P L when we hit enter.
You can see we're in a new mode B.L. and we can always leave using controls C..
So if I take control c I'm back in debug mode and I can just type r l to get back into R L mode.
Now when we're Inari APL we can access the application as it currently stands.
So we're right here.
We haven't executed this line and we haven't logged on anything to the screen but we do have a person
object.
So let's go ahead and look at it just by typing it person.
Right here we get our object back her name is Andrew.
And age is 25 exactly as we expected.
Now I could also go ahead and access person data age to get 25 back.
I could take person Dom age and I could add 100 to it.
Which would be 125.
I can write any sort of javascript statement I want right in here to play around with the application.
At this point in time which is really useful when you're debugging if something's going wrong you want
to use the debugger to figure out where it's going wrong.
At what point in the application do various variables look incorrect.
Now from here we could always manipulate the data.
Let's go ahead and set person.
Age equal to 100.
Then I'm going to go ahead and leave.
R E P L.
Using control-C.
Now we're back in debug mode in debug mode.
We can do all of those things we explored before I could run list.
I could use any to go to the next line.
I could use C to continue.
I'm going to go ahead and use C to continue.
It runs through the other two statements.
Those two statements change the name and print the person and right here we get our Person object named
Mike age one hundred.
So using these tools we're going to be able to easily get into our application and figure out what's
going wrong.
But we have a simple app right.
What about a more complex one.
I don't want to use and to get into the middle of the program.
Every single time that I want to do some debugging.
Well we actually have a better way.
But we can do is we can use the debugger statement we type debugger with the semi-colon at the end.
We save the file and this creates a special line break so the node Inspektor it's going to stop right
here.
It's going to stop here allowing us to view it and we're not going to need to use end to get to this
point.
We can use C to skip everything before it will stop here and we can you see again to run through to
the end.
This is the most common technique.
I never really use N to iterate through an entire program it takes a ton of time but using debugger
we can get to a specific place in our program really easily.
You just type this and here and you rerun the program I'm going to shut down the debugger clear the
output once again and we'll restart it this time around we're getting the same output.
We are not going to use end though.
We're going to go right to see that when we first did this.
He brought us to the very end of the program but we have a debugger in place.
We told the program to break on line 7 when I type C.
It does indeed break on line 7.
So at this point we have a person named Andrew and a person age 25 although the name hasn't been updated
to Mike just yet.
We can prove all of that by using R E P L we can dump person to the council and right here we get that
object name Andrew.
Age 25.
So when I am debugging I'm almost always using the debugger that allows me to quickly execute the debugger
and get to a specific place in my program where I can actually figure out what's happening now that
we've done a little bit of debugging in debugging Dhananjay s I want you to use the techniques that
you just learned here to debug the notes application.
So I'm going to shut down the debugger clear the terminal output and I'll tell you what I'd like you
to do for the challenge.
So over inside of notes what you're going to do is make a modification to the alog note function which
is sitting down here in notes.
Dot J.
S. What I'd like you to do is break on this line and use R E P L to output.
Note.
So what you're going to do is use debugger on this very line inside of the log note function.
You're then going to run our notes application like we've been doing from the command line but this
time around you're going to use inspect So node inspect followed by the file name followed by the various
arguments required to get a log.
Note to run in this case you're going to use the read command use a read command with title and you
can pick any note that you happen to have in the Notes database and file.
I've got a few sitting right here.
I'm going to eventually use to buy.
That is what I'm going to run.
So when I do use out in the debugger and I output the notes object what I expect I would expect that
data title of two by and a body of food.
So take some time to add the debugger right here.
Run the program in debug mode.
Then when you get to that break point.
Use our APL to dump note to the screen when you're done.
Go ahead and click play how that go.
Hopefully you were able to get that done but I'm going to start with is adding debuggers are right here.
We're going to add debugger and then we're going to go ahead and run the program using the read command
with a title that can allow us to actually run this function to find the notes dot.
S and ensure that note equals what we would expect.
Now I'm going to save notes Scott J S and we're going to run the program from the terminal.
We want to use node.
We want to use inspect to run our application in debug mode.
Then we want to provide the file name app dot J.
S. And we have to provide the other stuff necessary like list the list command.
Excuse me the read a command and the title argument.
Now I already picked a note out the title was to space by.
So that's it.
I'm going to search for and when I run the program what happens we see exactly what we saw before the
application is indeed up and running.
We are in the debugger but it hasn't started yet.
Now in the past we might have used n to just go through line by line.
Very tedious but we're going to do is use C to run the application until it hits this line.
Now if it doesn't have that line we're never gonna break.
But in this case we've used the correct command read log note should indeed print.
I'm going to use C..
It's going to continue to that break point and now from here I wanted you to use R E P L to dump the
contents of note to the screen.
I'm going to type note in right here.
I do have the correct data I have to buy and I have food for the body.
Now I can go ahead and leave our EPL with Control-C I can quit right from here or I could rerun the
rest of the program.
The choice really is yours and there we have it.
We just ran through the debugger for the notes application.
Now we can actually also run node mine with inspect.
So I can type in node Mohn inspect followed by our application Abhaya as we can use the read command
once again with a title to by so literally the only difference between this man and the one I just wrote
is gnomon got swapped out.
It was previously Noad.
Now when I run this it's going to start the debugger.
So we're seeing a combination of the gnomon output and the inspect output.
Now I could hit C and that would bring me to my break point and I could mess around with the data or
do whatever I needed to but I can also make changes to the program so I could change this to four hyphens
instead of two.
And when I save the file it's automatically going to restart the debugger which is super useful.
I can then see it to get back to that same point and I can see the changes I just made.
So typically when you are running your application here to bugging something you want to go through
multiple times making sure your changes are actually fixing that bug.
So I find it a whole lot easier to use Nordman than to just use knode.
Now we can go ahead and undo that change.
I am going to leave debugger in place for the moment and we'll be using it once again in the next video.
I'm going to go ahead and wrap things up by shutting down debug clearing the output.
And that is it for this one.
Now we know how to debug via the command line.
But as you just saw the interface while it works isn't necessarily the most ideal and the next video
you're going to learn how to use the chrome and developer tools to debug your node applications.
So you're gonna get a really nice gooey with all the features you'd expect if you've ever used those
dev tools to debug websites.
It's all coming up in the next video.
I'm real excited to get to it.
So stay tuned.
I'll see you next time.