Welcome back to part two on Noad debugging as a quick reminder you do need Noad or version 8 in order
to go through this video successfully.
And for this one you're also going to need chrome install because we're going to be using the chrome
developer tools to go through the same process we went through in the last video.
Now we actually don't need to make any changes to our code.
Things like debugger those also work when we're debugging from the dev tools exactly like they work
when we're going from the command line.
So we can kick things off right away by running a brand new command from the terminal.
Now Previously we used node inspect that allowed us to debug via the command line when we want to debug
via the chrome developer tools we use node with a flag.
It is the inspect hyphen be r.k flag this tells node that we want to run in inspect mode but we don't
actually want to connect via that command line.
So we don't want to see all that output and we don't want to issue commands like an OR c.
We also want a break before that first line just like we did last time from here.
We're going to type the things that you'd expect.
We're just going to reference the file we want to run.
Playground forward slash debugging dot J.
S..
I'm going to run this and you're going to notice that we only get two lines in this time and these are
the exact same first two lines we got in the last video the first one is letting us know that the debugger
is up and running.
And the second one is letting us know where we can learn more.
But that third line is gone.
If you remember that third line told you you successfully connected followed by a bunch of output.
We're not getting that here because we haven't connected yet.
We're going to connect via Chrome to do that.
We're going to head over to the Chrome browser and we're going to go to Chrome Colan forward slash forward
slash inspect.
Now this chrome protocol is where you can find all of those chrome pages so I could go to Chrome Kolin
thoughts flash forward slash version for example.
That'll bring me to the version page you can go to the settings page.
There's a whole bunch of them.
We just need the inspect page.
Now on this page you should be seeing what I see here and a remote target.
You should have one.
Here is my note version as well as the file that's currently running.
Now there's an inspect button below this but you don't want to click that we actually want to go to
the open dedicated dev tools for node link.
Now if you're not seeing the remote target showing up that is OK we're just going to need to work through
some configuration together these tools are still new and there are still a few edge cases depending
on what operating system you're on and whether or not you have things like VPN or firewall settings.
If you're not seeing this just open up a question in the Q&amp;A and I promise we'll get to the bottom of
it.
If you are then you can click this button and it's going to bring us right into the dev tools and what
do we see here.
We see the exact same file we saw in the last video.
We have a wrapper function we have all of the code we wrote and we also have a whole bunch of other
stuff.
Now when it comes to the bugging with Node the only tab we're going to focus on is this source's tab
the counsel tab is also useful but you can actually open up the console on the sources tab using the
escape key.
That's going to allow you to hide and show it and the console is similar to our EPL.
Or we can run javascript like one plus four for here we get five.
Awesome.
Now on the left hand side we have a sources treeview.
Under no domain we have a bunch of files that aren't part of our application under File.
We have some files that are in this case just one debugging dodgiest which happens to already be open.
Now what we can do is go ahead and actually run through the app.
So at this point once again we have paused before our app code has executed.
So if I try to type person down below we're going to get undefined.
We can go ahead and run the program though using this big blue button.
You can also note the keyboard shortcut there if you want to use that later when we click the blue button.
We're doing exactly what C did in the command line to bugger.
It is going to continue until the program ends or until we hit one of our break points.
We do have a break point let's click that blue button and see what happens right here.
We stop on line 7.
Now not only are we stopping on line 7 but we're getting some pretty cool output up above we can see
over here we have some information about the arguments that got passed in down below.
We have some information about what person looks like.
So it's giving us a sneak peek into that data.
So if I wanted to know what person equaled at this point in time I could run a person down below to
get those properties back or I could just view it right here in line.
Now we can go ahead and continue on through the program and there we are we are done.
Now there's no need to close this window.
We can actually leave this one open and the next time we run one of our node apps in debug mode for
the dev tools it will automatically refresh this guy.
So let's go ahead and do that over inside of the terminal.
I'm going to shut things down.
We're going to reload the last command.
But we're going to swap out node for node Mon so Nordman can also be called with the inspector Bjarke
flag that's going to do exactly what you might expect it's going to restart the debugger every time
you change your file.
Up above we would not have had that same effect we would have had to shut things down and restart them
every time we change a file.
But when we do run this with gnomon we're going to notice that right away we're brought inside of the
debugger we're paused on the very first line and we can go ahead and continue through the program I
can click blue to get to our break point.
Now aside from creating breakpoints with debugger in the dev tools you can actually click the line number
to automatically create a breakpoint on the fly.
So right now I have a breakpoint on line five and line 11 now line 5 has come and gone to that one is
not going to get caught.
But we haven't got into line 11 yet.
So if I click that blue button you can see that instead of continuing all the way through the end and
printing out the object we actually have stopped just before we print out the object.
If I look at person I can see that the person is indeed Mike and if I click that blue play button once
again it prints to the screen.
Now there are still a few weird quirks you'll notice that it printed out four times.
There are things that are being worked through in the dev tools.
Hopefully we're going to get some of these get have issues cleaned up really soon here.
Now that we have all of this in place we can switch back over to Adam and make a change.
For example I could change this to 26.
Save the file and head back into the dev tools right away we are running the new version of the application.
I can continue through the program use the new code and make sure it's working as expected.
So when I do my no debugging I'm almost always doing it from the chrome developer tools.
It is very useful to know that the command line tools exist.
If you are on a server where you don't have access to things like installing chrome it is an essential
tool in your tool belt.
But for you right now going through this course I always recommend just using the chrome dev tools.
Now that we have this in place we can head back into ADOM.
I'm going to revert that change and we can move on to your challenge which is once again going to be
running the notes application and stopping at that breakpoint.
I can shut things down over inside of the terminal and clear the output.
Now as I mentioned before we can just leave this window open.
There's no need to go to the Crome inspect you RL and reconnect every single time it'll automatically
reconnect.
For us we're going to go back into Adam and open up notes.
J.
S So right here.
Remember you added that debugger and you ran the application with the read command and a title argument.
You're going to do the exact same thing just pick a different note.
So I'm going to go ahead and use this one right here.
Things to do.
That's the note that I'll be searching for when I go through this challenge.
Pick a note on your own.
Then run the application with the new flag.
We just explored get to this point in the chrome developer tools.
Print out no and ensure that it looks correct.
Once you're done you can go ahead and click play all right how that one go hopefully you were able to
get that done without too much trouble.
We're going to go ahead and knock things out.
First off by running the command no need for a code change.
I'm going to run node man though node would work as well.
Inspect hyphen be r.k then the applications are apt at Jap's we want to use the read command and we
want to read a note with a specific title.
In our case I picked one I believe it was called things to do us.
Now at this point we're brought over into the Croman developer tools and you can see that there is a
ton of application code inside a file.
We now have apparat J S and if I click play you can see that the other files come into play as they're
used.
Now we have notes.
J.S. we're stopped at that point where we put our debugger and we can actually see that the object is
correct by looking at this little in line.
Note that the chrome dev tools has at it for us.
We could also go ahead and just type note down below.
And we are indeed getting quite a few copies of that so we're going to work on fixing that one.
Hopefully the do good effects.
For now though at least it's the same thing multiple times and it's still easy to figure out what's
happening now that we've done that.
We could always change something that wasn't part of the challenge but you could set.
Note dot body equal to something else we can run that I can click play and when the program ends the
new body value is indeed the one that is showing up.
So there we have it.
We don't have two tools we can use to debug our applications.
We can use the command line interface if we must.
And when we're debugging our applications what I suggest you do is you use the chrome developer tools
if you ever forget how any of that works just come back and check these videos out.
Debugging is one of those skills that is really really tedious and slow at first.
It's going to take quite a bit of time before you really get comfortable with that flow but I promise
that every issue you debug gets you moving a little bit faster and before you know it you're going to
be moving through bugs really really quickly.
I'm going to remove the debugger from notes that just save the file.
That is it for this one.
I will see you next time.