And now that we've made some awesome progress on debugging Let's go back to the commands for our app
because there is only one more to fill out the list command and it can be really really easy there is
nothing complex going on here.
In order to get started all we need to do is fill out the list notes function which in this case we
called Get all get all those responsible for returning every single note.
That means it's going to return an array of objects an array of all of our notes.
All we have to do to do that is return fetch notes.
There's no need to filter there's no need to manipulate the data.
We just need to pass the data from fecche notes back through Get all.
Now that we have this in place we can fill out the functionality over inside of app.
Yes we have to create a variable where we can store the notes.
I was going to call it notes but I probably shouldn't because we already have a Notes variable declared.
I'm going to create a variable called all notes setting it equal to the return value Froemming get 0.
Which is we know because we just filled out returns all the notes.
Now I can use Konsole dot Lague to print a little message console dialog and I'm going to use template
string so I can inject the actual number of notes that are going to be printed.
Right here I'm going to say printing then the number of notes using the dollar sign in the curly braces
all notes dot Langguth that's the length of the array followed by notes with the in parentheses to handle
both singular and plural cases.
So if there are six nodes it would say printing six nodes.
Now that we have this in place we have to go about the process of actually printing each note which
means we need to call Lague no once for every item in the all notes array.
To do this we're going to use for each which is an array method similar to filter filter lets you manipulate
the array by returning true or false to keep items or remove items for each simply cause a callback
function.
Once for each item in the array.
In this case we can use it using all notes for each passing in a callback function.
Now that callback function is going to be an arrow function.
In our case and it's going to get called with the note variable just like filter would have and all
we're going to do is call notes dot log.
Note passing in the note argument which is right here and now that we have this in place we can actually
simplify it taking the lag no call removing the curly braces and pasting it right here.
This is the exact same functionality only using the expression syntax.
Now that we have our arrow function in place we are calling notes that live.
Note once for each item in the all notes array.
Let's go ahead and save the app Dowton J.S. file and test this out over in the terminal in order to
test out the list command.
All I'm going to do is use node after J ass with the command list.
There is no need to pass in any arguments.
When I run this I do get printing three notes and then I get my three notes to buy to buy from store
and things to do which is fantastic.
With this in place all of our commands are now working we can add notes we can remove notes we can read
an individual know and we can list all of the notes stored in our Jason File with this emplace I also
do want to clean up some of these commands up above.
We have some console log statements that are printing out a few things we no longer need at the very
top of apt.
Yes I am going to remove the starting apps out.
J.S. console lock statement making the constant f s the first line.
I'm also going to remove the two statements right here that print the command and the args variable
value.
I'm also inside of nodes Don J ask to remove the console log statement at the very top of that file
since it's no longer necessary.
It was definitely useful when we first started exploring different files but now we have everything
in place and there's no need.
If I rerun the list command this time you can see it looks a lot cleaner.
Printing three notes is the very first line showing up with this in place.
We are done our commands but there is still one thing I want to do in the next video we're going to
take a slightly more in-depth look at how we can configure yards.
This is going to let us require certain arguments for our commands.
So if someone tries to add a note without a title we can warn the user and prevent the program from
executing.
I'll see you next time.