In this video you are going to learn a little bit more about how we can configure yards for command
line interface applications.
We're going to learn how to set up the commands their descriptions and the arguments will be able to
set various properties on the arguments like whether or not they're required and others.
Now before we get into any of that I do want to pull up the barge docks so you at least know where this
information is coming from.
You can get it by googling NPM yards.
We're going to go to the first page which is the yard's package page on NPM.
This has the documentation for yards.
Now there is no table of contents for the Yards docks which makes it kind of difficult to navigate.
It starts off with some examples that don't go in any particular order and then eventually it gets into
a list of all the methods you have available.
And that's what we're looking for.
So I'm going to use command to search the page for methods and right here we get the methods Hetter.
This is the one we're looking for.
If you scroll down just a little bit we start to see an alphabetical list of all the methods you have
access to inside of yards.
And we're looking for dot command.
This is the method we can use to configure all four of our commands.
We're going to specify which options they require if any and we can also set up things like descriptions
and help functionality.
Now in order to get started we're going to pull up the terminal obviously and the Adam editor and we
need to do is make some changes inside of APTA.
Yes this is exactly where we're going to get started and we're going to start with that ad command.
We want to add a few helpful pieces of information in here.
That's going to one let dogs verify the add command is ran appropriately and to let the user know how
the add command is meant to be executed.
Now we are going to be changing property calls which means right before I access Arvie I want to call
dock command and then I'm going to call are we on the return value from command.
Now the syntax probably looks familiar.
This chaining syntax if you've used something like Jay query a lot of different libraries support it.
Anyways once we call a command on yards we're going to pass in three arguments.
The first one is the command name exactly how the user is going to type it in the terminal.
In our case it's going to be and then we're going to pass a another string in and this is going to be
a description of what the command does some sort of English readable description that a user can read
to figure out if that's the command they want to run.
Add a new note perfect.
The next one is going to be an object.
This is going to be the options object that lets us specify what arguments this command requires.
Now before we get into the options object let's go ahead and add one more call right after command.
We're going to call daat help which is a method so we're going to call it as a function and we don't
need to pass in any arguments when we add on this help call it sets up yards to return some really useful
information when someone runs the program.
For example I can run node app Jap's with the help flag to help flag is added because we call that help
method.
And when I run the program you can see all of the options we have available.
We have one command add add and you know and we have a Help option for the current command which is
nothing it's just help.
And the same thing holds true if we do node apps.
Yes.
And with that here we can view all of the options and arguments for ADD which in this case happens to
be none because we haven't set those up.
Let's go ahead and do that back inside of Adam in order to add properties.
We're going to update this options object where the key is the property name whether it's title or body
and the value is another object that lets us specify how that property should work.
So in the case of title we would add title on the left and we would put our options object on the right
inside of here we are going to configure three properties.
Describe Let's do that one first.
It's super simple describe describe is going to get set equal to a string and this is going to describe
what is supposed to be passed in and for the title in this case we can just use title
awesome now after described as in place we can go ahead and configure it.
Demand demand is going to tell Yarg whether or not this argument is required.
Demand is false by default.
We're going to go ahead and set it to true demand.
True.
Now if someone tries to run the ad command without the title it's going to fail and we can prove this
we can save apparat J.S. and over in the terminal we can rerun our previous command removing the help
flag.
And when I do that you see we get a warning missing required argument title.
Right here you see the title argument we have the title of note which is the describe string we used
and it's required on the right letting you know that you have to provide a title when you're calling
that add a command.
Now along with describe end demand we are going to be providing a third option.
This is called Aliase alias lets you provide a shortcut so you don't have to type hyphen hyphen title.
You can set the alias equal to a single character like ti.
When you do that you can now run the command in the terminal using the new syntax.
Let's go ahead and run our ad command node app that at instead of hyphen hyphen title.
We're going to use hyphen title which is the flag version and we can set that equal to whatever we like.
Flag title will be the title and hyphen hyphen body will get set equal to body.
We haven't set up the body argument yet so there is no alias.
But if I run this command everything works as expected.
The flag title shows up right where it should.
Even though we use the alias version which is the letter T.
Now that we have our title configured we can do the exact same thing for body.
We're going to specify our options object right here.
And we can provide those three arguments.
What I would like you to do is set up describe demand an alias for a body.
So describe equal to whatever you like.
Something like the body of note said demand equal to true and set the Aliase equal to the letter B.
Then over in the terminal run the help command to make sure that the body shows up like title did right
here.
Then go ahead and run ad with the body argument but use the short cut version of the b flag.
Take a moment to knock that out.
Run the commands from the terminal and when you're done go ahead and click play.
How to go.
Hopefully you didn't have too much trouble getting those three options set up.
The first one is describe and that one's pretty easy.
Describe is going to get set equal to a string.
And in this case body of note will get the job done.
Next step is going to be demand.
And to add a note we are going to need a body.
So we're going to set demand equal to true.
Just like we do up above for title and last but not least is the Illyas the alias is going to get set
equal to a single letter.
I'm going to use the letter B for body with this in place.
We can now save apparat J S and over inside of the terminal we can take a moment to rerun node after
J.S. ad with the help flag when we run this command.
We should now see the body argument showing up and you can even see it shows the flag version right
here the Aliase hyphen B body of note.
And it is required.
Everything looks great.
Now I'm going to go ahead and run add node abduct Jap's add passing in two arguments.
I'm going to set that equal to T and B setting an equal to B when I run the command.
Everything works as expected.
A new note was created with a title of tea and a body of B.
Were this in place.
We've now successfully completed the set up for the add command.
We have our ad command title.
We have a description and we have the block that specifies the arguments for that command now we do
have three more commands to add support for us.
Let's go ahead and get started doing that on the next line.
I'm going to call it Doc command again passing in the command name.
Let's go ahead and do the LIST command first because that one's really easy.
No arguments are required then we're going to pass in the description for the list command list all
notes.
Excellent.
Next up we're going to call a command again.
This time we'll do the command for read read reads an individual note.
So for the description for the read command will you something like read a note.
Now the read command does require the title argument.
That means we are going to need to provide that options object.
And I'm going to take title from up above copy and paste it below.
Now as you probably just noticed we have repeated code the title configuration just got copy and pasted
into multiple places.
It would be pretty nice if this was dry if it was in one variable we could reference in both locations
right here and right here.
Now this is going to be your challenge for the video.
What I want you to do is fill out the remove command.
Call it a command.
That means are going to set up remove the description and the options.
It only requires the title so the options are going to look identical to what we have here for.
Read then what I'd like you to do is pull the body object.
What I have highlighted right here and the title object right here in two separate variables that get
defined up above and you can reference title options and body options inside of the command arguments.
Right here you would put title options like this and right here you would put body options.
Now I'm going to undo that so we have the working code in place.
You can do the same thing for read read only has the title so you only need to reference the title options
variable and remove which you're going to add only uses the title as well.
So you just need to add the title setting it equal to title options.
Now since we've added these other commands we've actually gotten access to more help features.
If I run node apps.
J.S. with help you can see our other commands have shown up.
So once you're done with the challenge make sure remove shows up here as well.
Then try to remove a note.
Use the alias for title and use the regular version for title which is hyphen hyphen title.
Making sure everything still works as expected takes some time to knock that out.
That means you're going to call command for remove.
Set up its arguments and then you're going to move these objects one to three and the fourth one that
you're going to create out into separate variables that can get referenced everywhere they required.
All right.
Pause the video.
Knock that out and when you're done click play.
How'd you do.
I know I left this one a little open ended but that's the goal of these challenges.
As the course progresses I want you to make more decisions about how things are done now in order to
get started.
We are going to call command because there really is no way around that.
Just below where we call the command for read.
I'll call command again this time for remove.
Now the roof command is going to have a description.
We'll stick with something simple like remove a note and we are going to be providing a Options object
and in that options object I'm going to set title equal to title options.
Now I don't have title options created yet.
So the code would currently fail but the general idea we want to create the title options object once
and reference it in all the locations we use it.
I can take title options and add it here for read title options and up above for ADD.
I can cut out the object putting it in the clipboard and I can replace it with title options.
Now up above I can create a constant called Title options and I can set it equal to that object that
I just cut out to the clipboard.
Right here we now have the title options in place and this is going to work as expected.
We have the exact same functionality we did before but we now have the title options in a separate object.
Now we could also do the same thing for a body.
It might seem like overkill since we're only using it in one location but if we're sticking to the pattern
of breaking that out into variables I'm going to do it here as well.
I'm going to cut it out adding it to the clipboard and I'm going to reference body options now up above
I can create that constant body actions steady and equal to the object.
I just cut out and with this in place we are now done we have ADD read and remove all with their arguments
set up referencing the variables defined above.
With this in place let's go ahead and test out that remove command.
I'm going to list out my notes using node mapped out James list so I can see which notes I have to remove.
I'm going to go ahead and remove the note with the title of flag title and the note with the title of
t using Knode opt out.
Yes.
Remove.
Let's go ahead and use our flag.
First Tee we're going to remove the note with a title of T.
And then we go.
Note was removed Prince to the screen.
And if I use the up arrow key twice I can list the notes out again.
And you can see the note with the title of T is indeed gone.
Let's go ahead and remove one more note using note after J.
Yes.
Remove this time and we're going to use hyphen hyphen title which is the argument name and the note
we're going to remove has a title of flag title.
When I remove it it says no it was removed.
And if I rerun the list command I can see that we have three notes left.
The note was indeed removed and that is it for the notes application.
In this application we learned a lot of new things we learned how to create command line tools we learned
how to use third party modules how to use global modules and how to create our own files like notes
dodgiest that have functions we can use inside of our application.
We also took a look at how we can access the file system which is exactly what we did with our notes
data.
Jason File here we used a couple of functions to encode our Jason data save in a file and then read
it out when someone ran the command that let us store data in the file system.
And when I run a command like node at HHS list fetch that data back.
That is the end of this video and it is the end of the notes application the notes app is a great start.
We learned the basics of node but now it's time to learn more about asynchronous programming and how
we can fetch data from third party API.
That is the big topic of the next section.
I'll see you in the next video where we're going to go over aero functions in more detail it's still
going to be part of the notes application although we won't be updating the app itself.
We're going to work in the playground folder to explore how aero functions are different from the regular
E.S. 5 functions you're probably used to.
Stay tuned.
I will see you then.