In this video you're going to learn the ins and outs of the arrow function it's an E.S. Six feature
and we have taken a little look at it inside of notes.
Yes.
We used it in a few basic examples to create methods like fetch notes and save notes.
And we also passed that into a few Array methods like philtre right here.
And for each we used it as the callback function that gets called once for every item in the array.
Now if you try to swap out all of the functions in a program with aero functions it's most likely not
going to work as expected because there are some differences between the two and it's really important
to know what those differences are.
So you can make the decision to use a regular E.S. five function or to use an E.S. 6 arrow function.
The goal in this video is to give you the knowledge to make that choice and we're going to kick things
off by creating a new file in the playground folder.
Called Aero hyphen function dot J.S. inside of here.
We're going to play around with a few examples going over some of the subtleties to the arrow function
before we type anything inside of the file.
I'm going to start up this file with gnomon.
So every time we make a change it automatically refreshes over in the terminal.
If you remember gnomon is that utility we installed earlier in this section.
It was a global NPM module gnomon is the command to run.
And then we just pass in the file path like we would for any other node command.
Here we're going into the playground folder and the file itself is called erro hyphen function.
J.S. we're going to run the file and nothing prints to the screen besides the node monologs because
we have nothing in the file to get started.
We're going to create a function called Square by making a variable called Square and setting it equal
to an arrow function to make our arrow function.
We're going to first provide the arguments inside Apprentice's since we're going to be squaring a number
we just need one number and I'm going to refer to that number as x.
If I pass in three I should expect nine back and if I pass in nine I would expect 81 back after the
arguments list.
We have to put the arrow in Arrow function by putting the equal sign and the greater than symbol together
creating our nice little arrow from here we can go ahead and provide inside of curly braces all the
statements we want to execute.
We might go ahead and create a variable called result setting that equal to x times x then we might
return the result variable using the return keyword.
Now obviously this can be done on one line but the goal here is to illustrate that when you use the
statement as a function you can put as many lines as you want in between those curly braces.
Let's go ahead and call Square.
We're going to do that using counsel that log so we can print the result to the screen.
Counsel.
Lague right here.
I'm going to call square and we're going to call square with nine the square of nine would be 81.
So we would expect 81 to print to the screen.
I'm going to save the arrow function file.
And over here in the terminal 81 shows up just like we expect.
Now this is the statement syntax for the era function.
We've also explored the expression syntax which lets you simplify your erro functions when you're just
going to be returning some expression.
In this case all we need to do is specify the expression that we want to return.
In our case that's X times x.
You don't need to explicitly add the return keyword when you use the arrow function with all your curly
braces.
It's implicitly provided for you.
That means we can save the function just like this.
And the exact same result is going to print to the screen.
81 shows up.
This is one of the great advantages of era functions when you're using them in cases like filter or
for each.
Which we did in the notes file.
It lets you simplify your code keeping everything on one line and making your code a lot easier to maintain
and scan.
Now there is one thing I want to note when you have an arrow function that has just one argument and
you can actually leave off the parentheses.
If you have two or more arguments or you have zero arguments like this you are going to need to provide
the parentheses.
But if you just have one you can reference it like this with no parentheses.
If I save the file in this state 81 still prints to the screen.
And this is great.
We have an even simpler version of our arrow function now that we have a basic example down.
I want to move on to a more complex example that's going to explore the nuances between regular functions
and aero functions.
To illustrate this I'm going to make a variable called the user which is going to be an object on this
object.
We're going to specify one property name.
Go ahead and set name equal to the string your name in this case.
I'm going to set it equal to the string Andrew.
Then we can go ahead and define a method on the user object right after name with my comma at the end
of the line.
I'm going to provide the method.
Say hi setting an equal to an arrow function that doesn't take any arguments for the moment.
We'll keep the arrow function really simple.
All we're going to do inside of say hi is use console log to print to the screen inside of template
strings.
Hi we're not using template strings yet but we will in a second.
I'm going to use them here down below.
We can test out say hi by calling it user dot.
Say hi I'm going to go ahead and call it then save the file and we would expect that high prints to
the screen because all our erro function does is use console log to print a static string.
Nothing here is going to cause any problems.
You'll be able to swap out a regular function for an arrow function without issue.
Now the first issue that's going to arise when you're using aero functions is the fact that aero functions
do not bind a.
This keyword.
So if you are using this inside of your function it's not going to work when you swap it out for an
arrow function.
This binding refers to the parent binding.
In this case there is no parent function so this would refer to the global.
This keyword.
Now here we have our council that log that does not use this.
I'm going to swap it out for a case that does.
We're going to put a period after high and I'll say I'm followed by the name which we would usually
be able to access via this dot name.
If I try to run this code it is not going to work as expected.
We're going to get high.
I'm undefined printing to the screen which is exactly what we have in order to fix this.
We're going to look at an alternative syntax to erro functions.
That's great when you're defining object literals like we are right here after say hi.
I'm going to make a new method called Say hi Allt using a different Yes 6 feature E-6 provides us a
new way to make methods on objects.
You provide the method name.
Say hi Allt.
Then you go right to the parentheses.
Skipping the colon.
There's also no need for the function keyword even though it is a regular function it's not an arrow
function.
Then we move on to our curly braces inside of here.
I can have the exact same code we have above but it is going to work as expected.
It's going to print.
Hi I'm Andrew.
I'm going to call say hi all down below instead of the regular say hi method and right here you can
see.
Hi I'm Andrew Prince to the screen.
This is a syntax that you can use to solve this problem.
When you're creating functions on object literals like we are here now that we know that this keyword
does not get bound.
Let's go ahead and explore one other quirk.
The arrow functions have.
It also does not bind that arguments array regular functions like the one we have here are going to
have an arguments array that's accessible inside of the function console.
Lague arguments.
Now it's not an actual array it's more like an object with array like properties.
You can google that for more information but the arguments object is indeed specified in a regular function.
If I pass in one two and three and say the file We're going to get that back when we log out arguments
over inside of gnomon it's taking a quick second to restart and write.
Here we have our object.
We have one two and three.
We have the index for each as the property name.
And this works because we're using a regular function.
If we were to switch to the arrow function though it is not going to work as expected.
I'm going add console dialog arguments inside of my arrow function and I'm going to switch from calling
say hi alt back to the original method.
Say hi when I save the file here.
We're going to get something a lot different than what we had before.
We're actually getting the global arguments variable.
This is the arguments variable for that wrapper function we explored.
Here we have things like the require function definition.
Our modules object and a couple of string paths to the file end to the current directory.
These are obviously not what we are expecting and that is another thing we have to be aware of when
you're using aero functions.
You're not going to get that arguments.
Keyword.
You're not going to get that this binding that you'd expect these problems mostly arise when you try
to create methods on an object and use aira functions.
I would highly recommend switching to this syntax in those cases.
You get a simplified syntax but you also get the binding and you get your arguments variable.
Like you'd expect that is it for this video.
You've explored a little bit more about aero functions how they work when to use them and when not to
use them.
In general if you don't need the this keyword or the arguments keyword you can use an arrow function
without problem.
And I always prefer using era functions over regular functions when I can.
Now in the next section when we explore asynchronous programming we're going to use both regular functions
and aero functions a lot more and you'll be able to see firsthand how to choose between one over the
other.
That's coming up in the next section so stay tuned.
I am super excited to get to it.
I'll see you soon.