In this video you are finally going to learn some node J.S. code and we're going to kick things off
by talking about modules inside of Node.
Now modules are units of functionality.
So imagine I create a few functions that do something similar like a few functions that help with math
problems things like add subtract and divide.
I could bundle those up as a module call it Andrew hyphen math and other people could take advantage
of it.
Well we're going to be looking at in this video is not how to make our own module we are going to be
looking at how we can use modules and that is going to get done using a function in node called require
require is going to let us do three things.
First it's going to let us load in modules that come bundled with no J.S..
These are things like the TTP module which lets us make a web server and the FS module which lets us
access the file system for our machine.
We are also going to be using require in later videos to load in third party libraries things like Express
and sequel eyes which are going to let us write less code.
We're going to be able to use pre-written libraries to handle complex problems and all we need to do
is implemented by calling a few methods.
And lastly we are going to use require to require our very own files.
It's going to let us break up our application into multiple smaller files which is essential for building
real world apps.
If you have all of your code in one file it is going to be really hard to test maintain and update never
require isn't that bad.
What we're going to be doing in this video is exploring that first use case.
We're going to take a look at two built in modules.
We're going to figure out how to require them and how to use them and then we're going to move on to
starting the process of building that note application.
The first step we're going to take inside of the terminal is we're going to make a directory to store
all of these files.
I'm going to navigate from my home directory to the desktop using CD desktop then we're going to go
ahead and make a folder to store all of the lesson files for this project.
And now these lesson files are going to be available in the resources section for every video.
So if you get stuck or your code just isn't working for some reason you can download the lesson files
compare your files and figure out where things went wrong.
Now we're going to make that folder using M-K Diyar which is short for make a directory.
And let's go ahead and call the folder notes node or whatever you like.
We're going to be making a note app in node so notes node seems appropriate.
Then we'll see into nodes node and we can get started playing around with some of the built in modules.
Now these modules are built in.
So there's no need to install anything in the terminal.
We can simply require them right inside of our node files.
The next step in the process is going to be to open up at your rectory inside of Adam I'm going to open
up that directory we just created on the desktop and there it is.
We have notes node sitting right here.
Now we are going to need to make a file and I'm going to put that file in the root of the project.
It's going to be called app dot.
Yes.
And this is where our application is going to start.
We will be writing other files that get used throughout the app but this is the only file we're ever
going to be running from the terminal.
This is the initialization file for our application now to keep things off.
The first thing I want to do is use console dot log to print starting app.
The only reason we're going to do this is to keep track of how our files are executing and we're only
going to do this for the first project down the line.
Once you're comfortable with how files get loaded and how they run we'll be able to remove the console
log statements and they aren't necessary.
Now after we call cancel that log starting app the next thing we're going to do is load in a built in
module using require and we can get a complete list of all of the built in modules on the node.
J.S. API docs to view that had to your browser go to node.
J.S. dot org forward slash API.
When you go to this you are Alan you're going to be greeted with a long list of built in modules what
we're going to be doing is using the file system module to create a new file and the O S module the
OS module is going to let us fetch things like the user name for the currently logged in user to get
things off though we will start with the file system module.
We're going to go through the process of creating a file and appending to it.
Now when you view a dock's page for a built in module whether it's the file system one or a different
module you're going to see a long list of all the different functions properties that you have available
to you.
The one we're going to be using in this video is EF-S append file.
If you click it it'll take you to the specific documentation end of this.
This is where we can go ahead and figure out how to use a pen file.
Now a pen file is pretty simple.
We're going to pass it to string arguments.
One is going to be the file name and two is going to be the data we want to append to the file that
is all we need to provide in order to call FS append 5 before we can call EF-S data pen file.
We need to require it.
The whole point of require is to let us load in other modules.
In this case we're going to load in the FS module from app dot jazz.
Let's go ahead and create a variable that's going to be a constant using Konst since we're not going
to be manipulating the code.
The module sends back.
There's no need to use the VAR keyword.
We'll use the Konst keyword.
Then we're going to give it a name like f s and we're going to set it equal to require require is a
function that's available to you inside of any of your node J.S. files.
You don't have to do anything special to call it you simply call it like this inside of the arguments
list.
We're just going to pass one now.
Every time you call require whether you're loading a built in module a third party module or your own
file.
You just pass in one string.
And this case will pass in the module name which is fast and will toss a semi-colon at the end.
This is going to tell Noad you want to fetch all of the contents of the FS module and store them in
the F as a variable.
At this point we now have access to all of the functions available on the FS module which we explored
over in the docs including FS data pen file back in atom.
We can call upon file by calling FS dot append a file passing in the two arguments that we're going
to use.
The first one is going to be the file name.
Let's go ahead and put in.
Greetings itx T.
And the second one is going to be the text you want to append to the file.
In this case we're going to append.
Hello world.
Awesome.
Let's go ahead and save the file like this and run it from the terminal to see what happens if you're
running node v 7 or greater.
You're going to get a little warning when you run the program inside of the terminal.
Now on v 7 it's still going to work it's just a warning.
This is how you can get rid of it.
Above we have the original line as we have inside of our program.
Option 1 is adding a callback as the third argument to append file.
This callback is going to get executed when either an error occurs or the file successfully gets written
to inside of here we have an if statement.
If there is an error we simply print a message to the screen.
Unable to write to file.
Now our second option down below option 2 is to call append file sync append file sync is a synchronous
method.
We'll talk more about that later.
This function does not take the third argument.
You can type it just like this and you won't get the warning.
So go ahead and pick one of those two options if you are seeing the warning.
Both are going to work much the same.
If you are on V-6 you can stick with the line up above.
Although you might as well use one of the two down below to make your code a little more future proof.
Fear not we're going to be talking about asynchronous and synchronous functions as well as callback
functions extensively throughout the course.
What I'm giving you here is just a template something you can write in your file to get that error removed
in a few sections.
You understand exactly what these two methods are and how they work.
All right let's go ahead and dive back in.
If we do this over inside of the terminal node apt.
J.S. we're going to see something pretty cool right here.
We get our one council out lock statement starting out so we know the app started correctly and head
over into atom.
We actually see there's a brand new Greetings ts t file.
This is the text file that was created by EF-S data pen file.
It tries to append it to a file if the file doesn't exist.
It simply creates it.
Right here we have our message.
Hello world.
Printing to the screen.
And this is fantastic.
In just minutes we were able to load in a built in node module and call a function that lets us create
a brand new file and if we call it again by rerunning the command using the up key and the enter key
and we head back into the contents of greetings that t you can see this time around we have hello world
twice.
Independent at one time for each time we ran the program.
Now this is pretty cool.
We have a application that creates a brand new file on our file system and if the file already exists
it simply adds to it.
What I'd like to do though is customize this greeting and to do that we're going to explore one more
built in module.
Now we're going to be using more than just a pen file in the future.
We'll be exploring other methods.
For now the real goal is to understand require require let's us load in the modules functionality so
we can call it down below.
The second module that we're going to be using is OS and we can view it over in the documentation down
on the left hand side.
We're looking for the OS module and on the OS module we're going to be using the method defined at the
very bottom user info user info gets called and returns some various information about the currently
logged in user such as the user name.
And this is what we're going to pull off using the user name that comes from the OS.
We're going to be able to customize that greeting instead of hello world.
It can say hello.
In this case Andrew to get started we have to require OS.
That means back inside of Adam just below where I create my f s constant.
I'm going to create a new constant called OS setting and equal to require which gets called as a function
and gets passed one argument.
The module name.
Oh yes from here we can go ahead and start calling methods available on the os module like user info.
Let's make a new variable called user to store the result.
The variable user is going to get set equal to OS dot user info and we can call user info without any
arguments.
Now before we go ahead and do anything with it the append file line I'm going to comment it out and
print out the contents of the User variable using Konsole that Lague.
This is going to let us explore exactly what we get back over in the terminal we can rerun our program
using up and enter and right here and you see we have an object with a few properties.
We have a new ID G ID user name home directory and shell depending on your OS you're not going to have
all of these but you should always have the user name property.
This is the one we care about.
That means back inside of atom we can use user dot username inside of a pen file.
I'm going to go ahead and remove the console lock statement and uncomment are called to FS data append
file right here where we have world.
We're going to be swapping that out with user dot username.
Now there's two ways we can do this.
The first way is to remove world with the exclamation mark and concatenate user dot username.
Then we can concatenate a nother string using the plus operator.
That's just the exclamation mark.
And if we run this everything is going to work as expected over in the terminal.
We can rerun our app it prints starting app and over in a Greetings anti-X he should see something like
this right here I have.
Hello Andrew.
Printing to the screen and this is brilliant.
Using the s module end of the O S module we were able to grab the user's username and create a new file
storing it right here inside of app.
We can also do this another way using an E.S. six feature known as template strings template strings
start and end with the tick operator which is available to the left of the one key on your keyboard.
Then you type things like you normally would.
We're going to type hello space with the exclamation mark and right here is where we want to put the
name to insert a javascript variable inside of your template string.
You use the dollar sign followed by an opening and closing curly braces and right here you can see the
Adam editor actually picks up on this syntax.
Then we just reference a variable like user dot username.
This is all it takes to use template strings.
It's an easy six feature available because you're using node these six.
It's super useful for things like this.
This syntax is much easier to understand and update than the string concatenation version we just had.
And if you run it it's going to produce the exact same output.
We can run it.
View the text file and this time around we have.
Hello Andrew twice which is brilliant.
With this in place we are now done with our very basic example.
Let's take a quick moment to recap what we learned.
First up we learned that we can use require it to load in modules.
This lets us take existing functionality written by either the no developers or a third party library
ourselves and loaded into a file so we can be reusable creating reusable code as essential for building
large apps.
If you have to build everything in an app every time no one would ever get anything done because they
would get stuck at building the basics things like HTP servers and web servers.
There's already modules for that stuff and we're going to be taking advantage of the great and PMA community
in this case we used to built in modules f FS and Os.
We loaded them in and using require and we stored in the module results inside of two variables.
These variables store everything available to us from the module in the case of F as we used the append
file method.
And in the case of OS we use the user info method together we were able to grab the user name and save
it into a file which is fantastic.
With this in place we're not ready to start creating our own files for our notes application and requiring
them inside of app.
Jay asked.
And that is exactly what you are going to learn how to do in the next video.
I am super excited to show you how.
So stay tuned.
I will see you next time.