In the last video you learn how to use require to load in modules that come with notes.
Yes.
In this video you are going to learn how to use required to load and other files that you created inside
of your project.
This is going to let you move functions outside of apps that drive us into more specific files which
is going to make your application easier to scale easier to task and easier to update.
To get started the first thing we're going to do is make that new file.
Now in the context of our notes app the new file is going to store various functions for writing and
reading notes for the moment.
We're not going to be worrying about that functionality but we are going to create the file where it
will eventually live.
This file is going to be notes dodgiest and we're going to save it inside of the root of our application
right alongside apt.
Jay Yes and greetings Don TXI T.
For the moment all we're going to do inside of notes is use console dialog to print a little log showing
the file has been executed starting notes Dhananjay us perfect.
Now we have a log on the top of notes and one on the top of app.
I'm going to change that to app.
Yes.
Awesome.
With this in place we can now require the notes file.
It doesn't export any functionality but that's fine by the way when I say export.
I mean the notes file.
It doesn't have any functions or properties that another file can take advantage of.
We'll look at how to export stuff in just a second.
For now though we're going to load our module in much the same way we loaded in the built in node modules.
Let's go ahead and make a contest.
I'm going to call this one it notes and we're going to set it equal to the return result from require
just like we've done up above inside of here.
We are going to pass in one argument that's going to be a string.
But it is going to be a little different in the past.
We typed in the module name of what we have here is not a module we have a file notes.
Yes but we need to do is tell a node where that file lives using a relative path.
Now relative paths start with a dot forward slash which points to the current directory that the file
is in.
In this case this points us to the app JSE directory which is the root of our project from here.
We don't have to go into any other folders to access notes.
J.S. it's sitting right here.
So you can type its name with this in place we can now save apt.
Yes and see what happens when we run our application.
I'm going to go ahead and run the app using node app Jap's and right here you see we get our two locks.
First we get starting apparat.
And then we get starting notes.
Yes now starting notes that J.S. comes from here and it only runs because we required the file inside
of Aptor.
Yes.
If I comment out this line save the file and rerun it from the terminal you can see the notes file never
executes because we never explicitly touch it.
We never call it inside of the terminal like we do here and we never require.
For now though we are going to be requiring it.
So I'm going to comment that line by the way I'm using command.
Forward slash to comment and and comment lines quickly.
This is a keyboard shortcut available in most text editors.
If you're on Windows or Linux it might not be command.
It might be control or something else.
Go ahead and just click around on there and try to find the one that works with forward slash just to
the left of the shift key to comment and on comment lines that's going to save you a lot of time down
the line.
I'm a big fan of keyboard shortcuts and I'll try to explain as many of them as I can if I'm using one
that I haven't explained.
And you're curious.
Please just ask in the Q&amp;A.
I'd be happy to tell you exactly how it's done.
For now though the focus is going to be to export something from notes dodgiest that we can use in app.
J.S. inside of notes.
Yes.
Actually inside of all of our node files we have access to a variable called module I'm going to use
console log to print it to the screen so we can explore it over in the terminal module just like this
is available in all of our files.
Let's go ahead and rerun the file to explore it right here.
We got a pretty big object now.
Truth be told we're not going to be using most of these properties.
We have things like ID exports parent file name and a bunch more if the only one we're ever going to
use in this course is exports.
This is pretty much the only useful one here.
Exports is fantastic.
It's an object on the module property and everything on this object.
This gets exported this object gets set as the variable right here.
Notice that means we can set properties on it and those will get set on notes and we can use them inside
of apps.
Yes let's take a quick look at how that works.
Well we're going to do is define an age property using module dot exports the object we just explored
over in the terminal.
And we know it's an object because we can see it right here.
Which means I can at a property age and set it equal to my age which is 25 then I can go ahead and save
this file and move into Aptos to take advantage of this new age property.
Notes is going to be storing all of my exports in this case just age right here after the greeting.
I'm going to say you are followed by the age inside of template strings we use dollar with curly braces
notes dot age and I'll put a period at the end.
And now our greeting should say Hello Andrew.
You are twenty five.
It's getting the 25 from our separate file which is fantastic.
Let's take a quick moment to rerun the program.
Over inside of the terminal using the up arrow key and the Enter key back inside of the app we can open.
Greetings don t s t.
And sitting right here you see we have hello.
Andrew you are 25 which is awesome.
Using require we were able to require a file that we created and this file stored some properties that
were advantageous to the rest of the project.
Now obviously this is a pretty contrived example.
We're not going to be exporting static numbers.
The real goal of exports is to be able to export functions that get used inside of app.
Yes let's take a quick moment.
Export two functions
right here I'm going to set module.
Exports dot add.
Note equal to a function function.
Followed by opening and closing parentheses followed by the curly braces.
Now throughout the course I'm going to be using aero functions where I can like right here to convert
a regular S-5 function into an era function.
All you do is you remove the function keyword and replace it with a equals greater then sign right between
the parentheses end of the opening curly braces.
Now there are some more subtleties to aero functions we'll be talking about throughout the course but
if you have an anonymous function you can swap it to an arrow function without any problems.
The big difference is that the function is not going to bind the this keyword or the arguments array
which will be exploring throughout the course.
So if you do get some errors it's good to know that the error function could be the cause.
For now though we're going to keep things really simple using console log to print add.
Note.
This is going to let us know that the ADD note function was called and we're going to go ahead and return
some string like new note.
Now this function is going to find in notes dodgiest but we can take advantage of it over inside of
app.
Yes let's take a quick second to comment out both the append file and the user line.
I can highlight both and use that keyboard shortcut.
We talked about to comment both of them out and right here.
All I'm going to do is make a variable call the result or yes for short and set it equal to the return
result from notes dot.
Add note now the add function is a dummy function for the moment.
It doesn't take any arguments and it doesn't actually do anything.
So we can call it without any arguments.
Then we're going to print the result variable like this and we would expect the result variable to be
equal to that string.
New in.
If I save both of my files and rerun things from the terminal right here you can see new note prints
to the screen at the very end and just before it add no prints.
This means that we required successfully our notes file.
We called add no and its return result was successfully returned to app..
J.S..
Which is fantastic.
Using this exact pattern we're going to be able to define our functions for adding and removing notes
over here in our notes file but we'll be able to call them anywhere inside of our app including in app
dot J as.
Now it's time for a quick challenge.
What I'd like you to do is make a new function in notes.
J.S. called add this add function is going to get set on the exports object and remember it's an object
so you can set multiple properties.
This add function is going to take two arguments A and B.
It's going to add them together and return the result.
Then over inside of x.
Yes I'd like you to call that notes add function passing in two numbers whatever you like.
Like 9 Ninan negative 2.
Then print the result to the screen and make sure it works correctly.
I can get started by removing the call to add notes since this is not going to be needed for the challenge.
So take a moment create that add function inside of notes.
J.
Call it inside of apt g s and make sure the proper result prints to the screen.
Take a moment pause the video.
Knock that out and when you're done click play
how'd it go.
Hopefully you were able to make that function and call it from app dot.
Yes the first step in the process is going to be to define the new function.
Right here I'm going to set module dot exports dot add equal to that function.
Let's set it equal to an arrow function.
If you used a regular function that is perfectly fine I just prefer using the arrow function when I
can and inside of here we are going to be getting into arguments.
Going to be getting a and b.
All we need to do is return the result really simple.
We're going to return a plus b just like this.
Now this was the first part of your challenge.
Defining a utility function in notes dodgiest the second part was to actually use it over an app.
Yes right here we can use our function by printing Konsole dot log.
Result with the colon.
And this is just for formatting and that's the second argument we're going to print.
The actual result notes dot add.
And we're going to add up to numbers.
Let's go ahead and add 9 and negative to the result.
Here should be 7.
If we go ahead and run the program you can see we get just that 7 prints to the screen.
If you are able to get this Congratulations you successfully completed one of your first challenges.
These are going to be sprinkled throughout the course and they're going to get progressively more complex
in the beginning.
I'm going to lead you through the process not leaving too much open ended later in the course though
it's going to be really important to your own learning to have a lot of time to explore different ways
to do things.
This means the problems will be a little more open ended as will the solutions.
Don't worry for now we're going to keep the challenges pretty explicit.
I'll tell you exactly what I want and exactly how I want it done.
Now you can go ahead and play around with different ways to do it.
That is perfectly fine.
The real goal is to just get you writing code independent of following someone else's lead.
That is where the real learning happens and that is it for this one.
We now know how to require other files that we created and we know how to export things like properties
and functions from those files.
This makes the module system inside of node super useful.
Now there really is only one more piece to the puzzle.
We explored how to use built in modules we explored how to use modules we have to find in the next video
we are going to explore how to use third party modules from there.
We're going to start building the notes application so stay tuned.
I will see you next time.