You know two out of the three ways to use require And in this one we're going to explore the last way
which is to require a package that you've installed from and pm as I mentioned in the first section
and is a big part of what makes a node so fantastic.
There is a huge community of developers that have created thousands of packages that already solve some
of the most common problems in node applications.
We are going to be taking advantage of quite a few packages throughout the course now in these packages.
There's nothing magical it's regular node code that aims to solve a specific problem.
The reason you'd want to use it is so you don't have to spend all your time writing these utility functions
that already exist.
Not only do they exist.
They've been tested.
They've been proven to work.
Others have used them and documented them.
Now with all that said how do we get started.
Well to get started we actually have to run a command from the terminal to tell our application we want
to use NPM modules that command is going to get run over in the terminal.
Make sure you've navigated inside of your project folder right here and you can see an inside of the
notes node directory.
Now when you installed node you also install something called NPM which at one point stood for node
package manager but there's now an on running joke because there is plenty of things on NPM that are
not specific to node A lot of front end frameworks like Jay queery and re-act now live on NPM as well.
So that pretty much ditched the node package manager explanation.
And now on their site they cycle between a bunch of hilarious things that happen to match up with NPM.
Regardless though we are going to be running some NPM commands and you can test that you have it installed
by running and P.M. space hyphen VI were running NPM with the V flag which should print the version
and right here you can see I'm on version three point nine point five it's OK if your version is slightly
different that's not important what is important is that you have NPM installed from here.
We're going to run a command called NPM in it and it is going to prompt you to fill out a few questions
about your NPM project.
We can go ahead and run the command and we can cycle through the questions up above is a quick description
of what's happening and down below.
It's going to start asking you a few questions.
First up is the name now your name can't have uppercase characters or spaces nodes.
Node works great like I hit enter to use the default value which is in parentheses for the version point
zero point zero works fine too.
We are going to leave most of these at their default value.
We can leave the description empty.
The entry point is going to be apt.
J.S..
Make sure that shows up right here.
Next up we have a test command.
We're going to explore testing later in the course.
So for now we can leave this empty.
After that we have a good repository section.
We're going to leave that empty for now as well.
We have some keywords which are used for searching for modules.
We're not going to be publishing this module so we can leave those empty.
Lastly we have an author.
You might as well go ahead and type your name wups and hit enter for the license we're going to stick
with us.
See at the moment since we're not publishing it it doesn't really matter.
Now I want to dispel that this command is doing anything magical oldest commands doing is it's creating
a single file inside of your project.
It's going to be in the root of the project and it's called package dot Jason and the file is going
to look exactly like this.
Down below you can hit enter or type yes to confirm that this is what you want to do.
Now that we have the file created we can actually view it inside of our project right here.
We have the package and Jason File and this is all it is.
It's a simple description of your application.
Now as I mentioned we're not going to be publishing our app to NPM.
So a lot of this information really isn't important to us.
What is important though is that packaged out Jason is where we define the third party modules we want
to install in our application and to install a module in the app.
We are going to run a command over in the terminal in this section we're going to be installing a module
called Low dash low dash comes with a ton of utility methods and functions that make developing inside
of node or javascript a heck of a lot easier to take a look at what exactly we're getting into.
Let's go ahead and move into the browser.
We're going to go to NPM J.S. dot com.
Then we're going to search for the package low dash and you can see it comes up right here.
When you click it you should be taken to the package page and the package page is going to show you
a lot of statistics about the module and the documentation.
Now if I use this package page when I'm looking for new modules I'd like to see how many downloads it
has and when it was last updated here you can see it was updated recently which is great.
It means the package is most likely compatible with the latest versions of Node.
And down below you can see this is actually one of the most popular NPM packages with over a million
downloads a day.
We are going to be using this module to explore how to install NPM modules and how to actually use them
in the project.
The first thing you need to grab is just the module name which has low dash.
Once you have that information you're ready to install it.
Back in the terminal we're going to run NPM install after install.
We're going to specify the module load dash just like this.
Now this command alone would work.
What we're also going to do though is provide the save flank.
This command is going to install the module and we'll explore exactly what that means in a second.
And the save flag two hyphens followed by the word save is going to update the contents of the package.
Jason 5.
Let's go ahead and run this command.
This command is going to go off to the NPM servers and fetch the code and install inside of your project.
And any time you install an NPM module it's going to live in your project in a node modules folder.
Now if you open that node modules folder you're going to see the low dash folder right here.
This is the module that we just installed and you can see over and packaged out Jason.
We've also had some updates automatically take place.
There's a new dependencies attribute that has an object with key value pairs where the key is the module
we want to use in our project and the value is the version number.
In this case the most recent version version four point one three point one.
With this in place we can now require our module inside of the project over inside of us.
We can take advantage of everything that comes in low Dasch by going through the same process of acquiring
it.
We're going to make it Konst we're going to name that Konst underscore which is a common name for the
low dash utility library.
And we're going to set it equal to require just like this inside of here.
We're going to pass in the module name exactly as it appears in the package that Jason File.
This is the same module name you used when you ran install right here.
We're going to type load dash and that is it.
This is all it takes to include a third party module in your project.
Now the order of operations is pretty important here.
Notice first going to look for a core module with the name low dash.
It's not going to find one because there is no core module.
So the next place is going to look is the node modules folder.
Right here it is going to find low dash and it's going to go ahead and load that module returning any
of the exports it provides.
With this in place we can now take advantage of some of the utilities that come with low dash.
We're going to explore too quickly in this video and we'll be exploring more throughout the course since
Lo dash is basically just a set of really handy utilities.
Before we do we should take a look at the documentation so we know exactly what we're getting into.
This is a really common step when you're using an NPM module first you install it second.
You got to look at those docs and make sure that you can get done what you want to get done down below.
There really isn't a lot that don't go through the API that lives on a separate web site.
If you click the link or go to low dash dot com and you click the API documentation page you can view
all of the various methods you have available to you.
In this case we're going to be using command F to search for underscore dot is string.
Then in the docs I can go ahead and click it.
Opening it up in the main page is string is a utility that comes with low dash and it returns true if
the variable you pass in is a string and it returns false if the value you pass in is not a string.
And we can prove that using it over inside of atom.
Let's go ahead and use this.
I'm going to cancel that log.
The result to the screen and we're going to use underscore dot is string passing in a couple of values.
Let's go ahead and pass in true first then we can duplicate this line and we're going to pass in a string
like Andrew with this in place.
We now have our low dash module included and we're taking advantage of some of the functions it provides
we can run our project over inside of the terminal using the same command we've used in the past node
space app Dhananjay ass to run our file when we run the file.
We get our two prompts that we've started both files and we get false and then true false comes because
the Boolean is not a string.
And true comes up because Andrew is indeed a string so it passes the test of is string.
This is one of the many utility functions that comes bundled with low dash no load.
ASH can do a lot more than simple type checking.
It comes with a bunch of other utility methods we can take advantage of.
Let's go ahead and explore one more.
Before we wrap this video up back inside of the browser we can use Command F again to search for this
new one.
It is underscore dot you n i q now right here this is not the one you want so I'm going to click through
a few times until we get to the one I want over here in the Table of Contents.
We have underscored dot you and I q.
This is the one we want.
This unique method all it takes is an array and it returns that array with all duplicates removed.
That means if I had the same number a few times or the same string is going to go ahead and remove any
duplicates.
Let's go ahead and run this one to wrap this up.
Back inside out if we can add to this into our project.
I'm going to comment out our is string calls and replace it with a call to console log above the call
to cancel that log.
We're going to make a variable called filtered array.
This is going to be the array without the duplicate.
And what we're going to do is call after the equal sign underscore.
You and I.
Q Now as we know this takes an array.
And since we're trying to use the unique function we're going to pass in an array with some duplicates.
Go ahead and use your name twice as a string.
I'm going to use my name once followed by the number 1 followed by my name again.
Then I can use one two three and four.
Now if things go as planned we should get an array with all the duplicates removed which means we'll
have one instance of Andrew one instance of 1 and 2 3 4 which don't have duplicates.
The last thing to do is to print that using console dialog so we can view it inside of the terminal
right here.
I'm going to pass in the filtered array variable to our consul that lock statement.
From here we can go ahead and run our project inside of Node.
I'm going to use the up arrow key to run the last command.
Then I can press the enter key and right here.
You see we get our array with all duplicated removed.
We have one instance of the string.
Andrew one instance of the number one and then we have two three four.
Exactly what we expected.
The low dash utility really is endless.
There are so many functions that can be kind of overwhelming to explore at first but as you start creating
more Javascript and node projects you're going to find yourself solving a lot of the same problems over
and over again when it comes to sorting filtering or type checking.
And in that case it's best to use a utility like low dash to get that lifting done load ash is great
because one you don't have to keep rewriting your methods and to it is well-tested and it has been tried
in production.
If there are any issues they have been sorted out by now.
Now that you know how to use a third party module there is one more thing I want to discuss.
That is the node modules folder in general.
When you take your node project and you put it on get hub like we'll be doing later or you're copying
it around or sending it to a friend.
The node modules folder really shouldn't be taken with you.
The node modules folder contains generated code.
This is not code you've written.
And you should never make any updates to the files inside of node modules because there's a pretty good
chance they're going to get overwritten next time you install some modules.
In our case we've already defined the modules and the versions inside a package.
Jason because we use that handy safe flag this actually means we can delete the node modules folder
completely.
Now we can copy the folder and give it to a friend.
We can put it on get hub whatever we want to do when we want to get that node modules folder back.
All we have to do inside of the terminal is run NPM install without any module names or any flags NPM
install when ran without any names or flags is going to load in your package that Jason File grab all
of the dependencies and install them after running this command the node modules folder is going to
look exactly as it looked before we deleted it.
Now when you are using get and get hub instead of deleting the node modules folder you're just going
to ignore it from your repository.
If that means nothing to you that's fine.
We will be exploring the basics of get later but for now I wanted to let you know this because when
I add the lecture files to you to me I am not going to be including the node modules folder because
it takes up a lot of space and it's a pain to download.
It also gets generated differently depending on the version of NPM you install.
So it's best to always generate the node modules folder on your local machine.
That means when you download a zip from the lecture files you're going to on zip it navigate into the
project run NPM install.
Then you can run the code that you download it with that in place.
We are done.
We've explored a little bit about NPM how we can use NPM in it to generate a package that Jason File
and how we can install and use third party modules.
Now this is a process we're going to be going through a lot more throughout the course.
So if it still seems foreign or you're not quite sure why it's even useful I promise it will become
clear as we do more with our third party modules rather than just type checking or looking for unique
items in an array.
There's a ton of power behind the NPM community and we're going to be harnessing that to our fullest
as we make real world apps.
For now though that is it.
So stay tuned and I will see you next time.