The number one complaint I got about version 1 of this course was the fact that students had to restart
the app from the terminal every time they wanted to see the changes they just made inside of their text
editor.
Luckily there is a better way to do things in this video we're going to take a look at how we can automatically
restart our app as we make changes to the file.
That means if I change Andrew to Mike and say that it would automatically restart over in the terminal.
Now to do this we have to install a command line utility and we're going to do this using NPM to get
started.
We're going to go to Google Chrome and head over to NPM.
Jay ass at dot com just like we did previously and the module we're looking for is called node mine
mon node mine is going to be responsible for watching out for changes and restarting the app when those
changes occur.
Right here we can view the docs for gnomon as well as various things like current version numbers etc..
You can also see it's a really popular module with over 13000 downloads a day.
Now this module is a little different than the one we used in the last video low dash low Dash got installed
and added into our project package.
Jason File right here.
That means it went into our node modules folder and we were able to require it in our apt at jast file
gnomon however works a little differently it's a command line utility that gets executed from the terminal.
It's going to be a completely new way of starting our application and to install modules to be run from
the command line and we have to tweak the install command that we used in the last video.
For now we can start off much the same way though we're going to use NPM install just like we did in
the last video.
We're going to tape the name just like we did in the last video but instead of using the Save flag what
we're going to do is use the G flag which is short for global.
This installs gnomon as a global utility on your machine which means it's not going to get added to
your specific project and you're never going to require node one.
Instead you're going to be running the node on command from the terminal when we install this command.
It's going to go off to NPM fetch all of the code that comes with gnomon and that's going to add it
into the installation where node and NPM live on your machine outside of the project you're working
on.
This command could be executed from anywhere in your machine.
It does not need to be executed from the project folder since it doesn't actually update the project
at all.
With this in place though we now have a brand new command on our machine node on gnomon is going to
get executed just like node did where we type the command and then we type the file we want to start.
In our case app is the root of our project.
When you run it you're going to see a few things.
We're going to see a combination of our apps output along with no demand logs that show you what's happening
here you can see the version node using the files it's watching and the command it actually ran.
Now at this point it's waiting for more changes.
It already ran through the entire app and it's just going to sit here.
It's going to keep running until another change happens or until you shut it down inside out.
That means we can go ahead and make a few changes to our app.
Let's get started by changing Andrew to Mike and then we're going to go ahead and remove everything
else from the array leaving it just like this.
Now I'm going to be saving the file to pay attention to what happens in the terminal right here.
You can see the app automatically restarted and within a split second the new output is shown to the
screen.
You can see we now have our array with one item a string Mike.
And this is the real power of gnomon.
You can create your applications and it will automatically restart over inside of the terminal which
is super useful.
It's going to save you a ton of time and a ton of headaches.
You don't have to switch back and forth every time you make a small tweak.
This also prevents ton of errors where you are running a web server.
You make a change and you forget to restart that web server.
You might think your change didn't work as expected because the app is not working as expected.
But in reality you just never restarted the app for the most part we are going to be using node mom
throughout the course since it's super useful.
It's only used for development purposes which is exactly what we're doing on our local machine.
Later on in the course when we deploy our node apps to a real web server we won't be using gnomon but
gnomon is awesome for local development because it makes it that much easier.
That is it for this video.
Now it's time to start exploring how we can get input from the user to create our notes application
that's going to be the topic of the next few videos.
I am super excited to get started.
Before we do get started we're going to take a quick second to clean up a lot of the code we've already
written.
I'm going to remove all of the commented out code down below and up above where we have FS OS and low
dash.
I'm going to simply remove OS since we're not going to be using it for the project.
I'm also going to be adding a space between the third party and node modules and the files I've written.
I find this to be a good syntax that makes it a lot easier to quickly scan for either third party slash
known modules and modules that I've created and required down below.
Next up over in notes we're going to go ahead and remove the add function.
This was only added for demonstration purposes and we can go ahead and save both of these files and
gnomon is automatically going to restart.
Last but not least we can remove that.
Greetings itx tif file that was used to demonstrate how the FS module works and since we already know
how it works we can go ahead and wipe that file and last but not least we can always shut down gnomon
and using control-C.
Now we're back at the regular terminal and with this in place we are done it's time to move on figuring
out how we can get input from the user because that's how users are going to be able to create notes
remove notes and fetch their notes.
That is all coming up in the next several videos so stay tuned.
I will see you then