In this video you're going to learn how to get input from the user which is exactly what we need to
create the notes application.
If a user wants to add a note we need to know the notes title as well as the body of the note.
If they want to fetch a note we need to know the title of the note.
They want to fetch and all this information needs to come into our app and note apps they don't really
do anything cool until they do get this dynamic user input.
This is what makes your scripts useful and awesome.
Now throughout the course we're going to be creating node apps that get input from the user in a lot
of different ways.
We're going to be using socket IO to get realtime info from a web app.
We'll be creating our own API.
So other Web sites and servers can make Ajax requests to our app but in this video we're going to start
things off with a very basic example of how to get user input.
We're going to be getting input from the user inside of the command line.
That means when you run the app in the command line you'll be able to pass in some arguments those arguments
will be available inside of node and then we can do something with them like create a note delete a
note or return notes to kick things off.
Let's go ahead and run our app from the terminal.
We're going to run it pretty similar lead to how we ran in the past.
We're going to start with node.
I'm not using node Mansons we're going to be changing the input and then we're going to use app dot
J asked which is the file we want to run but then we can still type.
Other variables we can pass all sorts of command line arguments and we could have a comment and this
would tell the app what to do whether you want to add a note remove a note or list a note that might
look something like this.
This would add a note.
We could remove a note like this and we could list all of our notes using the list command.
Now when we run this command the app is still going to work as expected just because we passed in a
new argument doesn't mean our app is going to crash and we actually have access to this argument already.
We're just not using it inside of the application to access the command line arguments.
Your app was initialized with.
You're going to want to use that process object that we explored in the very first section of this course.
We can go ahead and log out all of the arguments using cancel that log to print them to the screen.
It's on the process object and the property we're looking for is arg.
The RV is short for arguments of vector or in the case of javascript it's more like an argument array.
This is going to be an array of all of the command line arguments passed in and we can use them to start
creating our application.
Take a moment to save apage Yes and then we're going to go ahead and rerun this file and right here
we have three items the first two are not particularly useful.
One that points to the executable for node that was used.
The second one points to the app file that was started in this case it was app dot.
Yes.
The third one though this is where our command line arguments start to come into play.
Right here we have our list showing up as a string.
And this is fantastic.
That means we can access that third item in the array and that is going to be the command for our note
application.
Let's go ahead and do that right now.
I'm going to make a variable called the command and set it equal to process dot R V and we're going
to grab that item in the third position which is the index of two.
Then we can go ahead and log that out to the screen by logging out command the string.
Then I'm going to go ahead and as the second argument passed in into the actual command that was used
and this is just a simple log to keep track of how the app is getting executed.
The cost of is going to come when we add if statements that do different things depending on that command.
Let's go ahead and create an if else block down below.
If the command equals add if that's the case we're going to go through the process of adding a new note.
Now as you notice we're not specifying the other arguments that are going to be necessary for that.
Like the title or the body we'll get to that in just a few years.
For now though if the command does equal add we're going to go ahead and use console log.
To print adding new note awesome and we can go ahead and do the exact same thing with a command like
list else if command equals the string list.
If the command does equal the string list we're going to go ahead and run this block of code using Konsole
dot log.
To print listing all notes we can also add an else clause if there is no command else console larg command
not recognized
perfect.
With this in place we can now rerun our app for a third time and this time around you see we have the
command equal to list and listing all notes shows up.
This means we were able to use our argument to run different code.
Notice that we didn't run adding you know and we didn't run command not recognized.
We could however switch this from list to add and in that case we're going to get adding new note printing
down below.
And if we run a command that doesn't exist like a read you can see command not recognized prints.
So far everything is working great.
We're able to get that input from the user.
What I'd like you to do is add two more else if clauses to are if block one is going to be for the read
command which will be responsible for getting an individual note back and another one called remove
is going to be responsible for removing the note.
All you have to do is add the else if statement for both of them.
And then just put a quick counsel dot log printing something like fetching note or removing note.
Take a moment to knock that out as your challenge for this video.
Once you add those two LCF clauses go ahead and run them both of them from the terminal and make sure
your log shows up.
If it does show up you are done.
You can go ahead and click play.
Take a moment to pause the video.
Knock that out and when you're done click Play
How to go.
Hopefully you were able to add those two LCF clauses and test things out from the terminal.
The first thing I'm going to do is add a ELSE IF for read I'm going to open and close my curly braces
and hit enter right in the middle.
So everything gets formatted correctly here.
I'm going to check if the command variable equals the string read in the future we're going to be calling
methods that update our local database with the notes.
But for now we're going to use console log to print reading.
Note perfect the next thing you need to do was at an ELSE IF clause that checks if the command equals
remove else if I'm going to open and close my condition.
And had entered just like I did before this time if the command equals remove We want to do something.
And in that case all we're going to do is use console log to print removing.
Note excellence.
And with this in place we are done.
We've added two new commands.
We can run over inside of the terminal and we can test those.
First up I'm going to run node apps out with the read command.
And here a reading note shows up and then I'm going to rerun the command.
This time I'm going to be using remove and when I do that removing note prints to the screen I'm going
to wrap up my testing by using a command that doesn't exist.
And when I run that you can see command not recognize shows up which is fantastic.
Now this is step one.
We now have support for various commands.
The next thing we have to figure out is how we're going to get more specific information for example.
Which note do you want to remove.
Which note do you want to read.
And what do you want the note text to be in the case of ADD.
This is all information we need to get from the terminal.
Now getting it is going to be pretty similar to what we did before and to show you what it looks like
we're going to be printing out the entire arc of the object once again using council log.
Process Dot are the over in the terminal.
We can now run a more complex command.
Let's say we want to remove a note using node opt out.
Yes remove and we're going to do that by its title.
We might use the title argument which looks like this.
Here we have two hyphens followed by the argument name which is title followed by the equals sign.
Then we can type or no title maybe the note title is secrets.
This is going to pass the title argument into our application.
Now there is a couple of different ways you could format this.
We can have title secrets like this.
We can have title equals secrets inside of quotes which is going to let us use spaces in the title or
we can remove the equal sign altogether and simply put a space no matter how you choose to format your
argument.
These are all valid ways to pass in the title.
This is Andrew with a quick update as you see here I am using double quotes when wrapping my string.
Now if you switch to single quotes it's not going to break on Linux or OSX but it is going to break
on Windows.
That means when you're passing in command line arguments like the title or the note body you're going
to want to wrap your strings when you have spaces in double quotes not single.
So if you are using Windows and you're getting some sort of unexpected behavior with your arguments
make sure you are using double quotes instead of single.
That should fix the issue.
For the moment I'm going to keep the equal sign and the quotes and rerun the command when I run the
command this time.
You can see we have our two arguments.
These are the arguments that we don't need.
We have our command which is the third one and we now have a new fourth string the title that is equal
to.
Secrets 2.
And this is great.
Our argument was successfully passed into the application.
The problem is that it's not very easy to use.
Here we have to parse out the key which is title and the value which is secrets too when we use the
command which is the third argument.
It was a lot easier to use inside of our app.
We simply pulled it out of the arguments array and we referenced it by using the command variable and
checking if it equaled add list read or remove things get a lot more complex as we use different styles
for passing in the arguments.
If we rerun the last command with a space instead of an equal sign which is perfectly valid our arguments
are right now looks completely different.
Here we have the title as the fourth item and we have the value which is secret to as the fifth which
means we have to add other conditions for parsing.
And this turns into a pain really quick which is why we are not going to do it.
We're going to use a third party module called yards in the next video to make parsing the command line
arguments effortless instead of having strings like this one or the one up above.
We're going to get an object where the title property equals the secrets to string that's going to make
it super easy to implement.
The rest of the notes application before we go let's take a quick moment to recap what we learned.
First up we learned that we can use command line arguments to pass data into our app inside of the app.
We can use process vi to grab that information and do something with it.
In the case of our command we run different code depending on the command the user wanted to use.
This is all done because process that our TVs automatically populated with all the command line arguments.
You don't have to do anything special to get them now parsing certain types of command line arguments
like key value pairs becomes a lot more complex which is why in the next video we're going to be using
yarns to do just that.
So stay tuned.
I will see you soon.