In this video we are going to use Yarg as a third party NPM manual to make the process of parsing a
much much easier.
It's going to let us access things like title and body information without needing to write a manual
parser.
This is a great example of when you should look for NPM module.
We're about to write some really boring code if we don't use a module.
It's much more productive for our node application to use a third party module that has been tested
and thoroughly vetted now to get started.
We're going to install the module then we'll add it into the project parsing for things like the title
on the body and we'll call all the functions that are going to get defined over and notes.
Yes.
If the command is add we'll call add note so on and so forth.
To get started we can go view the docs page for yards.
It's always a good idea to know what you're getting yourself into.
If you google.
It should be the first result.
Here we have the get home page for the Yards library no yards is a very complex library.
It has a ton of features for validating all sorts of input and it has different ways you can format
that input.
We are going to start with a very basic example although we will be introducing more complex examples
throughout this section.
For now though this is the docs and if you want to look at any other features that we don't discuss
in the section or you just want to see how something works.
We have talked about.
You can always find that here.
But we're going to do though is move into the terminal to install this module inside of our application
that's going to get done using NPM install followed by the module name.
Why a large Yes yards.
And in this case I'm going to use the at sign to specify a specific version of the module I want to
use in this case for point seven point 7.1 which is the most recent version at the time this video was
filmed throughout the course.
I will be using version numbers on some modules in case they change down the line.
I want to make sure the videos still work after you go through the videos.
You can always update to the latest versions of the modules to check it out.
There's no breaking changes if there is no breaking changes.
Great.
Stan the latest version if there's not.
Go ahead and revert.
For now though.
Go ahead and use a four point seven point one.
I'm going to add the save flag which as we know updates the package.
Jason File.
If I leave off the saved flag yards is going to get installed into the node modules folder.
But if we wipe that node modules folder later and run NPM install yours won't get reinstalled because
it's not listed in the package on Chaisson fine.
This is why we use the save flag.
And now that uninstalling yards we can move over into atom inside of apparat genius and get started
using it and the basics of yards.
The very core of its feature set is really simple to take advantage of.
The first thing we're going to do is require it up above.
Just like we did FS and lo dash lets make a constant and call it Yard's setting an equal to you guessed
it require yards.
From here we can go ahead and fetch the arguments as your EXE parses them.
It's taking the same process dot org V array but it's going behind the scenes and parsing it giving
us something that's much more useful than what node gives us up above just above my command variable.
We can make a concept called art the setting is equal to yards.
V Yarg Scott are vi is where the args library stores its version of the arguments that your app ran
with.
Now we can go ahead and print it out down below.
And this is going to let us take a look at process darg V and the yards are v variable and we can compare
them and see how yours differs for the command where we use cancel dialog to print process r v.
I'm going to make the first argument is string called process so we can differentiate it in the terminal.
We're going to call cancel that log.
Again the first argument is going to be the string yards and the second one will be the actual are the
variable which comes from Yorke's.
Now we can go ahead and run our app a few different ways and see how these two differ.
First up we're going to run node app.
J.S. with the add command and we can run this very basic example and we already know what the process
dot org VRA looks like.
The useful information is this third string inside of the array which is.
And down below on the other hand yardages gives us an object that looks very different.
Here we have the underscore property.
This is where commands like ad are stored.
If I were to add another command like add and I work out a modifier like encrypted you can see that
ad is the first argument and encrypted is the second.
Now so far yours really isn't shining.
This isn't much more useful than what we have up above where it really shines is when we start passing
in key value pairs like that title example we used in the last video I can set my title equal to secrets
that enter.
And this time around we get something much more useful up above.
We have a string that we would need to parse in order to fetch the value and the key down below.
We actually have a title property with a value of secrets and yards has built in parsing for all the
different ways you could specify this.
We can put a space after title and it still works just as it did before we could add quotes around secrets.
Adding another word like secrets from Andrew and it parses it correctly setting the title prop to the
string.
Secrets from Andrew.
This is where yours really shines.
It makes the process of parsing your arguments much much easier.
That means over inside of our app we can take advantage of that parsing calling the proper functions.
Let's take ad for example.
Once the ad command gets called We want to call a function defined in notes that's going to be responsible
for actually adding the note notes don't add a note it's going to get the job done.
And what do we want to pass to add note you want to pass in two things.
The title which is accessible on our the title as we saw here and the body are the dot body.
Currently these command line arguments title and body are required.
So technically the user could run the application without one of them which would cause it to crash.
But in the future it will be requiring both of these.
Now that we in this in place we can remove our console that live statement which was just a placeholder
and we can move into the Notes application inside of notes.
I'm going to wipe what we have so far since it was just a basic example and we're going to get started
by making a variable with the same name as the method we used over and after.
Yes no note and it's going to get set equal to an anonymous arrow function just like this.
Now this alone isn't too useful because we're not exporting the ad note function down below.
We can define a module that exports in a slightly different way.
In the past we added properties onto exports to export them.
We can actually define an entire object that gets set to exports.
And in this case we can set add note equal to the ADD note function defined up above now any six there's
actually a shortcut for this.
When you're selling an object attribute and a value that's a variable and they're both exactly the same.
You can actually leave off the colon and the value that this is identical.
Here we're setting an object equal to module that exports the object has a property add note which points
to the ADD note function above.
Once again this and this are identical inside of ESX we are going to be using the e-s six syntax for
everything throughout this course.
Now I can take my two arguments title and body and actually do something with them.
In this case we're not going to be modifying the database just yet although we are getting pretty close
for now.
But we're going to do is call console dot log adding note passing in the two arguments as the second
and third argument to console dot Lague title and body.
And now we're in a pretty good position to run the ad command with title and body and see if we get
exactly what we'd expect which is this console that live statement to print over in the terminal we
can start by running the app with the node then specify the file name we're going to use the ad command
which will run the appropriate function then we're going to pass and title setting an equal to secret
and we can pass in a body which is going to be our second command line argument setting that equal to
a string and since I'm going to have some spaces this is my secret right here we have specified three
things the command ad in the title argument which gets set to secret and to the body argument which
gets set to this is my secret if all goes well we'll get the appropriate log.
Let's run the command and right here you can see adding note.
We have secret which is the title.
And this is my secret which is the body and this log is the one we have to find right here which is
fantastic.
With us in place we don't have one of our methods set up and ready to go.
The next thing we're going to do is convert the other ones we have list.
We have read and we have remove.
Let's do one more together and then you'll do the other two by yourself.
Now the list command is right here.
I'm going to remove the console log statement and call notes dot get all at some point get all is going
to return all of the notes.
Now once again this is not wired up.
Now get all doesn't take any arguments since it's going to return all of the notes regardless of the
title the read command is going to require a title and remove will also require the title of the note.
You want to remove.
For now though we can create the get all function over inside of nodes.
We're going to go through that process again.
We're going to start by making a variable calling it get all and setting an equal to an arrow function
which we've used before we start with our arguments list.
Then we set up the arrow which is the equal sign and the greater than sign then we specify the statements
we want to run inside of our code block.
We're going to run a console log getting all notes.
The last step to the process after adding that semi-colon is going to be to add get all to the experts
here.
We can use get all just like this.
And what we have here is identical to this.
Remember in Essex if you have a property whose name is identical to the value which is a variable you
can simply remove the value variable and the column perfect.
And now that we have this in place and we've wired it up in app japes which I did not mean to just close.
We can go ahead and run things over inside of the terminal.
In this case we're going to run that list command node app dot J.S. list and right here you can see
at the bottom and getting all notes Prince to the screen.
And this is fantastic.
Now that we have this in place we can go ahead and remove the process log.
Since we no longer need that I am going to keep the yards log around since we will be exploring other
ways to use yards throughout the section.
What I'd like you to do as the challenge for this video is to create a method for the read command and
the remove command.
You're going to create inside of notes.
J.S. a get note function which is going to take the title then you can go ahead and use a council log
to print getting note and just print the title to make sure it works and you're going to do the same
thing for remove.
Right here you're going to call notes dot remove.
Note passing in the title of the note you want to remove.
And once again when you define the function go ahead and log out the title argument to make sure it
was passed in properly and then over in the terminal.
I want to run both of them passing in the title and making sure the log prints as expected Go ahead
and do this.
Pause the video knock it out.
Run both read and remove from the terminal to test your work and when you're done click play.
How'd you do.
Hopefully it didn't have too much trouble creating and calling both of those functions.
We're going to get started with the command for read first.
When the read command is used we want to call notes dot get no passing in the title.
Now the title is going to get passed in and parsed using yours which means we can use our TV title to
fetch it and that's all we have to do when it comes to calling a function.
The next step is to define get.
Note because currently it doesn't exist over inside of notes.
J.S. Right below.
All we can make a variable called Get No get know is going to be a function.
We're going to use the arrow function and it is going to take an argument it's going to take the note
title get note takes the title then and returns the body for that note inside of get note we can use
console like to print something like getting no followed by the title of the note you're going to fetch
which is going to be the second argument to console that.
Perfect.
That's the first one.
And we can go ahead and test it before we go on to the second one which is move over in the terminal.
We can use Noad apt just to run the file We're going to be using the new read command passing in a title.
I'm going to use a different syntax or title get set equal to the value outside of quotes.
I'm going to use something like accounts this is going to read the accounts note in the future and it's
going to print it to the screen.
For now though we get an error which is fantastic.
Getting an error is not the end of the world getting an error means you usually have a small typo or
you forgot one step in the process.
And what we're going to take a moment to do is figure out how to parse through these error messages
because what you get which is what I've highlighted here can be pretty daunting as you can see the first
line it shows you where the error occurred.
It's inside of our app js file and the number after the colon is the line on line 19.
It shows you the line and it shows you exactly where things went bad.
Type error notes don't get no is not a function it's telling you pretty clearly that the function you
tried to run get.
Note doesn't exist and now we can take this information and go debug our app.
Right here we see we call notes doc get note.
Everything looks great but when we move into notes.
Yes we realize that we never actually exported get.
No that is why when we try to call the function we get get.
Note is not a function because we never exported it.
All we have to do to fix that error message is export get.
Note.
Just like this.
When I save the file and rerun the app from the terminal.
Now we're going to get what we expect which is getting no followed by the title which is accounts and
that is how we can do bug our error messages error messages for the most part contain really useful
information.
Right here we have some useful information and down below.
We have a lot of useless information.
This is the stack trace it's all the code that's running to get to the point where the air happened.
For the most part the first couple lines are code that you've written and the other ones are internal
node code or third party modules.
In our case the first line of the stack trace is important.
It shows exactly where the error occurred.
When you get an error inside of your app which you totally will throughout the course.
Don't worry.
It's usually the result of a simple mistake in our case we simply forgot to export the function.
Now though the read command is working so we can move on to the last one which is going to be the remove
command.
I'm going to remove the console lock statement and call notes dot remove.
Note passing in the title which as we know is available under the dot title.
Next up we're going to define in the Remove note function over inside of our notes API file.
Right below.
Note var remove.
Nope never move.
No it is going to work much the same way as get note.
All it needs is the title it can use that information to find the note and remove it from the database.
This is going to be an arrow function that takes the title argument and for the moment we're going to
print the console that lock statement.
Removing note then at the second argument we're going to simply print that title back to the screen
to make sure that it's going through the process successfully this time around.
We're not going to forget to export or remove.
Note function.
We're going to define it right here.
Remove.
Note using the 6 syntax.
The last thing to do is to test it and make sure it works.
We can reload the last command using the up arrow key.
We can change your read to remove and that is all we need to do.
We're still passing in the title which is great because that is what remove needs.
When I run the command we get exactly what we expected.
Removing note prints to the screen and then we get the title of the note that we were supposed to be
removing which is accounts which looks great.
That is all it takes to use yards to parse your arguments.
Let's take a quick moment to recap what we learned.
We learned that parsing in process can be a real pain in the butt.
We would have to write a lot of manual code to parse out those hyphens the equal signs and the optional
quotes.
It's a real pain.
Yagis can do all of that for us and it puts it on a really simple object we can access.
Now here we use the R V object coming from yards to grab the title and here we use it to grab the body.
These are all the methods that we're actually going to be calling throughout the course.
Currently none of them are wired up.
But we now have a place to define all of that functionality for saving notes reading notes listing notes
and removing notes.
The last thing I want to do before we wrap this video up is switch how we fetch the command.
As we know the command is available in the underscore property as the first and only item which means
right here we can set command equal to r v then dot underscore.
Then we're going to use brackets to grab the first item in the array.
With this in place we now have the same functionality but we're using yagis everywhere.
And if I we're on the last command we can test that the functionality still works and it does command
remove shows up.
That is it for this one I will see you next time as we start filling out the individual functions.
We're going to take a look first at how we can use Jason to store our notes inside of our file system
that is coming up next so stay tuned.
I will see you soon.