Now that you know how to parse command line arguments using process are vi and yards you solve the first
piece of the puzzle.
For the notes application how do we get that unique input from the user.
The second piece of the puzzle is how do we store this information.
When someone adds a new note we want to save it somewhere preferably on the file system.
So the next time they try to fetch remove or read that note they actually get the note back to do this.
We're going to need to introduce something called Jason.
Now if you're already familiar with Jason you probably know it is super popular.
It stands for javascript object notation and it's a way to represent javascript arrays and objects using
a string.
Now why would you ever want to do that.
Well you might want to do that because strings are just text and that's pretty much supported anyway.
I can save Jason to a text file and then I can read it later parse it back into a javascript array or
object and do something with it.
That's exactly what we're going to take a look at in this video to explore Jason and how it works.
Let's go ahead and make a new folder inside of our project called Playground
throughout the course.
I'm going to create playground folders in various projects which stores simple one off of files that
aren't a part of the bigger application.
They're just a way to explore a new feature or learn a new concept.
In the playground folder we're going to make a file called Jason dot Jay ass.
This is where we can explore how Jason works to get started.
Let's make a very simple object.
We're going to make a variable called J setting and equal to an object and on that object.
For the moment we're just going to define one property name like it's equal to your first name.
I'm going to go ahead and set this one equal to Andrew.
Now let's assume we want to take this object and do something with it.
We want to do something like send it between servers as a string.
Save it to a text file or anything else to do that.
We're going to need to call one.
Jason Methot Let's take a moment to define a variable to store the result string.
Oh B.J. and we're going to set it equal to in uppercase.
Jason dot string ify s t r i n g f y.
Jason douching if I takes your object in this case the object variable and returns the Jasen string
of fied version.
That means the result stored in a string object is actually a string.
It's no longer an object.
We can take a look at that using Konsole that lock.
I'm going to use cancel that log twice.
First up we're going to use the type of operator to print the type of the string object to make sure
it actually is a string type of is an operator.
It gets typed like this in lowercase.
There is no camel casing.
Then you pass in the variable whose type you want to check.
Next up we can use council dot like to print out the contents of the string itself console.
Lague printing out the string Oby J var..
Perfect.
What we've done is we've taken an object converted into adjacent string and we're printing it out to
the screen over in the terminal.
I'm going to navigate into that playground folder for the moment.
It doesn't matter where you run the command but in the future it is going to matter that we are in the
playground folder.
So take a moment to navigate into it then we can use node to run our Jason J us file when we run the
file.
We see two things.
First we get our type which is a string and this is great because remember Jason is a string.
Next we get our object and it looks pretty similar to a javascript object but there are a few differences.
First up your Jason is going to have its attribute names automatically wrapped in double quotes.
This is a requirement of the adjacent syntax.
Next up you'll notice your strings are also wrapped in double quotes as opposed to single quotes.
Now Jason doesn't just support string values.
I could use an array.
I could have a boolean a number or anything else.
All of those types are perfectly valid inside of your jason.
In this case we have a very simple example where we have a name property and it's set to change.
Now this is the process of taking an object and converting it into a string.
Next up we're going to define a string and convert that into an object.
We can actually use in our app.
Let's get started by making a variable called Person string.
And we're going to set it equal to a string using a single quotes.
Since Jason uses double quotes inside of itself then we're going to define our Jason right here.
We're going to start by opening and closing some curly braces.
We're going to use double quotes to create our first attribute which will call name.
And we're going to set that attribute equal to Andrew.
That means after the closing quote We're going to add the colon then we're going to open and close double
quotes again and type the value.
Andrew Next up we can add another property after the value.
Andrew I'm going to create another property after the comma called age the age property is going to
get set equal to a number I can use my colon and then define the number without the quotes.
In this case 25 go ahead and define your Jason to look just like this.
You can go ahead and use your name and your age obviously but make sure the rest looks identical.
Now let's say we get this Jason from a server or we grab it from a text file.
Currently it's useless if we want to get the name value there is no good way to do that because we're
using a string.
So a person string
name doesn't exist.
We need to do is take this string and convert it back into an object to do this.
We're going to use the opposite of adjacent string of phi which is Jason dot parse.
Let's make a variable to store the result.
I'm going to create a person variable and it's going to get set equal to Jason dot parse passing in
as the one and only argument the string you want to parse.
In this case the person string which we defined up above.
Now what this does is it takes your Jason and it converts it from a string back into its original form
which could be an array or it could be an object.
In our case it converts it back into an object and we have the person object right here and we can prove
it's an object by using the type of operator.
I'm going to use counsel that Lague twice.
Just like we did above.
First up we're going to print the type of person.
Whoops.
That's type of not just type and sucking up.
We're going to print the actual person variable.
Cancel that log person.
Perfect with this in place we can now rerun the command.
I'm actually going to start gnomon I'm going to pass in Jason J.
Yes and right here you see we're working with an object which is great and we have our regular object
below.
We know it's an object because it's not wrapped in double quotes.
The values don't have any quotes and we use single quotes for Andrew which is valid in javascript but
it's not valid in Jason and thus the entire process of taking an object converting it to a string and
then taking the string and converting it back into the object.
And this is exactly what we're going to be doing in the Notes app.
The only difference is we're going to be taking this string and storing it in a file then later on we're
going to be reading that string from the file using Jason parse to convert it back to an object with
the basics in place.
Let's go ahead and take it just one step further.
What I'd like to do is actually store the string in a file.
Then I want to read the contents of that file back using the FS module and printing some properties
from it.
That means we're going to need to convert the string which we get back from FS dot.
Read files sink into an object using Jason Dopp parts.
Let's go ahead and comment on all the code we have so far and start with a clean slate.
I am going to leave it up there though as a reminder of the various methods we've introduced throughout
this video.
First up let's go ahead and load an FS.
The Konst FS is going to get set equal to require And we're going to require the FS module which we've
used in the past.
The next thing we're going to do is define that object.
This is the one that's going to be stored inside of our file and this one is going to be read back and
parsed.
This is going to be a variable called original note and I'm calling it original note because later on
we're going to load it back in and we'll call that variable.
Note Now the original note is going to be a regular javascript object with two properties.
We're going to have that title property which will set equal to some title and we're going to have that
body property which will set equal to some bàn.
The next step that you are going to need to do is take original note and create a variable called Original
no string and set that variable equal to the adjacent value of the object we defined above.
That means that you're going to need to use one of the two adjacent methods we used previously in this
video.
Now once you have that original note string variable we can go ahead and write a file to the file system
and I'll write that line for you fs dot or write file sync write file sync which we used before.
Takes two arguments.
The first one is going to be the file name.
And since we're using Jason it's important to use the Jasen file extension.
I'm going to call this one notes.
Jason and the text content is going to be that original note string which is not yet defined but will
be defined once you fill this line out and this is the first step to the process this is how we're going
to write that file into the playground fold.
The next step to the process is going to be to read out the contents parse it using the Jason method
above and print one of the properties to the screen to make sure it's an object.
In this case we're going to print the title.
The first step is going to be to use a method we haven't used yet.
We're going to use the read method available on the file system module to read the contents.
Let's make a variable called note string the note string is going to get set equal to FS.
Read file sync.
Now read file saying is similar to write file S..
Except it doesn't take the text content since it's getting the text content back for you.
In this case we just specified the first argument which is the file name.
Notes dot Jason.
Now that we have the string it's going to be your job to take that string.
Use one of the methods above and convert it back into an object.
You can call that variable.
Note Next up down below.
The only thing left to do is test that things are working as expected.
By printing using council Lague the type of note
then below that will use council that log to print the title note dot title.
Your job for this video is going to be to make these two things work by filling out these two lines.
Both original note string you have to make that bearable and the note variable.
Both are going to require a call to a Jasen method.
Now over in the terminal you can see I saved the file in a broken state and it crashed.
That's expected when you're using node mon.
So take a moment pause the video.
Knock this out and click play.
If you've done things correctly you should be able to see that the type of is an object and that note
title equals some title.
You should also see a brand new file on the playground folder.
Go ahead and open it up and take a look at what you got.
Knock it out then go ahead and click play.
The first thing I'm going to do is fill out this original note string.
It's going to be a variable called the original note string and we're going to set it equal to the return
value from Jason docstring ify.
Now we know Jason docstring a fight takes our regular object and it converts it into a string.
In this case we're going to take the original note object and convert that into a string.
The next line which we already have filled out is going to save that Jason value into the file notes.
Jason then we read that value out and the next step is going to be to create the note variable var.
Note will get set equal to Jason dot parce.
Jason parce takes the string Jason and converts it back into a regular javascript object or array depending
on whatever you save.
Here we're going to pass in a note string which we're getting from the file with this in place we are
now done.
When I save the file gnomon is going to automatically restart and we would expect to not see an error.
Instead we're expecting that we're going to see the object type as well as the note title.
And here we go right over here inside of the terminal.
We have an object and some title printing to the screen.
With this in place we are now done.
We successfully completed the challenge.
This is exactly how we are going to save our notes when someone adds a new note.
We're going to use this code to save it when someone wants to read their note.
We're going to use this code to read it.
Now what if someone wants to add and no that's going to require us to first read all of the notes then
we're going to modify the notes array.
Then we're going to use the code above to save the new array back into the file system.
If you open up that notes Jason file you can see right here we have our Jason code inside of the file
and Jason is actually a file format that supported by most text editors.
So I actually already have some nice syntax highlighting built in.
Now in the next video we're going to be filling out the ad note function using the exact same logic
that we'd just use inside of this video.
So let's take a quick second to recap.
First up Jason is nothing more than a string that kind of looks like a javascript object with the notable
differences being that it uses double quotes instead of single quotes and all of your property names
like in name and age in this case require quotes around them.
Now when you want to create some Jason you can do that using a regular javascript object passing it
into the Jason docstring a Find method that takes your object and converts it to Jason string.
When you have adjacent string and you want to convert it back into an object you simply take that string
and you pass it into Jason dot.
Parse this returns an object whose properties you can access.
With this in place we are now ready to move on to the next video and start really filling out the functionality
for the Notes app.
I am super excited to get started so stay tuned.
I will see you next time.