In the last video you learn how to work with Jason inside of no genius.
And as we know this is the exact format we're going to be using for the notes application.
When you first run a command will load in all the notes that might already exist.
Then we'll run the command whether it's adding removing or reading notes.
And finally if we've updated the array like we will when we add and remove notes we're going to save
that new notes back into the Jason File.
Now this is all going to happen inside of ADD.
Note the function we define in notes.
Yes.
And we already wired up this function in the past we ran the app ad command and this function executed
with the title and body arguments.
Since we already have that wired up I'm going to go ahead and remove the Consul that log statement and
we can start filling this one out to get started the first thing I want to do is create a variable called
the notes and for the moment we're going to set it equal to an empty array just like this using our
square brackets now that we have the empty array we can go ahead and make a variable called note which
is the individual name.
This is going to represent the new notes on that note we're going to have the two properties you probably
already expected a title and a body now a title can get set equal to the title variable but as we know
inside of six we can simply remove it when both values on the same title and body right here.
Now we have the know and we have the notes array.
The next step in the process is going to be to add the note to the notes array notes dot.
Push is going to let us do just that.
The push method on an array lets you pass in an item which gets added to the end of the array.
And in this case we're going to pass in the note object.
So we have an empty array.
We are one item and now we push it in.
Which means we have an array with one item.
The next step in the process is going to be to update the file.
Now we don't have a file in place but we can load an ass and start creating one up above.
Let's go ahead and load in FS.
I'm going to create a concept called FS and set it equal to the return result from require.
And we're going to require the FS module which is a core node module so there is no need to install
it using NPM and with this in place we can take advantage of each ass down inside of ADD.
Note Right after we push our item onto the notes array we're going to call FS dot right.
File sync which we've used before we need to pass in two things the file name.
I'm going to call this one notes Heinsohn data dot Jason.
And then we're going to pass in the content we want to save which in this case is going to be the string
of side notes array which means we can call Jason docstring ify
passing in notes.
Now we could have broken this out into its own variable and referenced the variable here.
But since we're only going to be using it in one place I find this is the better solution.
Now at this point when we add a new note it's going to update the notes data Jason File which will be
created on the machine since it does not exist.
And the note will sit inside of it.
Now it's important to note.
Currently every time you add a new note it's going to wipe all existing ones because we never load in
the existing ones.
But we can get started testing that this works as expected.
I'm going to save the file and over inside of the terminal we can run this using node app.
J.S. since you want to add a note we are going to be using that ad command which we set up.
Then we're going to specify our title and our body.
The title can get set equal to something like secret and for the body I'm going to go ahead and set
it equal to the string some body here.
Excellent.
Now when we run this command from the terminal we're going to see what we expect a couple of the file
commands we added.
We see the command ad was executed and we have our Yard's arguments right here.
Everything looks great.
The title in the body do show up back inside of Adam.
We also see we have a new notes hyphen and data Jason File and right here we have our note with the
title secret and the body.
Some body here.
And this is fantastic.
This is the first step in wiring up that ad note function.
We have an existing notes file and we do want to take advantage of these notes as notes already exist.
We don't want to simply wipe them every time someone adds a new note.
That means up above at the beginning of the add a note function we're going want to go ahead and fetch
those notes.
I'm actually going to do it right here below where I find the notes and no variable inside of here.
We're going to use FS dot Reed file sync which we've already explored.
This is going to take the file name in our case notes hyphen data dot Jason.
Now we are going to want to store the return value from read file sync on a variable.
I don't recall that variable notes string.
Since this is the string version we haven't passed it through Jason dump parts then and down below.
I can set notes the variable we defined up above equal to the return value from Jason dot parse.
Jason parce is going to take the string from the file we read and it's going to parse it into an array.
Right here we can pass in notes string just like this awesome.
With this in place adding a new no is no longer going to remove all of the notes that were already there.
We have a note with the title of secret and a body of some body here.
I'm going to use the up arrow key to load in the last command and I'm going to navigate over to the
title and change it to secret to end or rerun the command this time around.
You can see we now have two notes inside of our file.
We have an array with two objects.
The first one has the title of secret and the second one has the title of secret to which is brilliant.
Now there is a problem here.
If the notes data file does not exist which it won't.
When the user first runs that command I'm going to go ahead and delete it to show you what happens.
The program is going to crash.
We can prove this by simply rerunning the last command after deleting the note data.
Jason File right here.
You can see we're actually getting a javascript error.
No such file or directory exists.
It's trying to open up the notes data Jason File but without much success to fix this we're going to
use a try catch statement from javascript which hopefully you've seen in the past.
If you haven't we're going to go over it really quick to create a try catch.
All you do is you type try.
Which is a reserved keyword and then you open and close a set of curly braces inside.
Here is the code that you're going to run.
This is the code that may or may not throw an error down below.
You're going to specify the catch block.
Now the catch block is going to take an argument an error argument and it also has a code block that
runs this code is going to run if and only if one of your errors try actually occurs.
So if we load the file using read file sync in the file exists that's fine catches never going to run.
If it fails catch will run and we can do something to recover from that error.
With this in place all we're going to do is move these two lines into try.
That's it.
Nothing else needs to happen.
We don't need to put any code in catch although you do need to define the catch block.
Now let's take a look at what happens.
The first thing that happens is we create our static variables.
Nothing special there.
Then we try to load in the file.
If this fails that is fine because we already defined notes to be an empty array and if the file doesn't
exist and it fails then we probably want an empty array for notes anyways because clearly there are
no notes.
There's no file.
Next up we're going to parse that data into notes.
There is a chance this fails if there's invalid data in the notes hyphen data.
Jason File.
So these two lines.
They could have problems and by putting them in TRY CATCH we're basically guaranteeing that the program
isn't going to work unexpectedly even if the file doesn't exist or if it does exist but it contains
corrupted data.
With this in place we can now save notes and rerun that last command.
Note I do not have the notes data file in place when I run the command.
We don't see any errors.
Everything seems to run as expected and when I visit Adam you can see the notes data file does indeed
exist and the data inside of it looks great.
This is all we need to do to fetch the notes update the notes with the new no and finally save the notes
to the screen.
Now there is still a slight problem with ADD and note.
Currently add note.
It allows for duplicate totals.
I could already have a note in the adjacent file with the title of secret.
I could come along and try to add a new note with the title of a secret and it's not going to throw
an error.
What I'd like to do is make the title unique so if there's already a note with that title it's going
to throw an error letting you know to create a note with a different title.
The first step to that process is going to be to loop through all of the notes after we load them in
and check if there are any duplicates.
If there are duplicates or not you get a call.
These two lines.
If there is no duplicates then it's fine.
We will call both of these lines updating the notes data file.
Now we're going to be refactoring this function down the line.
Things are getting a little wonky and a little out of control but for the moment we can add this functionality
right into the function.
Let's go ahead and make a variable called duplicate notes duplicate notes is going to eventually store
an array with all of the notes that already exist inside of the notes array that have the title of the
note you're trying to create.
Now this means that the duplicate notes array has any items that's bad.
That means the note already exists and we should not add the note this is going to get set equal to
a call to notes which is our right of notes dot shelter filter is an array method that takes a callback.
We're going to use an arrow function and that callback is going to get called with the argument.
In this case it's going to be the singular version.
If I have an array of notes it's going to get called with an individual note.
This function gets called once for every item in the array and you have the opportunity to return either
true or false.
If you return True it's going to keep that item in the array which will eventually get saved in two
duplicate notes if you return false.
The new array it generates it's not going to have that item inside of it.
All we want to do is return true if the titles match which means we can return if Note dot title triple
equals title.
If they are equal then this is going to result in true.
And the item will be kept in the array which means there are duplicate notes if the titles are not equal
which is most likely the case that's going to result in false and duplicate notes will be empty.
Now we can simplify this a little more and using aero functions aero functions actually allow you to
remove the curly braces if you simply have one statement like we do here.
I'm going to go ahead and copy this statement to the clipboard.
Excluding the return key word and the semi-colon then what I'm going to do is delete everything from
the closing curly brace to the opening curly brace right here.
I can paste in my statement.
This is perfectly valid.
Using E.S. six era functions you have your arguments on the left you have your arrow and on the right
you have one expression.
The expression doesn't take a semicolon and it's automatically returned as the function result.
This means the code we have here is identical to the code we had earlier only it's much simpler and
it only takes up one line.
Now that we have this in place we can go ahead and check the length of duplicate notes.
If the length of duplicate notes is greater than zero that means we don't want to save the note because
a note already exists with that title.
If it is zero we're going to go ahead and save the note.
If duplicate notes
dot length is equal to zero here inside of the if condition we're comparing the notes length with the
number 0 if they are equal then we do want to go ahead and push for the note onto the notes array and
save the file.
I'm going to cut these two lines and paste them right inside of the if statement.
If they're not equal that's OK too.
In that case we're going to go ahead and do nothing with this in place we can now save our file and
test this functionality out.
We have our notes data file and that already has a note with a title of secret to.
Let's rerun the last command to try to add a new note with that same title.
You run the command.
We head back into our Jason File and you can see right here we still just have one note and this is
fantastic.
Now all the titles inside of our application are going to be unique.
So we can use these titles to fetch notes and delete notes.
Let's go ahead and test real quick that other notes can still be added.
I'm going to change the title from secret to top secret run that command.
And over here inside of our notes data file you can see both notes show up which is awesome.
And that is it for this video.
In this one we filled out the ad note function as I mentioned we are going to be doing some refactoring
since this code which loads the file and this code which saves the file they're going to be used in
most of the functions down below.
But for now everything works great.
We're able to add notes using the command line and we're able to save those notes into a Jasen file.
That is it for this one I will see you next time where we do that refactoring.
From there we'll be able to quickly fill out get all get no end remove note because we'll have those
reusable functions that we can take advantage of Seah soon.